<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The angel of the Church of Ephesus no bishop of Ephesus, distinguished in order from, and superior in power to a presbyter. As it was lately delivered in a collation before the Reverend Assembly of divines. By Constant Jessop Minister of the Word at Fifeild in Essex. Imprimatur Charles Herle.</title>
            <author>Jessop, Constantine, 1601 or 2-1658.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1644</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 218 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 37 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A87575</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing J699</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E42_22</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R11787</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99859130</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99859130</idno>
            <idno type="VID">111196</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A87575)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 111196)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 8:E42[22])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The angel of the Church of Ephesus no bishop of Ephesus, distinguished in order from, and superior in power to a presbyter. As it was lately delivered in a collation before the Reverend Assembly of divines. By Constant Jessop Minister of the Word at Fifeild in Essex. Imprimatur Charles Herle.</title>
                  <author>Jessop, Constantine, 1601 or 2-1658.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[6], 65, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by G. M. for Christopher Meredith at the Signe of the Crane in Pauls Church-yard,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1644.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Errata: p. 65.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "Aprill 13th".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
                  <note>Includes bibliographical references in marginal notes.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Church polity --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  Church history --  17th century --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-12</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-12</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:111196:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE ANGEL OF THE Church of Epheſus NO BISHOP OF EPHESVS, Diſtinguiſhed in Order from, and ſuperior in Power to a PRESBYTER.</p>
            <p>As it was lately delivered in a Collation before the Reverend Aſſembly of Divines.</p>
            <p>By <hi>Constant Jeſſop</hi> Miniſter of the Word at Fifeild in <hi>Eſſex.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Imprimatur</hi> CHARLES HERLE.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>G. M.</hi> for <hi>Chriſtopher Meredith</hi> at the Signe of the Crane in <hi>Pauls</hi> Church-yard. 1644.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:111196:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:111196:2"/>
            <head>TO THE RIGHT WORSHIPFVLL WILLIAM TWISSE, D<hi rend="sup">r</hi> in Divinitie, the Reverend &amp; Lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned <hi>Prolocutor,</hi> and to the reſt of the Religious and Grave Divines of this preſent Aſſembly, ſummoned by the authoritie of the Lords and Commons in Parliament.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Right Reverend and honoured Fathers and Brethren,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Never thought or intended to appeare in print in this learned and criticall age, being conſcious to my ſelf of mine own inſufficiencies: I ſpeak it not in an humble arrogancie, as the Orator obſerved ſome did write treatiſes againſt vain-glory, and then in a vain-glorious oſtentation put their names thereto. Muchleſſe ſhould I have pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumed to handle this controverſie, which hath been ſo fully agita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by others both at home and abroad. Not only by thoſe amongst us, who have diſtaſted the Hierarchicall frame of government, whoſe arguments have been by the Prelates anſwered for the moſt part no other way then by ſuſpenſions, ſilencings, deprivations, and proceedings againſt them as diſturbers of the Churches peace, and contemners of the commands of Authoritie: but alſo by almoſt all the Divines of note in the Reformed Churches, in their Pole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>micall diſsertations against Papists, out of whoſe Magazine our Hierarchiſts have borrowed thoſe weapons whereby they defend their own authority, and oppoſe their enemies; as is evident to any that ſhall compare the writings of the one and of the other, and (to ſay nothing of this as objected by the good old Non-con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formitans to the Patrons of Prelacie) is acknowledged by the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts
<pb facs="tcp:111196:3"/>themſelves, witneſſe that ſhort marginall Annotation of the Rhemists,<note place="margin">In <hi>Iohn</hi> 20.17.</note> 
               <hi>The Proteſtants otherwiſe denying this preemi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nence of</hi> Peter, <hi>yet to uphold their Archbiſhops do avouch it againſt Puritans.</hi> The courſe of my ſtudies when once I became a Smatterer in Divinitie, was bent another way then to the hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling of Controverſies. My principall and chiefeſt aime being this, that I might through Gods bleſsing on mine endevours be fitted for a Paſtorall employment, whenſoever the Lord in his due time ſhould call me thereunto. Wherein I deſire in humility and thank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſse to ſay with <hi>S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> PAUL,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.10.</note> 
               <hi>By the grace of God, I am what I am.</hi> As for this controverſie in particular, though I had ſome reaſon to have pried into it, in regard of my fathers ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rings more then once under the Prelates, in whoſe deprivation I and the rest of his poſteritie have had our ſhare of ſufferings alſo; yet knowing mine own inabilities to wade through it, wanting time in regard of other ſtudies more neceſſarie for the fitting of me for that calling wherin I was, and obſerving my fathers own te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>perature &amp; carriage, who forbare diſcourſing of it in private, or mentioning, much leſſe handling of it in publike, meerly on this ground, that he might fulfill his miniſtery in that remote, barren, (in reſpect of the Word) rude, and ignorant corner of <hi>Wales,</hi> to which the Lord by his providence removed him, I did alſo for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beare the ſtudying of it. The practiſes of the Prelates which cauſed ſuch commotions in <hi>Scotland</hi> at first, and in the iſſue the abjura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Prelacie; the proceedings againſt <hi>D<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Baſtwick</hi> here in England for his <hi>Flagellum Latiatium epiſcoporum,</hi> and thoſe high challenges which were made in the <hi>Star-chamber</hi> Speeches about that time, did firſt cauſe me to enquire into that tenure of Divine right, by which our Biſhops laid claim to their Preeminence. The Oath in the Canons which came forth after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward did provoke me to ſet to the work a little cloſer; which yet I entred on only for my own private information and ſatisfaction, and after the conſidering of ſome places of Scripture, I addreſſed
<pb facs="tcp:111196:3"/>my ſelf to Biſhop <hi>Halls</hi> Treatiſe on that ſubject, conceiving that in him, being the lateſt that did write, and withall a man of note in the Church, I ſhould find the ſubſtance, ſtrength and ſinewes of all thoſe arguments which could be produced in that cauſe. Whom when I did peruſe, the more I looked into his treatiſe, the further off I was from receiving ſatisfaction by him in that Tenure of Divine right, and from ſubſcribing to his aſſertions. Hereupon for my own private uſe I ſet down ſome ſhort marginall animad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſions (and to ſpeak the truth, as farre as I am able to judge, there is roome enough in the margent to anſwer the whole booke) divers of which are now at the deſire of ſome godly and learned members of your Aſſembly preſented to publike view. Sundry other Collections I had once, but <hi>S<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Arthur Aſtons</hi> upholders of the Proteſtant Religion, finding my papers, when they rifled my houſe at <hi>Reading</hi> of what they could, ſoon made an end of them by fire, and with them of ſome Treat ſes of my Fathers, in this and other arguments, which (in regard of that employment in the Ministery which lay on me whilſt I was in thoſe parts) I had not read over. Being thus driven from my habitation, and by loſse of my Papers and Manuſcripts diſabled from dealing in that con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troverſie, I had quite laid aſide the thoughts of it, untill that com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming before a Committee of your Aſsembly, according to an order of the houſe of Commons; I was by the Chairman of that Commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tee appointed to handle before you this Text, and controverſie out of it. Which I perſwade my ſelfe was done rather by way of Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bation then out of any deſire of Information from me, who am far more fit to be informed, and to receive, then to give information or ſatisfaction. Being thus eaſt on a neceſsity of reviving my for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer notions, and reviewing my marginall animadverſions with ſome other obſervations (which I had left) I undertook the taske, and preſented before you thoſe collections and arguments, which you were pleaſed immediately to call for. Let that I beſeech you, Fathers and Brethren, now find a ſecond, which found a former
<pb facs="tcp:111196:4"/>acceptance at your hands, and unto acceptation vouchſafe to adde a Patronage. Something I have indeed now added which was not in my former papers delivered, which I have done partly by the intimation of him by whoſe appointment I firſt did enter on the diſcuſsing of this queſtion; partly becauſe I ſaw the great confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence of the Biſhop with whom I principally deale in this vexati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous diſpute, whoſe grounds I held it in ſome reſpect neceſſary to conſider and examine. If in theſe papers there be any thing which may be ſubſervient to the glory of God, and his great work which he hath in hand, I have my deſire, and ſhall therein rejoyce, deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring to returne all to him from whom every good gift proceeds. Give me leave to cloſe my Dedication with the ſame petitions which cloſed my Sermon in your Aſſembly. The God and Father of our Lord Ieſus Christ the Father of mercies grant that his Spirit of peace and truth may be the Preſident of your Aſſembly, that the peace of God may rule in your hearts whereunto ye are called in one body, and nothing may be done amongst you through ſtrife, vain-glory or contention, but ye may ſeek the truth, and ſpeake the truth in love; that ſo through his bleſsing on your en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavours, ſtudies, conferences, meditations, the breaches may be made up which are in the Church, and the Lord in his due time heale the breaches of our Land, Kingdome, and Nation, which are exceedingly ſhaken; which is the hearty deſire, and daily prayer of</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>Fifeild, <date>
                     <hi>March</hi> 6. 1643.</date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>The meaneſt of your Fellow-helpers in the work of the Lord, <hi>Constant Jeſſop.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:111196:4"/>
            <head>THE Angel of the Church OF EPHESVS NO BISHOP of Epheſus, &amp;c.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>REVEL. 2.1.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>To the Angel of the Church of Epheſus, write.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T is not unknowne unto you, Reverend and beloved Fathers and Brethren, what vexati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous diſputes have been between the Prela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſts and Presbyterians concerning the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels mentioned in the Inſcription of this, and the other Epiſtles.<note n="a" place="margin">Sermon prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched at Lam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beth, <hi>Apr.</hi> 17. 1608.</note> D<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>Downham</hi> hath undertaken to prove the Angels to be Dio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſan Biſhops, and to juſtifie their function as lawfull and of divine inſtitution and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probation: but his<note n="b" place="margin">
                  <hi>Gerſom Bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cer, diſſert. de gub. eccl.</hi> An Anſwer to D<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                  <hi>Downham</hi> imprinted, <hi>an.</hi> 1609. A reply to D<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                  <hi>Downhams</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence imprin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, <hi>an</hi> 1013. The Dioceſans triall by M. <hi>Paul Baines,</hi> an. 1611.</note> Refuters both in Latine and Engliſh have (as I conceive with ſubmiſſion to better judgements) made it evident that notwithſtanding the Doctors bold adventure—</p>
            <p>— <hi>Magnis tamen excidit auſis,</hi> he hath come ſhort of his undertakings. Yea ſome of the members of this grave and lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned Aſſembly have vindicated this place from thoſe challenges which the humble Remonſtrant made unto it, by it to uphold the tottering cauſe of Prelacy. A cauſe which not long agone in <hi>Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> and lately in the Parliament of <hi>England,</hi> and amongſt you
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:111196:5"/>hath been, and ſtill is <hi>cauſa conclamata.</hi> I doubt not but you are ſufficiently ſatisfied in conſcience and judgement, otherwiſe you would not in ſo ſolemne a manner have vowed and covenanted with the Lord the extirpation of that Prelaticall forme of Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. It may be the Prelates themſelves ſee their owne ruine ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proaching, and that the down-fall of their honour is at hand, in which regard being either not willing, or not able by Scripture and force of argument to uphold it, they will now try whether it may be defended by the dint of ſword. As if they were the Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſours of thoſe Prelates mentioned by<note n="c" place="margin">Quibus adjice novum eleemo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſynae modum, quod in mercena<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rios m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>lites, equites &amp; pedites, borum plurima conſumuntur ad pugnas inter Chriſti fideles con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citandas &amp; continuè nutrien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>das, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t eos ſuae tandem ſubjice<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re valeant poteſtati. <hi>Defer ſ. pac. part. 2. cap. 24. pag. 358.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Marſilius Patavinus,</hi> who found out <hi>novum eleemoſynae modum, a new kinde of almes to expend thoſe meanes which were given them for hospitalitie and charitie to the poor, in the maintainance of ſouldiers, troops of horſes, and companies of foot, to the raiſing and proſecuting of warres between Christians, that ſo they might at length ſubject them to their tyrannicall power:</hi> Or elſe the ſonnes of that Martiall Pope<note n="d" place="margin">
                  <hi>Ealaeus in Iul.</hi> 2. cited by D<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                  <hi>Abbots</hi> 2. part of def. of the <hi>Ref. Cathol.</hi> p. 11.</note> 
               <hi>Julius</hi> the ſecond, who finding that his Buls and Excommunications would not prevaile, went in his own perſon to warre againſt the French King, and croſſing the river <hi>Tiberis,</hi> caſt <hi>Peters</hi> keyes into the ſtreame with indignation, being reſolved to try whether <hi>Pauls</hi> ſword would helpe him.</p>
            <p>I am not now to follow them, or lead you into the fields where trumpets ſound, troops are muſtered, and inſtruments of death to fly abroad, but to enquire (by your appointment) whether the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcription of this and other Epiſtles afford any ſolid argument for the pretended preeminence and ſuperioritie of a Biſhop in Order, Office, and Power of Juriſdiction above a Presbyter. A late Patron of Epiſcopacie is ſo confident, that he tels us,<note n="e" place="margin">Biſhop <hi>Hall,</hi> Epiſc. by divine right. <hi>p.</hi> 121.</note> 
               <hi>All the ſhifts in the world cannot elude it;</hi> that S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
               <hi>John was by the Spirit of God commanded to direct his ſeven Epiſtles to the Biſhops of thoſe ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven famous Churches, by the name of ſo many Angels.</hi> And the<note n="f" place="margin">Franc. à Sanct. clara Apol. ep<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſ c. <hi>5.</hi> p <hi>62.</hi> Argumentum de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niq<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>iſiud apud ortho. loxos non minus frequens quam efficax, de Epiſtolis Ioaxnis in Apocalypſi, quas ad ſeptem I ccleſiarum A ſiaticarum Angelos, ſeu Epiſcopos ſcripſit, originem ſaltem Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtolicam invictè dabit.</note> Romiſh Apologiſt for Biſhops is as confident as their Engliſh Patron, for he hath very boldly delivered it, that <hi>the argument drawn from this place will invin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cibly prove their originall to be at least Apoſtolicall.</hi>
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:111196:5"/>You heare their poſitions. Let us now conſider what juſt ground there is for this their great confidence.</p>
            <p n="1">1. The name <hi>Angel</hi> doth not import any ſuch eminencie of Order or Superioritie of power as our Prelates plead for, and would fain wreſt from the words of the Text. You know, Reverend and Beloved, that <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Angel</hi> is a name of Office not of Order, a title importing Dutie not Superioritie in Power. It ſignifieth a Meſſenger, and in point of Embaſſage all that are Gods Miniſters (unleſſe they have an immediate call from God, and infallible inſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, neither of which I conceive our Prelates will challenge to themſelves) are equall. They are all by their place and Office<note n="g" place="margin">Mal. 2.7.</note> 
               <hi>Meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſengers of the Lord of hosts.</hi> It is their dutie to<note n="h" place="margin">Act. 20.27, 20.</note> 
               <hi>declare the whole counſell of God, and keep back nothing which is profitable:</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>,<note n="i" place="margin">2 Cor. 5.19.</note> 
               <hi>We are Embaſſadours for Christ,</hi> ſaith the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle of himſelf, and all thoſe which are entruſted with the diſpenſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Goſpel. And from this their function they have their denomination<note n="k" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> euim utru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan>, ſignificat &amp; ſenem, &amp; legatum, teſte Scapula.</note> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. This name of Office, <hi>Angel,</hi> the Lord is pleaſed here to make uſe of rather then any other, for this reaſon as I conceive; Though the whole Scripture be the <hi>Epiſtle of the Almightie God unto his creature,</hi> as<note n="l" place="margin">Regiſt. ep. lib. <hi>4.</hi> epiſt. <hi>40.</hi> ad Theod. Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cum.</note> 
               <hi>Gregorie</hi> ſpeaks; yet here are now ſpeciall Letters to the Churches from the Lord Jeſus Chriſt, and therefore his Amanuenſis S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
               <hi>John</hi> is commanded to direct them <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, To the Angel or Meſſenger, to him that is the<note n="m" place="margin">Jer. 15.19.</note> 
               <hi>mouth</hi> of Jeſus Chriſt to interpret and declare his will. The dire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction is thus ſet down indefinitely, not pointing out any ſingular or individúall perſon, to give us to underſtand that whoſoever he be that is <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> by his Place and Office, an Angel or Meſſenger, it is his dutie to declare the will of the Lord Jeſus Chriſt in the follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing particulars to the Church. Let this little (which, as hath been obſerved, ſets forth the Function of that Perſon which is inveſted with it, not any order in that Function,) be duly conſidered, and it will caſt dirt in the faces of thoſe who ſo eagerly contend for the appropriation of it to the men of their order. If the Biſhop and he alone is the Angel, the Meſſenger and mouth of Jeſus Chriſt, how bad a caſe had the Church been in, in theſe latter dayes, how juſtly might <hi>England</hi> have joyned with<note n="n" place="margin">Dicit Apoſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lus Augelu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tanae ſe tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>figurare in Angelum lucis. <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>tinam his diehus Angeli lucis non fint transfigurati in Angelos tene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brarum. N<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>c. de Clem. tract. de nov. celebrit. non in ſtit. p. <hi>157.</hi> edit Lugd. Bat. an. <hi>1609.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Clement</hi> in his deſire, <hi>Oh
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:111196:6"/>that the Angels of light</hi> (<hi>i. e.</hi> thoſe which ſhould have been ſuch) <hi>had not been in theſe dayes transfigured into the angels of dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe.</hi> How truly that obſervation of <hi>Eſpencaeus</hi> concerning the Biſhops in his time hath been verified of the moſt of ours, let the world judge;<note n="o" place="margin">Eſpenc. digreſ. in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. ad Tim l. <hi>2.</hi> c <hi>2.</hi> p <hi>7<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</hi> ed t Lu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>et an. <hi>1619.</hi>
               </note> He tels us that heretofore it was accounted a very ſtrange thing to find a non-preaching Biſhop, but in theſe times, ſaith he, to finde a preaching Biſhop <hi>plus quàm monſtrilicae haberetur,</hi> would be eſteemed more then monſtrous. When the<note n="p" place="margin">in Apoc. c. <hi>1. v. 20.</hi>
               </note> Rhemiſts in their annotations on the former Chapter had obſerved, <hi>The Biſhops are the ſtarres of the Church:</hi> our learned <hi>Fulke</hi> returnes them this anſwer, S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
               <hi>John by the Angels of the Churches meaneth not all that ſhould weare Myters on their heads and hold Crozier ſtaves in their hands like dead idols, but them that are the faithfull Meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſengers of the Lords Word, and utter and declare the ſame.</hi> Had the Inſcription been <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> how would our Prelaticall men have vaunted? you ſhould have heard the ſame from them—<hi>Invento populus quod clamat Oſyri:</hi> We have found it, we have found it, when from a metaphoricall notion, and ſuch a denomination as is common to all Miniſters, becauſe uſed in the ſingular number, they doe thus triumph. Yet they are not, I perſwade my ſelfe, ignorant that not only<note n="q" place="margin">Angelus, i. e. nuncius Sacer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dos Deiveriſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mè dicitur, quia Dei &amp; hominis ſequeſter eſt, ejuſque ad po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulum nuntiat voluntatem, in <hi>Mal 2.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Hierome</hi> (their back friend, as they conceive) doth, as I have done before, interpret this denomination Angel, and gives his reaſon for it; but that with<note n="r" place="margin">Moral. in Iob. lib. <hi>34.</hi> c. <hi>7.</hi> edit. Baſil an. <hi>1564.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Gregorie</hi> the Great, a Biſhop and Pope of Rome, The Inſcription <hi>Angelis Eccleſiarum, To the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels of the Churches,</hi> is expounded thus, <hi>Praedicatoribus populorum, To the Preachers of the people.</hi> So that in the judgement of theſe Divines the Inſcription comprehends all thoſe who are ſharers in this title of Office, and are by it differenced, not one from the other joyned in the ſame Commiſſion of Embaſſage, but from the Church or people unto whom in the name of the Lord they are to performe the Office of Angels or Meſſengers. Thus much is indeed granted by our Hierarchiſts, though with ſome additionall fancies of their own; for they tell us, that<note n="ſ" place="margin">
                  <hi>Epiſc</hi> by div. right <hi>p.</hi> 122.</note> 
               <hi>All the Preſbyters of theſe Churches were Angels in reſpect of their Ministery, yet</hi> (forſooth) <hi>one was the Angel in reſpect of his fixed ſuperioritie. There were thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſands of ſtarres in this firmament of the Aſian Churches, there were but ſeven of the firſt magnitude.</hi> We heare them ſay ſo, but ſhill the queſtion is how this is proved, and the aſſertion made good.
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:111196:6"/>In which regard to this their peremptory aſſertion, it were ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent for me to give at preſent no other anſwer, then that ſhort mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginall animadverſion which<note n="*" place="margin">Faſcic. ro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>um expet ſol. <hi>104.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Orthuinus Gratius</hi> gives to that ſilly Frier <hi>William</hi> of <hi>Woodeford</hi> (who being preſſed by the authoritie of <hi>Hierome</hi> and <hi>Armachanus</hi>) alledged by <hi>Wickliffe,</hi> that before ſchiſmes did ariſe in the Church, matters were governed by com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon counſell of the Presbyters, which in that reſpect were all equall, returned thereto this anſwere, That ſchiſme began in the Apoſtles dayes, (as it is manifeſt in the Scripture) <hi>He</hi>
               <note n="a" place="margin">Dicit in Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptura patere ſed nibil probat.</note> 
               <hi>ſaith it is manifeſt in the Scripture, but proves nothing.</hi> And <hi>Mirum ubi legerit author de illo ſchiſmate. I wonder where the Author reads concerning that ſchiſme.</hi> By the way obſerve that from this ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple <hi>Ignoramus</hi> the forementioned Fryer, (who undertook to write againſt <hi>Wickliffe,</hi> that he might the better engratiate himſelfe in the eyes of that perſecuting Prelate <hi>Thomas Arundel</hi> Archbiſhop of Canterbury) D<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>Downham</hi> and Biſhop <hi>Hall</hi> our<note n="t" place="margin">D<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                  <hi>Downhams</hi> Sermon at <hi>La<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beth,</hi> p. 88, 89. Biſhop <hi>Hall,</hi> Epiſc. by div. right, <hi>p.</hi> 192.</note> Hierarchicall Rabbines for learning have borrowed that ſimple evaſion, as if that <hi>Hierome</hi> uſing the phraſe of the Apoſtle, by which he ſets forth the ſchiſmes and diviſions which were in his time in the Church of Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rinth, did point out the time when this Prelation of a Biſhop above the Presbyters began, to wit, in the Apoſtles dayes. Which how vain and weake it is, yea, how inconſiſtent with and contradictory unto what is by <hi>Hierome</hi> delivered in thoſe places, is ſufficiently diſcovered by ſundry<note n="u" place="margin">Chamier. Pan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrat. tom. <hi>2.</hi> l. <hi>9.</hi> de Occ Pont. c. <hi>5.</hi> n. <hi>16.</hi> Whitak cont. <hi>4.</hi> q. <hi>1.</hi> c. <hi>3.</hi> ſeci <hi>29.</hi> Wal. Meſſ. diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſert. de presh. &amp; epiſc. cap. <hi>4.</hi> p. <hi>242.</hi> ad p. <hi>249</hi>
               </note> Divines; to whom I referre the Reader, if he pleaſe to peruſe the quotations in the margent. I returne to the application and preſſing of the forementioned ſhort marginall ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>madverſion; and would faine know of our Prelaticall men where doth the holy Ghoſt intimate this Hierarchie of Angels, ſome An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels miniſterially, others Angels by a fixed ſuperiority. Where doth S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
               <hi>John</hi> in all this viſion give the leaſt hint of ſuch a diſtinction of Starres, that ſome are ſtarres of the firſt, ſome of the ſecond or third magnitude? Or where in all the Scripture is the name of ſtarres reſtrained unto Biſhops. Is it in S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
               <hi>Judes</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">Jude ver. 13.</note> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>wandring ſtarres to whom is reſerved blackneſſe of darkneſſe for ever:</hi> or is it afterward in the Revelation, when the holy Ghoſt telleth us the<note n="b" place="margin">Rev. 12.4.</note> 
               <hi>dragon did draw down the third part of the ſtarres with his tail?</hi> Doe not our Prelatiſts reaſon almoſt as wiſely and as ſolidely from this place and notion for their dignitie and ſuperioritie of order and
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:111196:7"/>of power, as once the Canoniſt <hi>Hoſtienſis,</hi> and after him <hi>Andreas Siculus Barbatias</hi> deſiring to curry favour with <hi>Beſſarion,</hi> did, who undertook to prove the Divine Inſtitution of Cardinals from that place of Scripture,<note n="x" place="margin">1 Sam. 2.</note> 
               <hi>Domini ſunt cardines terrae.</hi> And albeit the Lawyer thought he gave a witty reaſon for his conceit, <hi>becauſe as the doore in its motion is guided by the hinges whereunto it is fastned, and whereupon it hangeth, ſo the Church of Rome is go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verned by the counſell of Cardinals,</hi> yet<note n="y" place="margin">De Invent. rer. lib. <hi>4.</hi> c. <hi>o.</hi> p. <hi>290</hi> edit. Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. an. <hi>1555</hi> vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de, nonſecus iſti Iuriſconſulti aliquoties de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torquent ſacras literas quo vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lunt, ac ſuto<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>es ſolent ſordidas dentibus exten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e pelles.</note> 
               <hi>Polydore Virgil</hi> gave him this cenſure, which by the bare change of the name of the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons cenſured I ſhall apply to our preſent purpoſe. <hi>Theſe Lawyers,</hi> ſaid he, theſe Prelatiſts, ſay I, <hi>ſtretch Scripture as they pleaſe, just as the Shoe-maker doth his leather with his teeth, to fit it to his Laste.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. It is granted by Biſhop <hi>Hall</hi> as an undoubted truth, that<note n="z" place="margin">Loc. cit. p. <hi>122.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>in each of theſe Churches there were many Preſbyters, as for instance that of Epheſus; yet but one Angel,</hi> ſaith he, that is to ſay, but one Biſhop. But ſoft and faire my Lord. The ſame place of Scripture which makes it unqueſtionable that there were many Presbyters in the Church of Epheſus, doth as apparently declare the pluralitie of Biſhops, and ſo the identitie of Biſhops both in name and office. Thus much is yeelded by the ſame<note n="a" place="margin">
                  <hi>p.</hi> 119.</note> Patron of Epiſcopacie, that the Elders which <hi>Paul</hi> ſent for from Epheſus to Miletum, and to whom his ſpeech is directed, were indeed Biſhops, which he doth grant from thoſe words of the Apoſtle; <hi>Whereof the holy Ghoſt hath made you Biſhops.</hi> But forſooth <hi>they were not all Biſhops of Epheſus, but of different Territories, of farre diſperſed charges,</hi> and how is all this proved; we heare S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
               <hi>Paul</hi> ſay; <hi>Ye all amongſt whom I have gone preaching the Kingdome of God:</hi> very magiſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rially, <hi>&amp; tanquamè cathedra Epiſcopali,</hi> Epiſcopall dictates out of an Epiſcopall chaire, to which all muſt yeeld an implicite faith, and blinde beliefe. Belike S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
               <hi>Paul</hi> held now an Archiepiſcopall viſita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and albeit the Archbiſhops court were to be held at Miletum, yet from Epheſus by ſome Gentleman Apparitor, or other the Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitory Summons or Proceſſes were ſent forth to the ſeverall Dio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſes —<hi>Riſum teneatis amici.</hi> Who can almoſt refraine laughter at the very hearing or reading of ſuch ridiculous conceits. By the way let us take notice of one thing, that to this Archiepiſcopall vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitation not the inferiour Miniſters, but the Dioceſan Biſhops them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:111196:7"/>were ſummoned and cited. The evaſion is ſo weake that I am loth to ſpend time and tire your patience in refutation of it. Onely give me leave to ſay ſomewhat to it. 1. Had theſe Presbyters been Biſhops of farre diſperſed charges in Aſia and different Terri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tories, the holy Evangeliſt and Hiſtorian would rather have ſaid <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Of the Churches,</hi> then <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Of the Church.</hi> We finde the Apoſtle in the like caſes uſing the plurall number. The Churches of Aſia, <hi>Rom.</hi> 6.19. The Churches of God in Judea, 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 2.14. The Churches of Macedonia, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 8.1. 2. Though it be not ſaid expreſſely that theſe Elders or Presbyters were onely the Presbyters of the Church of Epheſus, yet the circumſtances of the text will clearely (as I conceive with ſubmiſſion to better judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments) evince it to be ſo. The Evangeliſt S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
               <hi>Luke</hi> deſcribing <hi>Pauls</hi> journey to <hi>Hieruſalem,</hi> ſaith<note n="b" place="margin">Act. 20.17. <hi>&amp; ſeq.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>we came to Miletum, For Paul de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termined to ſaile by Epheſus that he might not tarry in Aſia, for be haſtened if it were poſſible for him to be at Hieruſalem at Pen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tecoste. And ſending from Miletum unto Epheſus he called toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the Elders of the Church.</hi> To theſe Elders of the Church he doth appeale as witneſſes of his fidelitie and induſtrie in preaching the word, in ſerving the Lord with all humilitie, teares and in many temptations. Now conſider where was the place of <hi>Pauls</hi> abode and reſidence amongſt them, was it not Epheſus? the former paſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges of the hiſtorie tell us ſo in plain termes; that there he<note n="c" place="margin">Chap. 19.10.</note> 
               <hi>continued by the ſpace <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>f two yeares, ſo that all they which dwelt in Aſia heard the word of the Lord Jeſus both Jewes and Greekes.</hi> Ephe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus you ſee was the place of <hi>Pauls</hi> reſidence in Aſia, here he gathered the Church, in the planting and ſetling of which he continued amongſt them by the ſpace of two yeares, It being the place in which the Church was gathered muſt be alſo the place of reſidence of the Elders of the Church. 3. If Interpreters either Greeke or La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tine, Ancient or Modern be conſulted, we ſhall finde them all ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counting theſe Presbyters to be Presbyters of no other Church then the Church of Epheſus. By the cleare evidence of which place ſundry Divines of all ſorts doe prove the Identitie and Indiſtincti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Biſhops and Presbyters both in name and Office in ſacred Writ. In which regard I cannot but wonder with what face our Pretenders to Antiquitie for the diſtinction of their Order from a Presbyter, doe venture to obtrude ſo novell a fancie on their Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:111196:8"/>and ſeduced followers. For of how green antiquitie are <hi>Bucke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ride</hi> and <hi>Barlow</hi> with their follower D<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>Hall,</hi> that their Dictates muſt beare ſway againſt the current of Interpreters, not one Divine of note being produced (for ought that I could yet reade or heare) in favour of this ridiculous evaſion, which was I am perſwaded ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver heard of in the Chriſtian Church, till of late <hi>Hieromonarchici nostri,</hi> (as <hi>Spalatenſis</hi> ſtiles the Papalines, and we may not unfitly ſtile out Prelates) vented theſe their dreames, that by theſe their groundleſſe fancies they might the better uphold their own honour and dignities; So that we may juſtly retort the Proverbe applyed by one of them to M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>Brightmans</hi> conjectures, on their own heads. <hi>Thus the bels ſay what ſome hearers thinke.</hi> 4. There is no colour of reaſon to obtrude on us ſuch an interpretation of thoſe words, <hi>Ye all amongſt whom I have gone preaching the Kingdome of God,</hi> as if it muſt be underſtood of <hi>Pauls</hi> travelling from Dioceſſe to Dioceſſe, for the Text affords in plain termes another, the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle puts them in minde what he had done, that he.<note n="d" place="margin">Act 20.20.</note> had taught them and preached amongſt them <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>publikely and from houſe to houſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. Albeit the Inſcription be in the ſingular number <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>To the Angel,</hi> yet that doth not prove it to be ſpoken unto, or meant of one individuall perſon. He ſpake a truth who ſaid,<note n="c" place="margin">
                  <hi>Baines</hi> Dio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſans Triall, <hi>pag.</hi> 15.</note> 
               <hi>Seven ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gular ſtarres may ſignifie ſeven unites, whether ſingular or ag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregative: Seven pluralities of perſon who are ſo united as if they were one. And it is frequent in Scripture to note by an unity an united multitude.</hi> Now for as much as this is gain-ſaid by our Hierarchiſts as a ridiculous evaſion; I will therefore confirme it againſt their contradiction, and endeavour to make it evident that under one many may be, many are meant. This is the language and uſuall ſtile of the holy Ghoſt. 1. In viſionall ſpeeches <hi>Daniel</hi> in the narration and interpretation of the Kings dreame faith to <hi>Nebu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chadnezzar.</hi>
               <note n="f" place="margin">Dan. 2.38.</note> 
               <hi>Thou art this head of gold, after thee ſhall ariſe ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Kingdome inferiour unto thee.</hi> The ſpeech is directed to <hi>Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buchadnezzar</hi> in his own perſon, yet under one many are meant, for not he alone but all the Kings precedent and ſucceeding in that Monarchie are the head of gold, as Interpreters doe unanimouſly conſent. It is ſaid in the verſe following, After thee ſhall another Kingdome ariſe, yet all that have any inſight in hiſtory both ſacred
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:111196:8"/>and profane doe know that the Perſian Monarchie, which is the Kingdome there ſpoken of, did not ariſe immediately upon the death of <hi>Nebuchadnezzar</hi> the Great, to whom this dreame, and interpretation of it is made knowne, but upon the death of <hi>Belſhaz<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zar</hi> his Grand-childe. So that under the Perſon of one, many of the ſame order and degree are here neceſſarily to be underſtood. The Lord repreſents to<note n="g" place="margin">Chap. 1.18, 19, 20, 21. If any deſire more inſtances of this kinde, for the confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation of this, I refer him to the reply to D<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                  <hi>Downhams</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence, <hi>part</hi> 1. <hi>l.</hi> 3. <hi>c.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. <hi>ſect.</hi> 7.</note> 
               <hi>Zechariah</hi> in a viſion <hi>ſoure hornes which did ſcatter Judah and Jeruſalem, and foure Carpenters which were ſent to fray them away,</hi> and to repaire Jeruſalem. Will any ſober man hence conclude the Perſons which ſcattered Judah were individually foure, no more nor no leſſe, and the Repairers of Jeru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalem juſt foure and no more? yet this inference will hold as well as that which our Prelates make from this viſion in the Revelation. Chriſt holdeth in his hand ſeven ſtarres, which ſeven ſtarres are the Angels of the Churches, therefore the Angels of the Churches are juſt ſeven and no more. They may with as much colour of reaſon and truth extort another concluſion alſo thus: Chriſt holdeth in his hand ſeven ſtarres of the firſt magnitude and none but them, which ſeven ſtarres are the Angels by a fixed ſuperioritie, There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore Chriſt hath care of the direction and protection of none but the Biſhops, which are the ſtarres of the firſt magnitude, the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels by a fixed ſuperiority. Take one inſtance more. When the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle ſpeakes of that grand Apoſtate Antichriſt, he ſpeakes of him in the ſingular number,<note n="h" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Theſ. 2.3.</note> 
               <hi>That man of ſinne, the ſonne of perdition,</hi> now albeit the<note n="i" place="margin">Bell tib. <hi>3.</hi> de Rom. Pent. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.<hi>2.</hi> K. Secudus locus Graeci contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bunt ſignificationem ad unam tem certam, ut <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minem in co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>muni, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> hominem ſingularem fignificet. Et ſanè mirum eſt nullum ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſariorum, qui tamen jact ant linguarum peritiam, hoc ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>madvertiſſe.</note> Romiſh Cardinall doe from the article prefixed, when he is ſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ed <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>that maen of ſinne, the ſonne of perdition, that wicked one,</hi> plead for a reſtriction to one individuall perſon, and <hi>wonder at it that none of the adverſaries doe take no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice of it, notwithſtanding all their skill in the tongues, of which they ſo much boaſt;</hi> yet how ridiculous a conceit this is you all know. Our Polemicall Divines have ſufficiently diſcovered the falſhood and vanitie of this aſſertio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>; of which I may truly ſay as our learned <hi>Fulk</hi> doth in his reply to the Rhemiſts (who trod in the ſteps of their fellow Jeſuite fore-mentioned)<note n="k" place="margin">in 2 Theſ. 2. ver. 3. <hi>annot</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> 
               <hi>This is ſo falſe that young children, which have ſcarce taſted of the Greek tongue, are able to diſprove it by infinite Examples.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="10" facs="tcp:111196:9"/>
            <p n="2">2. In other places of Scripture where the ſpeech is directed unto one, yet under that one others of the ſame order and ſocietie are meant. Our Saviour Chriſt ſaid to <hi>Peter,</hi>
               <note n="l" place="margin">Matth. 16.19.</note> 
               <hi>I will give unto thee the keyes of the Kingdome of Heaven;</hi> though at Rome under the Popes noſe, in a conclave of Cardinals, the limitation of this to <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters</hi> perſon (as Chriſts Vicar) would be readily embraced, yet you all know, Reverend and Beloved, how repugnant this is to Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture: in which regard he would be hooted at, as having a Pope in his belly, that ſhould in any Reformed Church confine the power of the Keyes to <hi>Peters</hi> perſon: Yea,<note n="m" place="margin">de rep eccleſ. lib. <hi>1.</hi> cap. <hi>7.</hi> n. <hi>3.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Antonius de Dominis</hi> will tell us, that <hi>it would be a monſtrous thing indeed to deny that our Lord did there direct his ſpeech to Peter, and promiſe him the Keyes, which he did after wards infallibly conferre on him; But it would be</hi> monſtri majoris ſimile, <hi>more monſtrous by farre, ſo to limit this promiſe and the execution thereof unto Peter, as that it ſhould im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply an excluſion of the reſt of the Apoſtles.</hi> Hence divers of the Fathers have obſerved that there under the Perſon of One, to wit, <hi>Peter,</hi> to whom the ſpeech is primarily directed, is an united multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude, the Church, to be underſtood. Thus <hi>Auſtin</hi> ſundry times ſpeaks.<note n="n" place="margin">Tract <hi>50.</hi> in Evang. Iohan. Iudas malus Corpus malorum ſignificat, quomodo Petrus corpus bonorum, corpus eccleſiae, imò corpus eccleſiae, ſed in bonis: nam ſi in Petro non eſſet ſacramentum Eccleſiae, non <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>i diceret Dominus, Tibi dabo claves regni <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>oelorum.</note> 
               <hi>Wicked Judas ſignifieth the body of the wicked, as Peter the body of the good, the body of the Church which conſiſteth of the good, otherwiſe the Lord would not ſay to him<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> I will give unto thee the Keyes of the Kingdome of Heaven.</hi> And elſewhere,<note n="o" place="margin">Tract. <hi>124.</hi> in idem Evang. Eccleſiae Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trus Apoſtolus prop<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>er Apoſtolatus ſui primatum gerebat figurata generalitate perſonam. Quad enim ad ipſum propriè pertinet, natura unus homo erat, gratia u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus Chriſtianus, abundantiore gratia ur us idemq, primus Apoſtolus: ſed quando et di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>etum, Tibi dabo claves regni coelorum, uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſam ſignificabat eccleſiam.</note> 
               <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter</hi> in reſpect of himſelf <hi>was properly by na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture one man, by grace one Chriſtian, by a more abundant grace one and the ſame a chief Apostle. But when it was ſaid to him, I will give unto thee the Keyes of the Kingdome of Heaven, he did ſignifie the whole Church,</hi> &amp;c. So he, more teſtimonies might be produced, but theſe are ſufficient; he that deſireth to ſee this truth confirmed by more ſuffrages of the ancients may conſult<note n="p" place="margin">Loc. cit. n. <hi>4.</hi> &amp; ſeq.</note> 
               <hi>Spalatenſis,</hi> and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive abundant ſatisfaction. As then in the fore-mentioned ſpeech of our Saviour under one, a collected body of Apoſtles and Beleevers is underſtood, ſo here by one Angel is meant the united body of An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels, and what is ſpoken unto one is to be underſtood as ſpoken to
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:111196:9"/>all of them, as by their place they are Angels. For the denomina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is ſo uſed here that it points out rather <hi>the function then the perſon,</hi> as our induſtrious and learned Countrey man M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>
               <note n="q" place="margin">Medit. in A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poc. p. <hi>9.</hi> edit. Lond an. <hi>1587.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Foxe</hi> hath obſerved. To paſſe from this Inſtance to another. When the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle ſpeaking concerning the uſefulneſſe of the Scripture, that<note n="r" place="margin">2 Tim. 3.16, 17.</note> it is profitable for doctrine, for reproofe, for correction, for inſtruction in righteouſneſſe, addes this as a principall end of all, <hi>that the man of God might be perfect,</hi> is this, thinke you, ſpoken concerning the perfecting of one man of God alone, or of all that are ſuch by their place and calling? When the ſame Apoſtle gives this charge to <hi>Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mothy,</hi>
               <note n="ſ" place="margin">1 Tim. 6.11.</note> 
               <hi>Thou O man of God flee theſe things:</hi> doth he not in the perſon of <hi>Timothy</hi> lay this charge upon all the Miniſters of the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel, who ſhare in that honourable title and function? What ſhall we ſay then to thoſe which would make us to beleeve that what is here ſpoken to the Angel (a name of Office common to all the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters of Jeſus Chriſt) is to be underſtood as ſpoken unto one, a Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop and him that ſitteth in the throne. With the ſame ſtrength of argument, and as much colour of reaſon might a Romaniſt inferre, becauſe the Lord ſaith in the ſingular number of the Prieſt:<note n="ſ" place="margin">Mal. 2.7.</note> 
               <hi>The Priests lips ſhall preſerve knowledge, and they ſhall ſeeke the Law at his mouth, for he is the Meſſenger of the Lord of hoſts.</hi> And<note n="t" place="margin">Deut. 17.1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> 
               <hi>The man that will do preſumptuouſly, and will not hearken to the judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Priest, that ſtandeth to miniſter before the Lord, that man ſhall dye.</hi> Though all Prieſts are Angels or Meſſengers of the Lord in reſpect of their Miniſterie, yet there is one Prieſt that is the Meſſenger or Angel by a fixed ſuperioritie, and at his mouth you muſt enquire, to wit, the Pope, you are not (I know) ignorant that thus ſome have argued, and what our Divines have anſwered them their writings doe declare; both D<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>Reynolds</hi> in his<note n="u" place="margin">Chap. <hi>6.</hi> div. <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> p. <hi>252.</hi>
               </note> Conference with <hi>Hart,</hi> and the learned Frenchman<note n="*" place="margin">Sum. cont. part. <hi>1.</hi> q. <hi>8.</hi> p. <hi>127, 128.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Rivetus</hi> in confutation of <hi>Bailie</hi> the Jeſuite.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Let us conſider ſundry paſſages in the Epiſtles themſelves; in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the bowels of which if we diligently looke we ſhall finde that albeit the inſcription be in the ſingular number, To the Angel; yet the Angel was more then one diſtinct and individuall perſon, and that the denomination is not to be taken <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> Singularly or Perſonally, but <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> collectively including an united multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude. In the Epiſtle to Thyatira the Inſcription is as in the reſt in
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:111196:10"/>the ſingular number, yet afterwards the holy Ghoſt ſaith thus,<note n="*" place="margin">Revel. 2.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>4. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> &amp;c</note> 
               <hi>But unto you I ſay and to the reſt in Thyatira.</hi> In which words the Church of Thyatira is diſtinguiſhed, as<note n="x" place="margin">Habes hic duas eccleſie Thyatirenſis partes, quarum una eſt Paſtorum &amp; Praeſidem<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. Eccleſiae collegium; altera reliqui corpor is <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> Gerſ But drſſert. de guh. Eccl. p. <hi>203.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Gerſom Bucerus</hi> hath obſerved, into two parts, The one includeth the Colledge of Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtors and Preſidents of the Church; the other the reſt of the members, both are ſet forth in the Plurall number <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>unto you,</hi> anſwering to, <hi>To the Angel;</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>To the rest,</hi> anſwering unto <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>To the Church in Thyatira.</hi> The ſpeech directed to the Angel of the Church of Sar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dis is in the ſingular number,<note n="y" place="margin">Chap. 3.1.</note> 
               <hi>Thou haſt a name that thou liveſt, and art dead,</hi> compare this with that which followeth, and you ſhall finde that what is ſpoken of one is meant of many, and hereby is ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed the generall ſtate of the whole Church of Sardis both Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters and people; for it followeth,<note n="z" place="margin">
                  <hi>Ib.</hi> v. 4.</note> 
               <hi>Thou haſt a few names even in Sardis which have not defiled their garments.</hi> The greateſt part of both Miniſters and people had but the name of an outward profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, by which they ſeemed to live, but in hearts they denied the power of godlineſſe and ſo were dead; amongſt them all there were but a few that were living members, ſincere and holy. When the Lord Ieſus ſaith in the Epiſtle to Philadelphia,<note n="a" place="margin">Chap. 3.11.</note> 
               <hi>Hold faſt that which thou haſt, that no man take away thy crown:</hi> If this be an exhortation to the Biſhop alone to conſtancie in the truth, and a promiſe made to none but him, belike none ſhall weare a crown in heaven but he that hath worne a Mitre on earth, and rather parted with his Mitre here, then with the truth of Chriſt. The Epiphone<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maticall ſentence which is added at the end of each Epiſtle; <hi>He that hath an eare to heare, let him heare what the Spirit ſaith to the Churches,</hi> doth clearely evince it, that by the Angel is to be under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood the whole Church in all its members. I will adde but one in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance more: When the Angel of the Church of Epheſus is blamed,<note n="b" place="margin">Chap. 2.4, 5.</note> 
               <hi>I have ſomewhat againſt thee, becauſe thou haſt left thy firſt love,</hi> and this reprehenſion is backed with a Commination, <hi>I will come unto thee quickly, and will remove thy Candlestick out of his place, except thou repent:</hi> Can any man in ſober reaſon imagine that this is the reprooſe of, and threatning againſt one man alone, and that God would for the Apoſtaſie or remiſſeneſſe of love to the truth in one Prelate caſt off a whole Church? We finde no ſuch thing upon
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:111196:10"/>record in the whole Booke of God, or any other hiſtory. That of<note n="c" place="margin">Hom <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. in Apoc. Moveb<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> candelabrum tuum <hi>i.e</hi> diſper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gam populum pro peccatis.</note> 
               <hi>Auſtin</hi> is moſt conſonant to the truth, who doth thus paraphraſe the Comminatory ſentence, <hi>I will remove thy Candlestick.</hi> i. e. <hi>I will ſcatter the people for their ſinnes.</hi> In which regard the ſame Father doth afterwards tell us,<note n="d" place="margin">Angelos eccleſiam dicit, in quibus duas partes, <hi>i. e.</hi> bonorum &amp; malorum, oſten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit, ut laus ad bonos, Increpatio ad malos dtrigatur. Sicut dominus in Evangelto, Omne praepeſitorum corpus u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>um ſervum dixit, beatum &amp; nequam, quam venient dominus ipſe dividet. <hi>Id. ibid.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Hee calleth the Church the Angels, in which Church hee ſheweth there were two parts good and bad, that the praiſe may be directed to the good, the reproofe to the bad.</hi> Thus hee, with more to the ſame purpoſe. The ſame truth is delivered by <hi>Arethas</hi> and <hi>Andreas</hi> Biſhops of Caeſarea Cappadocia, the moſt ancient Interpreters of this Revelation.<note n="e" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> 
               <hi>He calleth the Angel of E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheſus the Church that was in Epheſus.</hi> And both confirm this Interpretation from ſundry paſſages in theſe Epiſtles: From whence<note n="f" place="margin">Sit ergò boc fixum — hoc argumentum ab Angetis qui Epiſcopos denotant, nibit facere ad pr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>bandum Epiſcopos tum ſuiſſe in urbibus ſingulos. Wal. Meſſ. diſſert. <hi>1.</hi> de presb. &amp; epiſe c. <hi>4.</hi> p <hi>184.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maſius</hi> (in whom the Reader if he pleaſe may ſee this laſt quotation at large) drawes this concluſion, <hi>Let this therefore be an undoubted truth, that this argument from the Angels makes nothing to prove that there was but one Biſhop in a Church or citie.</hi> Thus much of the third argument, I proceed to another.</p>
            <p n="4">4. By the Angel in this place is not to be underſtood a Biſhop in Order, Office, and power of Juriſdiction, diſtinguiſhed from, and ſuperiour to a Presbyter, for there was no ſuch diſtinction or ſupe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riority ſettled in the Church of Chriſt before, nor in S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
               <hi>Johns</hi> time, nor immediately after the Apoſtles dayes. The truth of this nega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive aſſertion I ſhall endeavour to confirme by theſe enſuing ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guments.</p>
            <p>Firſt, in the Word of God, we finde no ſuch difference or impa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity in Order and Power between a Biſhop and a Presbyter, as is pretended by our Prelates. In proſecuting of which undertaken taske I will as briefly as I may conſider what is delivered by a late Patron of Epiſcopacy, who tels us that<note n="g" place="margin">
                  <hi>Epiſc.</hi> by div. right. <hi>p.</hi> 91.</note> 
               <hi>This imparity of Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and Epiſcopall Juriſdiction was founded by Christ, erected by his Apoſtles, both by their practiſe and recommendation.</hi> In the proofe of which poſition when he had ſpent ſundry pages, he con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cludes with a great deale of aſſurance that he hath carried all down
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:111196:11"/>before him, ſaying,<note n="h" place="margin">Pag. <hi>127.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>I am for my part ſo confident of the Divine Inſtitution of the Majoritie of Biſhops above Preſbyters, that I dare boldly ſay, there are weighty points of faith, which have not ſo ſtrong evidence in holy Scriptures.</hi> We heare him ſpeaking with ſo much confidence, as if he had not only taken the Oath in the late Canons, but ſworne unto, or at leaſtwiſe in heart, and by his pen ſubſcribed to the<note n="i" place="margin">Si quis dixerit in Eccleſia catholica inon eſſe Hierar biam divina ordinatione inſtitutam, quae conſtat ex Epiſcopis &amp; Miniſtris Anathema ſit. <hi>Seis. 7. Can. 6.</hi>
               </note> Anathematiſme of the Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dentine Conventicle, in which <hi>this Hierarchie of Biſhops and Preſbyters is ſaid to be of Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine institution,</hi> and an Anathema denounced againſt thoſe that ſhall queſtion or deny it. Yet notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding the confidence of thoſe Biſhops and Fryars at Trent, and of our Engliſh Hierarchiſts how farre this was from being embraced as an article of faith Friar <hi>Peter</hi> will informe us.<note n="k" place="margin">Hiſtorie of the Counc of Trent. lib. <hi>8.</hi> pag. <hi>743.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>The ſixt Anathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matiſme,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>was much noted in Germany, in which an article of faith was made of Hierarchie: which word and ſignification thereof is alien, not to ſay contrary to the Scriptures: and though it was ſomewhat anciently invented, yet the Authour is not known; and in caſe he were, yet is he an hyperbolicall writer, not imitated in the uſe of that word, nor of others of his invention, by any of the an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cients, and following the ſtile of Chriſt our Lord, and of the holy Apoſtles and Primitive Church it ought to be named not Hierar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chie, but Hierodiaconia, or Hierodantia.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I will therfore, becauſe the Biſhop, whom I intend to chaſe, runs this way, follow him, and 1. Conſider whether our Saviour Chriſt laid any foundation for this Epiſcopall Juriſdiction. 2. Look to the practice of the Apoſtles in which they ſay this fabricke and frame of Church government was erected. 3. View their writings, whether in them there is any ſuch diſtinction of Order and Power between a Biſhop and a Presbyter.</p>
            <p n="1">1. As for that foundation which our Prelatiſts ſay was laid by Chriſt, <hi>placing his Apoſtles above his other Diſciples, the Twelve above the Seventie,</hi> it hath beene ſufficiently diſcovered by ſundry Divines (in which regard I ſhall have cauſe to ſay the leſſe) to be ſandy and weak, altogether unable to bear the weight of that fabricke which is by them hereupon erected; yea, ſome of their owne friends and ſticklers in the cauſe have confeſſed it, or at leaſtwiſe yeelded that which doth overthrow it. For,
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:111196:11"/>1.<note n="m" place="margin">Agnoſcit Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ravia Septua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginta diſcipulos Evang liſtarum dignitate eminuiſse, ac proinde Ordinariis Epiſcopis vocationis gradu a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>tecelluiſſe. Gerſ. Bucer p. <hi>515.</hi> ex Sar. de Min. Ev. grad cap. <hi>4.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Saravia</hi> (a profeſſed patron of Epiſcopacy and Antagoniſt to <hi>Beza,</hi> whom our Prelates looke on as their back-friend) doth ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge that <hi>the Seventie Diſciples were Evangeliſts, and in that reſpect by the degree of their calling ſuperior to Ordinary Biſhops.</hi> How then is there I pray you any foundation for the imparitie between a Biſhop and a Presbyter laid by Chriſt in this fact of his chooſing Twelve Apoſtles, and Seventie Diſciples, when theſe Seventie whom the Presbyters are ſaid to ſucceed were ſuperior to Biſhops themſelves? 2.<note n="n" place="margin">Peracto hoc primo munere, poſt quam re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſi ſunt gaudentes, non legimus eos am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plius a Chriſto miſſos in Miniſterium verbimeq, novam ill is ſuiſse replicara<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſionem, &amp;c. de rep. Eccl. lib. <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</hi> c. <hi>3.</hi> n. <hi>4.</hi> Quam confirmationem quedq<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, mandatum, &amp; generalem miſſionem, quia à Chriſto factam <hi>72.</hi> diſcipulis non invenio, ne<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſum affirmare in ipſis ſuiſſe directe, proxi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mè &amp; immediate inſtitutum ordinem presbyteralem, &amp;c Id. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>b num. <hi>4.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Spala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenſis</hi> hath obſerved that <hi>theſe Seventie Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples were not inſtituted by our Saviour for the perpetuall government of the Church, but onely that they had a temporarie Commiſſion</hi>
               <note n="p" place="margin">Luke 10.</note> 
               <hi>to goe before him into every City and place whither he himſelfe would come, which was not renewed to them after their returne with joy,</hi> becauſe the devils were made ſubject un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to them, as the Commiſſion (given to the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles at firſt with a limitation,<note n="q" place="margin">Match. 10.</note> 
               <hi>Go not in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the way of the Gentiles, neither enter into the Cities of the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maritanes, but goe rather to the lost ſheep of the houſe of Iſrael</hi>) was after his reſurrection repeated and enlarged,<note n="r" place="margin">Match. 28.</note> 
               <hi>Go teach all na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions.</hi> In which regard, ſaith he, <hi>I cannot, affirme that in them</hi> (the 70. Diſciples) <hi>was the Order of Preſbyters instituted directly and immediately.</hi> Chriſts election of the Seventie Diſciples affords you ſee by the confeſſion of the Archbiſhop of <hi>Spalato</hi> himſelf no ſure footing for the ſubjection of Presbyters to Biſhops; though he would fain claime an inſtitution of Biſhops in the Commiſſion gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven to the Apoſtles. But thirdly the<note n="ſ" place="margin">Enchir. Chriſt. relig. in Conc. Col. p. <hi>169.</hi> de ſacr. ord. edit. Pariſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>an <hi>1558.</hi> Non eſt tamen putan<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>um Epiſcopos ali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um in Eccleſia ordinem à Presbyteris con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtituiſſe. N<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>m in primitiva Eccleſia ii<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dem erant Presbyteri &amp; Epiſcopi, quod Apoſtolorum Petri &amp; Pauli epiſtolae di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> quo<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan>, Hierony nus, ac caeteri ſerè om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes veteres eccleſiaſſici ſcriptores a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantur.</note> Canons of Coleine ſpeak home to the point, and in plaine termes deny the conſequence of this, or that hereupon we ſhould imagine that Biſhops are a diſtinct Order from Presbyters. <hi>Albeit,</hi> ſay they, <hi>Chriſt did inſtitute twelve Apoſtles, in whoſe place the Biſhops are, and afterwards choſe ſeventie Diſciples whoſe place in the Church the Preſbyters do hold. Yet we muſt not thinke that Biſhops did conſtitute in the
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:111196:12"/>Church an order different from Preſbyters. For in the Primitive Church Biſhops and Preſbyters were the ſame, which the Epiſtles of the Apoſtles Peter and Paul,</hi> S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
               <hi>Hierome alſo, and almoſt all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ancient Eccleſiaſtic all writers doe teſtifie.</hi> In which regard our learned <hi>Junius</hi> ſpake a truth, and no more but the truth, when he told <hi>Bellarmine,</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">Quam patres Epiſcopos Apoſtolis, Presby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teros <hi>7<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</hi> Diſcipulis ſuccedere affirmaverunt, nunquam d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>xerunt ex inſtitute Chriſti ſuccede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re. Quia nunquam inſtitu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t Chriſtus ut Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſto is ſecundum gradum in Eccleſia ſucced<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur, quae res ſi fuiſſet ſam Apoſtolatus ſurctio ordinaria dicenda ſuiſſet. Hoc autem verira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ti &amp; rationi adverſatur, Omnes Dei ſervi in dectrina Apoſt olerum ſucceſſerunt, in gradum corum ne mine<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> adoptavit Deus. Sed &amp; <hi>70.</hi> Diſcipulorum vocatio fuit extraordinaria, po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtea in ordinariam <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>raducti ſunt ut Epiſcopi &amp; Presbyteri eſſent in tis eccleſiis, quibus ſunt attributi. Quomode ergo inquio dixetunt Dos illos ſuccedere? <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>empe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>umana ac non divina inſtitutione, analogica ratione quadam, non au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem propria, imitatione communi quadam, non fingulari neceſſita e eccleſiae. Succedere igitur ex ſimili non <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>utem pari, hos i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>is dixere Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tres, qu a gradus in Ec<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>leſiae non pares, ſed ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miles, non pleuè ſed quodommedo <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>bſervari putabant alii poſſe, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ii oportere. Siqua autem ſimilitudo eſt, tantum ſecu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>dum quid &amp; remo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſſima tamen fim<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>uco eſt; ſi verè vera, ſi imaginarie imaginaria. Haec verò ſecundum quid remota eſt &amp; imaginaria ſimiti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>do, ex qua ſiqui abſolute concludunt al ſolutè fallunt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>un. controv. <hi>5</hi> lib. <hi>1.</hi> cap. <hi>14</hi> not. <hi>15.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>When the Fathers ſaid the Biſhops ſucceed the Apoſtles, and the Preſbyters ſucceed the Seventie Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples, they never ſaid they did ſucceede one the other by Chriſts Inſtitution, but by humane no Divine Ordinance. They ſaid they did ſucceede them, becauſe ſome thought, there might be the like degrees after a ſort, though not fully the like, be obſerved in the Church. Yet this likeneſſe is but in ſome reſpect a remote and imagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary fimilitude, from which,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>if any doe inferre an abſolute concluſion</hi> (that it is ſo, that it ought to be ſo) <hi>they doe abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutely deceive</hi> themſelves and others. This is the ſumme of <hi>Junius</hi> more large and ſatisfactory anſwere. By all which hath been ſaid the Reader may eaſily diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerne on how uncertain grounds the faith of the Hierarchie is built. Of much more which might be ſpoken in this ſubject, I will adde onely one thing. Our Saviours act incorporating the Apoſtles into one collegrate body (as we may ſtile them) in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veſting all and each of them with equall power, conferring a Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perioritie or Primacy to none of them above his fellowes, doth plainly evince that he laid a foundation for, and gave a plat-forme of an Ariſtocraticall not Monarchick Governement in the Church. The Monarchie he hath reſerved to himſelfe as his peculiar Prero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gative; but thoſe to whom he gave a fixed ſuperiority (as our Hie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rarchiſts ſpeake) and commiſſion during terme of life, were all con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyned in an Ariſtocracy. If any deſire a reaſon why our Saviour Chriſt was pleaſed in his Apoſtles to ſettle an Ariſtocraticall Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment,
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:111196:12"/>and lay downe this as a ſtanding plat-forme for them and their ſucceſſours to follow; the Archbiſhop of <hi>Spalato</hi> ſhall informe him, in whom we have a full and ſatisfactory reaſon:<note n="t" place="margin">Derep. Eccl. lib. <hi>1.</hi> c. <hi>12.</hi> n. <hi>3.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Albeit,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>it is true that in humane Common-wealths a Monarchie, but eſpecially that which is tempered by lawes is beſt, yet in the Church Chriſt did not think it fit that way ſhould be gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven to a Monarchie, though never ſo well tempered amengſt thoſe that are his Miniſters, this he judged to be worſt of all in the Church.</hi> Obſerve I pray you his reaſon, for it carrieth a great deale of weight with it.<note n="u" place="margin">Salvator ipſe ſatis praevidit quam pernicioſa foret in Eccleſiae haec Monarchia, &amp; quam ſaci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lè in tyrannidem illa poſset erumpere, ideoq, ut tyrannis haec vitaretur uſus eſt fimilitudine ſervorum. &amp;c. — Sciebat enim Monarchiam banc Eccleſiaſticam ſurtim introductam ad ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rannidem apertum tandem tranſitum facturam. Id. ibid. num. <hi>4.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Our Saviour himſelfe did well fore-ſee how dangerous it would prove in the Church; that if once a Monarchie did creepe in by ſtealth it would open a manifeſt way to tyrannie to which it would degenerate.</hi> So <hi>Antonius de Dominis,</hi> well known to be a learned and great Patron of Epiſcopacie. As this reaſon given by him ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veth to overthrow the Papall Monarchie over the whole Church, ſo it doth effectually conclude againſt an Archiepiſcopall over a Provinciall, an Epiſcopall Soveraignty over a Dioceſan Church. For indeed there are not many ſteps betweene a Pope and a Prelate. <hi>Stapleton</hi> the Jeſuite (if the <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> have rightly quoted him) hath confeſſed it<note n="*" place="margin">Qui gravid a eſt ex Archi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>epiſcopo faciſe parere poteſt Papam. <hi>Staple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>an eaſio matter for an Archibiſhop, impregnated with an ambitious domineering ſpirit, to bring forth a Pope;</hi> and the practiſes of our later Prelates have made it evident to all the world, that a Dioceſan Monarch may quickly become a tyranni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call petti-Pope. In a word, ſuppoſe it ſhould be granted that the thrones promiſed by our<note place="margin">Matt. 19.28.</note> Saviour, are thrones Apoſtolicall, and that thereby is meant that power of Eccleſiaſticall Juriſdiction which Chriſt communicated to them his Extraordinarie Delegates and Embaſſadours (which yet is very queſtionable,<note n="x" place="margin">Chemnit. har. Ev. c <hi>132.</hi> I an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen. conc. Ev. c. <hi>100.</hi> Cajet. Par.</note> divers Divines car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rying it another way, yea,<note n="y" place="margin">L. cit. cap. <hi>11<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>=<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>3.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Spalatenſis</hi> affirmes the quite contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, that <hi>Chriſt there ſpeakes not a word of the throne in the Church</hi>) yet what is all this to an Epiſcopal throne, or to the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vancing of a Prelate above the reſt of the Presbyters? What af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finity is there between an Apoſtolicall and Epiſcopall throne, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween an Ariſtocraticall Government which Chriſt founded in his Apoſtles, and a Monarchicall Soveraignty which Prelates have uſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped.
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:111196:13"/>We reade indeed in Scripture of<note n="z" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Rev. 13.</note> 
               <hi>a throne</hi> which the Dragon did give to the beaſt on whoſe head are names of blaſphemie, but we reade not any where of an Apoſtolicall throne derived to a Biſhop. True it is as the Patron of Epiſcopacie hath told us that in the anci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ents there is mention of <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>The Biſhops throne.</hi>
               <note n="a" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, Orat. <hi>7.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gorie Nazianzen</hi> indeed ſo ſtiles his Epiſcopall dignity to which he was advanced, but withall, he ſaith, <hi>he could not well tell whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther he ſhould call it a tyrannicall throne or hierarchicall;</hi> in his next Oration he cals it in plaine termes<note n="b" place="margin">Orat. <hi>28.</hi>
               </note> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>a ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rannicall preheminence,</hi> and ſets down both there in proſe, and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards in<note n="c" place="margin">Carm. de vita ſu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> oper Grae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>col tom <hi>2.</hi> p. <hi>24.</hi> &amp; ſeq edit. Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>r ſan. <hi>1630</hi> &amp; Carm. de div. vitae gen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ad pſeudoepiſc.</note> verſe the bloudy contentions and diviſions which the ambition of Biſhops affecting this Epiſcopall throne cauſed both in Church and State. I would the ſame were not verified in our dayes, and that we had not cauſe with him to complain. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. Alas for our great ſorrowes and occaſions of griefe. Thus much for the foundation of Epiſcopall Juriſdiction pretended to be laid by Chriſt himſelf.</p>
            <p>We are in the next place to enquire whether it hath in the pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſe of the Apoſtles and their recommendation any more ſolid and firme erection; The onely inſtance of this, that is produced, is the charge of the Apoſtle in his Epiſtles to <hi>Timothy</hi> and <hi>Titus, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in in my underſtanding</hi> (ſaith our fore-mentioned<note n="d" place="margin">Page <hi>105.</hi>
               </note> Patron of E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſcopacie) <hi>the Apostle ſpeakes ſo home to the point, that if he were now to give direction to an Engliſh Biſhop, how to demeane him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe in his place, he could not ſpeake more fully to the execution of his ſacred Office.</hi> In which aſſertion we may ſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> what is one ſpeciall ground of this great confidence; Thoſe acts and offices which have beene by degrees limited to the. Biſhops as diſtinguiſhed from Presbyters, and granted by the Cuſtome of the Church, thoſe are ſingled out as if then by the Apoſtle limited and reſtrained to the Biſhop. Amidſt all that is here ſpoken out of theſe Epiſtles, we have not the leaſt mention of thoſe qualifications which S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
               <hi>Paul</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quirech in a Biſhop; It is not the <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> but <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> not <hi>the work</hi> of a Biſhop, but <hi>the dignitie</hi> and feigned Soveraignty for which they now contend and fight, however they would faine beare the world in hand that Epiſcopacie is a ſacred Order of Divine and Apoſtolicall inſtitution; ſo that we may truly apply that to ours which ſometimes <hi>Martin Duther</hi> firſt, and <hi>Marlorat</hi> after ſaid
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:111196:13"/>concerning Popiſh Prelates;<note n="e" place="margin">Perinde ſunt qui ſtatum epiſcopalem ſtatum jactitant perſéctionis, quum inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rim nthil agant, quam Satrap as pompa a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gere, equitare bellos caballos, niſi quod interdum templa conſecrant &amp; aras. Marl in <hi>2 Pet. 2.18.</hi> ex Luth.</note> 
               <hi>Like unto them</hi> (that ſpeake great ſwelling words of vanitie) <hi>are they which boaſt that Epiſcopacie is a ſtate of Perfection, when in the meane time the onely thing they aime at is to be equall to Peeres in pompe, to ride on ſtately horſes, only now and then their Lordſhips doe conſecrate a Temple or an Altar.</hi> For, if we ſhould looke for the ſame conditions and qualifications in many of ours, which S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
               <hi>Paul</hi> commands to bee in thoſe Biſhops there mentioned by him, we ſhall finde that we are<note n="f" place="margin">Hujuſmedi conditiones ſiquu exactè con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideret, &amp; conferat cum noſtrae aetatis epiſcopis, videbitur in novo orbe, &amp; in peregrina aliqua eccleſia, quae Chriſtum &amp; Apoſtolos penitus ignoraverit, ve ſari, Salm. in <hi>Tit. 1.</hi> diſp. <hi>1.</hi> ad <hi>4<hi rend="sup">•••</hi>
                  </hi> dub.</note> 
               <hi>in a new world</hi> (as <hi>Salmeron</hi> the Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuite once ſpake) <hi>and in a ſtrange Church that never heard of Chriſt and his Apostles.</hi> This by the way. From all that is culled out of theſe Epiſtles, the argument by which they muſt prove Epiſcopacie to have been erected by the Apoſtle labou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth with an uſuall fallacie, a ſhamefull begging of the queſtion. For firſt of all <hi>Timothy</hi> and <hi>Titus</hi> have been ſufficiently un-biſhop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped, not onely by him who hath written a particular treatiſe in that name, but by all that have waded into this controverſie, Domeſtick and Forraigne Divines, againſt Engliſh and Romiſh Hierarchiſts, neither hath there been any ſacriledge committed by thoſe which have unbiſhopped them, but they have been reſtored to the Digni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of Evangeliſts, from which the Prelates have ſacrilegiouſly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>graded them, that ſo they might on the ruines of the fore-mentio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned Evangeliſts honour build up their Epiſcopall Soveraignty. I might be large in proving this, that <hi>Timothy</hi> and <hi>Titus</hi> were Evan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geliſts, but the work is already ſufficiently done by others; Onely, I will (leaſt our Hierarchiſts ſhould ſay that this is the aſſertion of none but their oppoſites) put them in minde what<note n="g" place="margin">Video Time<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theum proculdu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bio Epiſcopum generalem, <hi>i. e.</hi> Apoſtolum nul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>li certae ſedi ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buc alligatum ab ipſo Paulo vocari ſuum adjutorem de rep Eccl. l. <hi>2.</hi> ca. <hi>3.</hi> n <hi>60.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Antonius de Dominis</hi> hath obſerved concerning <hi>Timothie,</hi> long after the firſt Epiſtle written to him, even when the Apoſtle wrote his Epiſtle to the Romans (which was about the time of his laſt journey to Hie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalem, as is cleare by paralleling thoſe two places of Scripture, <hi>Rom.</hi> 15.25. <hi>Act.</hi> 24.17, 18.) to wit, that <hi>he was out of doubt a ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall Biſhop,</hi> i. e. <hi>an Apoſtle, as yet confined to no certain ſeat.</hi> So that if <hi>Spalatenſis</hi> ſpeake truth, his Epiſcopacie of Epheſus is gone, for he was not yet ſaith he confined to any certain See. And as hee
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:111196:14"/>was not then when <hi>Paul</hi> wrote that Epiſtle to the Romans, ſo nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther was he when the ſame Apoſtle wrote his ſecond Epiſtle to <hi>Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mothie</hi> himſelfe. Conſider the charge which the Apoſtle there gives him;<note n="h" place="margin">2 Tim. 4.5.</note> 
               <hi>Doe the worke of an Evangelist, make full proofe of thy Ministery;</hi> He doth not ſay, <hi>Doe the worke of a Biſhop,</hi> then had our Prelatiſts ſome colour for their aſſertions, but <hi>of an Evan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geliſt,</hi> now it is well knowne that the Apoſtle ſetteth the<note n="i" place="margin">Epheſ. 4.</note> 
               <hi>Evan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geliſts</hi> as Perſons whoſe calling was extraordinarie above the ſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding and ordinary governours of the Church, <hi>Pastors and Teachers.</hi> Thoſe are by the Apoſtle there ſtiled Evangeliſts who did <hi>Evange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lizare ſine Cathedra,</hi> as<note n="k" place="margin">
                  <hi>in</hi> Eph 4.</note> 
               <hi>Ambroſe</hi> ſpeakes, Preach the Goſpel up and downe not being confined to Reſidence on any one peculiar charge. We have S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
               <hi>Paul</hi> profeſſing that on him did lye the<note n="l" place="margin">2 Cor. 11.27.</note> 
               <hi>Care of all the Churches,</hi> and oft expreſſing his deſire in his own perſon to come to them to confirme and ſtrengthen their faith, which when he could not do he ſent theſe two (not to mention any more) ſometimes to one Church, ſometimes to another, but being now im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſoned at Rome, and having once anſwered before <hi>Nero</hi> already, knowing that he<note n="m" place="margin">Ac. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>0.</note> 
               <hi>ſhould never ſee their faces any more,</hi> as he ſaid to thoſe Elders of Epheſus, that<note n="n" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Tim. 4.6.</note> 
               <hi>the time of his departure was at hand,</hi> as he ſpeakes to <hi>Timothy,</hi> he puts him in minde of that Office whereto he was choſen in an extraordinary manner<note n="o" place="margin">1 Tim. 1.14. Chap. 4.14.</note> 
               <hi>by the prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſies which went before concerning him,</hi> (For theſe extraordinary Offices had an extraordinary manner of vocation alſo (as ſundry<note n="p" place="margin">Vide Bez. Aq. Lyr. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſpenc. So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to major in loc.</note> Divines teſtifie concerning <hi>Timothy,</hi> induced thereto by the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentioned paſſages of Scripture) Doe the work of an Evangeliſt, which what it was, <hi>Euſebius</hi> doth ſet forth at large, where he ſpeaks of ſome who performed it thus;<note n="q" place="margin">Euſeb. Eccl. hiſt. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>i. <hi>3</hi> ca. <hi>34.</hi> edit Eaſil. an. <hi>1570.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>they did preach Chriſt to thoſe which had not as yet heard the word of faith, they delivered unto them the holy Scriptures, ordained Paſtors, and committed unto them the charge of thoſe which were newly received into the Church, and then they did</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>paſſe over unto other countries and nations.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Whereas it is demanded,<note n="r" place="margin">
                  <hi>Biſhop</hi> Hall, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>. cit. p. <hi>118.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>how ſhould thoſe Works of Ordination and execution of Church cenſures, Which are conſtant and ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, and ſo conſequently deriveable to all ſucceſſions, to the end of the World, be impoſed upon a meere extraordinary agent;</hi> this is a demand ſo ſenſeleſſe and voide of all reaſon that I wonder it ſhould
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:111196:14"/>fall from the pen of ſo learned and grave a Divine as D<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>Hall;</hi> but if he deſire an anſwere, I will returne it him in the words of <hi>Saravia</hi> (a friend and fellow-ſtickler in their cauſe) who will informe him; that<note n="ſ" place="margin">Gradus mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrorom evan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gelli itaſu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſſe diſt inctos ut majores inclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derent in eris<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum miniſteriae. Sar. ad cap. <hi>1.</hi> Bez. de div. gra. Min. Evang.</note> 
               <hi>The degrees of the Ministers of the Gospel were ſo diſtingui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed, that the greater did include the Ministeries of the leſſer.</hi> To the ſame purpoſe ſpeakes <hi>Cajetan</hi> (<hi>in Epheſ.</hi> 4.) ſo that whatſoever were the acts of an ordinary and ſtanding Miniſter of the Goſpel, the extraordinary Officer might performe them; albeit the Ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry officers might not preſume with the execution of thoſe which belonged to the extraordinary.</p>
            <p n="2">2. If the Precepts given here in charge to <hi>Timothy</hi> and <hi>Titus</hi> concerne a Biſhop alone, then doth it concerne a Biſhop alone to<note n="ſ" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Tim. 4.2.</note> 
               <hi>Preach the word in ſeaſon and out of ſeaſon,</hi> to<note n="t" place="margin">Ch 1.6.1. <hi>Ep.</hi> Chap. 4.4.</note> 
               <hi>ſtirre up the gift of God that is in him, and not neglect it,</hi> to take heed to himſelf and his doctrine; to flee covetouſneſſe, and follow after righteouſneſſe, godlineſſe, faith, love. Theſe with many other precepts belong alſo to the Biſhop and to him alone. If our adverſaries in this cauſe ſhall anſwer, that theſe are duties belonging to all Miniſters wherein they and Biſhops doe participate, but the other mentioned by them be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long to a Biſhop diſtinct from a Presbyter; I ſhall return them the ſame reply which <hi>Gerſom Bucerus</hi> doth to D<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>Downham,</hi>
               <note n="u" place="margin">Bucer. p. <hi>283.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Quem istius distinctionis authorem proferemus?</hi> Who hath taught us or them ſo to diſtinguiſh; Surely the Apoſtle hath not, for he makes not the leaſt mention of what belongs to <hi>Timothy</hi> as a Biſhop, what to him as a Presbyter; but gives all the commands promiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuouſly without any difference.</p>
            <p n="3">3. For as much as thoſe charges given to <hi>Timothy</hi> and <hi>Titus</hi> are ſo much inſiſted on, to prove their Epiſcopall Power, and conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently the Power and Preeminence of Biſhops above Presbyters by the Apoſtles practice and recommendation, I will take into con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration ſome of thoſe which are materiall, and ſee what ſtrength they afford unto the cauſe.</p>
            <p>That command given by the Apoſtle to <hi>Timothy,</hi> Lay hands ſuddenly on no man, and his appointing of <hi>Titus</hi> to ordaine Elders in every citie is ſtrongly urged by the ſticklers for Epiſcopall Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raignty, to prove that the Power of Ordination was in their hands alone. Be there what Elders ſoever in Epheſus, there hands with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out a <hi>Timothy</hi> will not ſerve to ordaine, his without theirs might,
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:111196:15"/>ſaith Biſhop<note n="a" place="margin">
                  <hi>Pa.</hi> 113.</note> 
               <hi>Hall;</hi> very confidently, but under favour, and with re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect to his gray haires, very weakly. Who ſeeth not how weak an inference this is, <hi>Timothy</hi> is commanded not to ordaine any man ſuddenly, Therefore <hi>Timothy</hi> alone had power to ordaine: the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequent may on juſt ground be denyed. The Preſident of a Colledge may be in a letter charged to take heed he admit not ſuddenly any man to a fellowſhip in the Colledge, will it therefore follow that the power of Election and admittance is in the hands of the Preſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent alone. For as much as this anſwer of thoſe which are oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſites to the Hierarchie, who ſay that <hi>Timothy</hi> and <hi>Titus</hi> were to or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daine, not by their owne power alone, but by way of Partnerſhip and Societie with the Presbyterie, joyning with them, is rejected by<note n="b" place="margin">
                  <hi>P.</hi> 115.</note> Biſhop <hi>Hall,</hi> as being <hi>ſo palpable, and quite againſt the haire, that he cannot think the authours of it can beleeve themſelves:</hi> I will therefore endeavour to confirme it, and make it good.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Since the Biſhop will not beleeve what his Oppoſites ſay, I would deſire to know whether the Biſhop doth beleeve that S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
               <hi>Paul</hi> would inveſt <hi>Timothy</hi> and <hi>Titus</hi> with a greater power then he himſelfe, or the Apoſtles did exerciſe. Now it is cleare that he did not aſſume the power of Ordination into his owne hands, to execute it by himſelfe, but in it, though he were as Preſident to conduct and guide the action, did conjoyne with himſelfe the Presbyters in the Ordination of <hi>Timothy.</hi> For albeit in<note n="c" place="margin">1 Tim. 1.6.</note> one place he ſpeaketh of the impoſition of his own hands alone, yet in<note n="d" place="margin">Chap. 4.14.</note> another he mentions the Presbytery as concurring with him in it. Beſides, the Ordinati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the Presbyters at Antioch, was not the act of <hi>Paul</hi> alone, but <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>Barnabas</hi> at leaſt, or rather by comparing it with other places, <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>Barnabas</hi> with the Presbyters of Antioch, did joyne together in the Ordination. The phraſe runnes in the plurall number,<note n="e" place="margin">Act. 14.236</note> 
               <hi>when they had ordained them Elders, and had prayed with faſting.</hi> From whence <hi>Gerſom Bucerus</hi> doth argue thus,<note n="f" place="margin">Doſſer. de gu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. Eccl. p <hi>321.</hi>
               </note> If the Hierarchiſts doe on juſt ground perſwade us that Ordinati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on doth belong to the Biſhops, becauſe the Apoſtles, whom the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops (as they ſay) doe ſucceed, did ordaine, by the ſame reaſon may Presbyters alſo ordaine, becauſe the 70. Diſciples (whom the Preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byters doe ſucceed, as they informe us) did ordaine. For <hi>Barna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bas</hi> is by many Hiſtorians reckoned among the 70. Diſciples. If we look further into the actions of the Apoſtles, we ſhall finde all their
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:111196:15"/>Ordinations not by their own power, but by the joynt conſent and concurrence of the Presbyters and Diſciples. When<note n="g" place="margin">Act. 1. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. <hi>Chryſ. hom.</hi> 3. <hi>in</hi> Act. <hi>c.</hi> 1.</note> 
               <hi>Matthias</hi> was choſen into the roome of <hi>Judas, Peter doth all by the common conſent of the Diſciples, nothing by his own authority, nothing like a Lord or Prince in a commanding manner,</hi> as <hi>Chryſoſtome</hi> hath obſerved. So in the Ordination of the<note n="h" place="margin">Chap. 6.</note> Deacons they carry them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves as Presbyters not as Apoſtles in the action, permitting the election to the Diſciples, concurring with the Presbyters in the Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dination of them. Adde hereunto one inſtance more out of the book of God. The command of the holy Ghoſt concerning <hi>Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nabas</hi> and <hi>Saul,</hi>
               <note n="i" place="margin">Chap. 13.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> Separate me <hi>Barnabas</hi> and <hi>Saul</hi> for the worke whereunto I have appointed them. <hi>Paul</hi> had his call to the Apoſtle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip immediately from the Lord ſome yeares before this; and <hi>Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nabas</hi> his call to the Miniſtery, for both of them had joyned together in the work of<note n="k" place="margin">Chap. 11.26.</note> Antioch, but being now by the Lords appoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to goe to the Gentiles, and preach the Goſpel unto them (for that ſeemeth to be the great worke here ſpoken of by the Lord, as<note n="l" place="margin">De rep hu. l. <hi>2.</hi> c. <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</hi> n. <hi>13.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Spalatenſis</hi> hath rightly obſerved) they are now commanded to be in a ſolemne manner ſet apart for this worke. As the Lord him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe by a voyce from Heaven gives them their immediate call, and Authoritative Deſignation for this Office, ſo their Externall Deſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation to it they have by his appointment alſo, not from any one particular perſon, either Biſhop or Presbyter, but from all thoſe in the Church of Antioch which miniſtred to the Lord; for ſo S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
               <hi>Luke</hi> ſets it down,<note n="m" place="margin">Cha. 13, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, 3.</note> 
               <hi>As they miniſtred to the Lord, and faſted, the Holy Ghost ſaid, Separate me Barnabas and Saul, for the work where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto I have called them. And when they had fasted, and prayed, and laid their hands on them, they ſent them away.</hi> From all which by the practice of the Apoſtles, and by this voyce of God from heaven, it is cleare, as farre as I can apprehend, that the Power of Ordinati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on or Deputation to the Miniſtery, and worke of the Lord therein, ſhould not, doth not reſide in the hand of any one particular perſon of what degree ſoever, either Biſhop or Presbyter, but of the colle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctive body of Paſtours and Presbyters which miniſter unto the Lord.</p>
            <p n="2">2. If the Biſhop will not beleeve his Oppoſites, ſuch as <hi>Parker</hi> that proud Schiſmaticke, or <hi>Cartwright</hi> and <hi>Ames</hi> with their ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norant and malecontented, followers, ſome giddy corner-creeping
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:111196:16"/>upſtarts,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pag.</hi> 60, 61. <hi>&amp;</hi> 148.</note> (theſe are not mine but Biſhop <hi>Halls</hi> titles of honour wherewith he doth beſpatter them) if the judgement of Divines of greateſt note in the Reformed Churches will ſtrike any ſtroke, we have them concurring in this, that The Power of Ordination is in the hands of the Presbyters, not of any one alone; that though theſe charges are given to <hi>Timothy</hi> and <hi>Titus</hi> in particular, yet doth it not follow that they alone could doe it. I will onely mention one of many that might be alledged. When <hi>Pamelius</hi> from thoſe places undertakes to prove the Superioritie of Biſhops above Presbyters, <hi>Gonlartius</hi> anſwereth him thus,<note n="n" place="margin">Annot. in Cyp. ep. <hi>65.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>The argument hath not ſtrength</hi> enough in it, Presbyters are ordained by Biſhops, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore Biſhops are above them. The ancient Biſhops were ordained by the Clergie and the people, if any ſhall thence inferre, therefore the Clergie and people are above the Biſhops, <hi>Pamelius</hi> and his Schollars will deny the Conſequence, Ordination doth not eſtabliſh a degree or <hi>Preeminence, but only ſheweth and commendeth the Diſcipline of the Church.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. Beſides Proteſtants, we have Papiſts aſſenting to this truth, and confeſſing 1. that Presbyters may ordain.<note n="p" place="margin">Gloſſ. in diſt. <hi>66</hi> cap. Porrò.</note> 
               <hi>Johannes Semeca</hi> in his Gloſſe on the Canon Law, proves it by this, <hi>the Apoſtles were but Preſbyters not Biſhops, yet they did ordaine, and in their dayes there was no difference between a Preſbyter and a Biſhop.</hi> And<note n="q" place="margin">Antiſ San ap. Apol. Epiſc. p. <hi>165.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Altiſſiodorenſis</hi> hath delivered it, that <hi>if there were but three Preſbyters in the World, they might ordaine one the other, a biſhop and an Archbiſhop,</hi> and gives this reaſon for it, <hi>Preſbyters as well as Biſhops doe receive the Keyes of the Kingdome in their Ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, for they are the ſucceſſours of the Apoſtles.</hi> 2. That <hi>Titus</hi> was left at Crete to ordaine Presbyters no otherwiſe then as a Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derator in the action, and as a Conſul or Dictator are ſaid to create Conſuls; becauſe they are, they hold, the Comitia or Aſſembly and meeting in which they are created. Thus<note n="r" place="margin">
                  <hi>In</hi> Tit. 1. <hi>d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſp.</hi> 1.</note> 
               <hi>Salmeron,</hi> as I ſhall af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terward ſhew more at large out of him. By this time I hope it doth appeare that this is not ſo palpable an eluſion as the Biſhop is pleaſed to ſtile it, but rather ſo manifeſt a truth, which the Biſhop himſelf nor all the mitred Fathers of that order are able to diſprove. Thus much for Ordination from thoſe charges, I proceed to the next.</p>
            <p>That precept of the Apoſtle,<note n="x" place="margin">1 Tim. 5.1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> 
               <hi>Againſt an Elder or Preſbyter
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:111196:16"/>receive not an accuſation, but before two or three witneſſes,</hi> is mainly inſiſted on by D<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>Hall</hi> and others, to prove that <hi>Timothy</hi> was inveſted with Epiſcopall Juriſdiction, and ſo to conclude the Juriſdictionall Preeminence of a Biſhop over the Presbyters, yet the weakneſſe of this argument hath bin already ſufficiently diſcovered, and the place anſwered to the full by our Polemicall Divines which have diſputed againſt Papiſts, from whom our Hierarchiſts have borrowed moſt of their weapons which they make uſe of in this quarrell. It ſhall be therefore ſufficient for me to mention the an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer which is given by our Proteſtant Divines to their Romiſh Op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſites in this cauſe. Firſt, our Countreyman D<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>Whitakers</hi> anſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth <hi>Bellarmine</hi> that this place proves not <hi>Timothies</hi> power over Presbyters, and from this place obſerveth that the power of Juriſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction was not in the hand of one, but of many that were endued with equall authoritie.<note n="y" place="margin">Quod Timotheus jubetur non temere <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> admittere, hoc non probat Timotheum in Presbyteros poteſtatem aut do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minatum habuiſſe. Nam ex Apoſtoli mente <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> eſt crimen ad Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiam deſerre, reum in judicium addacere, pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lam reprehendere, quod non modo ſuperiore<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> poſſunt, ſed aequales etiam at<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> inferiores. In Romana Repub. Equites non de populo tantum ſed etiam de Senatoribus &amp; Patrioiis judica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bant. Et certè non videtur Timotheus tale con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtorium aut forum babuiſſe, quale poſt Epiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>copis in Eccleſia conſtitutum ſuit, nam hi Preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byteri non alii quam Epiſcopi fuerunt ut ex Apoſtolo conſtat. — Qualis haec authoritas ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit ex eo quod ſequitur intelligi poteſt, Eos qui peccant coram omnibus <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, quod aequales quo<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> poſſunt. Sic elim Ep<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſcopeſiquis Presby<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>es aut Epiſcopus male auauet, ad Senatum Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>icum aut Synoaum reſerebant, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>um<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> ſi d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>gnus videretur <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ublico jud<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>cio damnabant, <hi>i. e.</hi> cut ſuspendebant, aut excommunicabant, aut removebant. <hi>Whitak.</hi> co. t. <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>.1.</hi> c. <hi>2.</hi> ſc. <hi>16.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>According to the meaning of the Apostle to receive an ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſation is to acquaint the Church with the crime, and to bring the offender into judgement, openly to reprove which not onely ſuperiours, but equals alſo, yea and inferiours may doe. The Knights of Rome did not only judge the people, but the Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natours and Noble-men alſo if they were delinquents. Certainly</hi> Timothy <hi>had no ſuch Conſistory or Court as was after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards attributed to the Biſhops. What this authority was may be underſtood from that which followeth, Them that ſin re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buke before all; which equals alſo may doe. Thus of old the Biſhops, if a Biſhop or Preſbyter were accuſed, did referre the matter to the Eccleſiaſticall Senate or Synod, and did condemne him if he were found worthy,</hi> i. e. <hi>they did ſuſpend, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>communicate, or remove him according to the nature of his of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence.</hi> Thus that Divinitie Profeſſour of <hi>Cambridge</hi> in his dayes. And that this was the manner of proceeding in adminiſtration of Church cenſures, appeares by our Saviours precept concerning other
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:111196:17"/>Offenders though private perſons,<note n="z" place="margin">Matth. 18.</note> 
               <hi>Dic Eccleſiae,</hi> Tell the Church; and the ſentence of Excommunication pronounced and executed on the inceſtuous perſon at Corinth; It was not the act of a Biſhop alone or of his Officiall or Chancellour (theſe are Apocryphall names and offices, unknowne for ſome Centuries of yeares in the Church of Chriſt) but it was<note n="a" place="margin">2 Cor. 2.6.</note> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>a Puniſhment inflicted by many.</hi> 2. I may adde the anſwer of <hi>Gonlartius</hi> unto <hi>Pamelius</hi> objecting this place of the Apoſtle to <hi>Timothy</hi> for the proofe of Epiſcopall Preeminence over Presbyters.<note n="b" place="margin">Annot. in Cypr. Epiſt. <hi>65.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>An accuſati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on is two wayes received either privately or in the Eccleſiaſticall aſſembly which doth judge of thoſe crimes.</hi> This though it be taken as ſpoken to <hi>Timothy</hi> alone, yet implieth, as he there ſhewes onely a preheminence of Order in <hi>Timothy</hi> not of power and authority. Which he thus makes good; if a Biſhop were accuſed the Presbyters did receive the accuſation and judge of it; as he proves out of <hi>Cy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prian,</hi> who<note n="c" place="margin">Epiſt. <hi>65.</hi> old. <hi>3</hi> Ep. <hi>9.</hi>
               </note> writes to <hi>Epictetus</hi> and the people of Aſſura com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manding them not to admit to the Epiſcopacie againe <hi>Eortunatia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus</hi> who ſometimes was their Biſhop, but had denyed the faith of Chriſt. <hi>Other Biſhops,</hi> ſaith <hi>Gonlartius, are not called together, nor is there any appeale to the Biſhop of Rome, but the Aſſuritan Church in a convenient order judgeth their own Biſhop. In the Preſbyterie one of the Preſbyters or Ministers of the Church did fit, for orders-ſake onely, untill thoſe degrees did ariſe of which we have elſewhere ſpoken. Therefore to receive an accuſation againſt one is not only a note of preheminence, but of order alſo, and that preheminence doth not confirme thoſe degrees which afterwards introduced tyranny into the Church, but manifeſteth an eutaxie in the houſe of God.</hi> This ſhall ſuffice to be ſpoken touching that branch of Epiſcopall Juriſdiction; I come to another, and that con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cernes the Commiſſion given to <hi>Timothy</hi> concerning the Doctrine of the Teachers.</p>
            <p>
               <note n="d" place="margin">
                  <hi>Epiſc</hi> by. di<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. right. <hi>p.</hi> 106.</note> 
               <hi>Timothy</hi> is charged to charge the Preachers of Epheſus, that they teach no other doctrine, that they doe not give heed to Fables and Genealogies and<note n="e" place="margin">
                  <hi>Pag.</hi> 116.</note> 
               <hi>Titus</hi> is commanded <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> to ſtop the mouths of thoſe falſe teachers, who broach doctrines they ought not for filthy lucres ſake, and to paſſe ſharp cenſures upon them, what can doe this but Epiſcopall authority, ſaith the Biſhop;<note place="margin">Pag. <hi>107.</hi>
               </note> I may truly ſay (ſaith he) that both S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
               <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>Timothy</hi> his Diſciple doe
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:111196:17"/>as truly Lord it here in their Epiſcopall power, as thoſe Biſhops which they (the Scots) have abdicated.</p>
            <p>I will not here <hi>Camerinam movere,</hi> rake into the ſinke of the Lordly tyrannicall exorbitancies of our later Prelates, they ſtinke bad enough already, I will not cauſe the Reader to ſtop his noſe at thoſe putrid ſteemes which would ariſe if that puddle were ſtirred. Onely I would deſire the Reader by the way to conſider that S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
               <hi>Paul</hi> hath profeſſedly diſclaimed all Lording it over the conſcien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of the Corinthians:<note n="f" place="margin">2 Cor. 1.14.</note> 
               <hi>Not that we have dominion over your faith,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>but are helpers of your joy; for by faith ye ſtand.</hi>
               <note n="g" place="margin">In locum.</note> 
               <hi>Cajetan</hi> hath well obſerved that this is here added by the Apoſtle to exclude a calumnie, which might have been caſt on him, becauſe the words of <hi>Paul</hi> which he ſpake immediately before, <hi>viz. to ſpare you,</hi> might ſeeme to imply ſome dominion, he preſently ſubjoynes this, <hi>Not that we have dominion over your faith,</hi> which words are fitly and fully paraphraſed by <hi>Beza</hi> thus,<note n="h" place="margin">Ineund. locum.</note> 
               <hi>Not as if I might doe any thing amongſt you in matter of Religion, What I pleaſed by my power in binding and looſing of your conſciences, but I am the Minister of God to comfort you and to cheere your hearts; we are helpers of your joy, wherein he doth ſecretly oppoſe the joy and peace of Conſcience, Where of he makes God the authour, but himſelfe and his colleagues the Miniſters, unto that tyrannicall terrour which is cauſed by thoſe who carry themſelves as if they were Lords over the conſciences of both Miniſters and people.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>We doe not ſay that either <hi>Timothy</hi> or <hi>Titus</hi> were meere Preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byters, and ſo compeeres or Equals to the Presbyters of Epheſus or Crete, nor were they Biſhops ſuch as you fancy them, and in that ſuperiority of degree above them; but Evangeliſts of an higher Orbe then either Biſhops, for which you plead, or Presbyters. Looke on them in that degree wherein they were, and they might on bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter grounds, with more authority charge falſe teachers, that they ſhould not <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> teach any other doctrine then what the Apoſtles had taught; (for unto that the<note n="i" place="margin">Gal. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.8, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> Apoſtle himſelfe doth limit it, doubling his <hi>Anathema</hi> on the heads of them whoſoever they were that ſhould doe it) then any ordinary Biſhop whatſoever, if there had been then any ſuch diſtinct from Presbyters. The caſe is cleare concerning them both, they had been the Apoſtles compani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons in his travailes, had been fully inſtructed in the doctrine which
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:111196:18"/>he preached, and in reſpect of their familiar converſing with him, they could avouch what truth he had delivered. That of <hi>Paul</hi> to <hi>Timothy,</hi> the pretended Biſhop of Epheſus is clear for him.<note n="k" place="margin">2 Tim. 3.10.</note> 
               <hi>Thou hast fully knowne my doctrine, manner of life.</hi>
               <note n="l" place="margin">
                  <hi>Ib.</hi> ver. 14.</note> 
               <hi>Continue thou in the things which thou haſt learned, and haſt been aſſured of, know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of whom thou haſt learned them.</hi> As for <hi>Titus</hi> (touching whom Biſhop<note n="m" place="margin">
                  <hi>Pag.</hi> 117.</note> 
               <hi>Hall</hi> is pleaſed to tell us, there is no colour to ſay he was an Evangeliſt) not to inſiſt on the frequent uſe which the Apoſtle made of him, in ſending him from one Church to another, conſider what falſe teachers they are whoſe mouths the Apoſtle would have in an eſpeciall manner to be ſtopped, they are<note n="n" place="margin">Tit. 1.10.</note> thoſe of the Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſion. Them <hi>Titus</hi> could more effectually convince and confound with greater authoritie then any other man whatſoever. For he could in reſpect of his owne perſon declare what priviledge S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
               <hi>Paul</hi> pleaded for, to wit, exemption from the yoke of Circumciſion.<note n="o" place="margin">Gal. 2.</note> 
               <hi>Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus was not cicumciſed by reaſon of falſe brethren, who creptin un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>awares to ſpie out our liberty which we have in Christ Jeſus that they might bring us again into bondage;</hi> this was done by the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpoſition of Apoſtolike authority, when others would have urged it. Yea, more then this, when <hi>Paul</hi> himſelfe with the choſen Elders from the Churches of Antioch went by revelation to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferre with the Apoſtles Elders and brethren concerning that vexa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious queſtion moved by ſome falſe teachers, who pretended the conſent of the Apoſtles with them, in that which they obtruded on the Gentiles, the neceſſity of Circumciſion,<note n="p" place="margin">Gal. 2.1.</note> 
               <hi>Titus</hi> was one of thoſe who went up with the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> to the Apoſtles at Jeru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalem; him and <hi>Barnabas</hi> did S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
               <hi>Paul</hi> take along with him, to be<note n="q" place="margin">Par. lect <hi>14.</hi> in Ep. ad <hi>Gal.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>witneſſes both before the Apoſtles of his doctrine preached among the Gentiles, and alſo to the Churches of his action with the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles,</hi> and their concurrence with him giving him the right hand of fellowſhip. Now conſider, I pray you, what was one ſpeciall privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of the Apoſtles, thoſe whom our Saviour himſelfe made choiſe of, to whom he did renew and enlarge his commiſſion after his Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection; and you ſhall finde that <hi>Titus</hi> was a ſharer in a privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge next removed unto it, but one degree below them. They were eye and eare-witneſſes of the doctrine, miracles, ſufferings and Reſurrection of the Lord Jeſus Chriſt, as is cleare from that<note n="r" place="margin">Act. 1.21, 22.</note> ſpeech of <hi>Peter</hi> (at the election of <hi>Matthias</hi> in the roome of <hi>Judas</hi>) and
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:111196:18"/>what elſewhere he writeth to the diſperſed Jewes,<note n="ſ" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Pet. 1.16, 18.</note> 
               <hi>We were eye-witneſſes of his Majeſty; and this voice we heard.</hi> The priviledge of an Evangeliſt was this; theſe things concerning Chriſt were<note n="ſ" place="margin">Luke 1.2.</note> 
               <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livered unto them by thoſe which from the beginning were eye-witneſſes, and miniſters of the Word.</hi> As the Apoſtles were Chriſts Attendants, and<note n="t" place="margin">Chap. 22.28.</note> 
               <hi>continued with him in all his temptations,</hi> ſo the Evangeliſts were <hi>Apoſtolorum comites,</hi> the Apoſtles companions in all their travailes and peregrinations, fellow-workers and helpers in the Miniſtery. <hi>Titus</hi> then being an eye-witneſſe and an eare-wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe not only of S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
               <hi>Pauls</hi> preaching among the Gentiles, but of the Apoſtles determination and concluſion in their Synodicall de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cree touching Circumciſion, might with farre more authoritie ſtop the mouthes of thoſe falſe teachers of the Circumciſion, then any ordinary Biſhop or Paſtour whatſoever. By this time, I hope, it is evident that the charge given to <hi>Timothy</hi> and <hi>Titus</hi> makes nothing for Epiſcopall authoritie and Juriſdiction. 2. There is no neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie to limit and reſtrain that phraſe of the Apoſtles,<note n="u" place="margin">Tit. 1.</note> 
               <hi>whoſe mouths muſt be ſtopped</hi> to an authoritative and judiciarie ſilencing of a falſe teacher, <hi>Cajetan</hi> extends it unto a<note n="*" place="margin">Authoritate &amp; doctrina. <hi>Cajet.</hi> in loc.</note> Doctrinall as well as a Defi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitive ſilencing by a ſentence againſt him.<note n="m" place="margin">Sckol. in loc.</note> 
               <hi>Piſcator</hi> hath obſerved that <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> is the ſame with <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, which latter word is uſed ſometimes to expreſſe ſuch a ſtopping of the mouth and ſilencing as is the fruit of a doctrinall conviction; and confutation by evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence of Scripture. So the Evangeliſt S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
               <hi>Matthew</hi> uſeth it,<note n="*" place="margin">Matt 22.34. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> 
               <hi>When the Phariſees had heard that he</hi> (Chriſt) <hi>had put the Sadduces to ſilence,</hi> which was done not by any definitive ſentence pronounced in a judiciary manner againſt them, authoritatively commanding them to hold their peace and preach ſuch falſe doctrine no more, but by teſtimonie of Scripture was their errour ſo fully diſcovered that they had not a word to reply for themſelves in maintainance of their erroneous opinions.<note n="x" place="margin">Ibid.</note> 
               <hi>Ye erre, becauſe ye know not the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, nor the power of God. Have ye not read what God ſaid unto Moſes in the buſh, &amp;c.</hi> Of this kind of ſilencing or ſtopping the mouth the Apoſtle ſpeakes in this place, as is evident by what goes before and what followes. Amongſt the qualifications of a Biſhop, <hi>i. e.</hi> a Presbyter, as you ſhall ſee anone, this is one, he muſt<note n="y" place="margin">Tit. 1.5.</note> 
               <hi>Hold faſt the faithfull word as he hath been taught, that he may be able by ſound doctrine both to exhort, and to convince the gainſayers.</hi>
               <pb n="30" facs="tcp:111196:19"/>Why is this required, the words following ſhew the reaſon,<note n="a" place="margin">Ver. 10, 11.</note> 
               <hi>For there are many unruly and vaine talkers and deceivers, ſpecially they of the circumciſion whoſe mouths must be ſtopped.</hi> This ſtop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping of the mouth here ſpoken of muſt be by a Conviction from ſound doctrine. Then conſider what followes immediately,<note n="b" place="margin">Ver. 13.</note> 
               <hi>This witneſſe is true, wherefore reprove them ſharply, that they may be ſound in the faith.</hi> You ſee ſtill the ſilencing is by a conviction, and a doctrinall confutation, ſo is the noune uſed when the Apoſtle ſaith of the Scripture, <hi>it is profitable</hi>
               <note n="c" place="margin">2 Tim. 3.16.</note> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>for conviction</hi> or con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>futation, ſo the compound of the Verbe, in that phraſe of the Evan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geliſt concerning <hi>Apollos,</hi>
               <note n="d" place="margin">Act. 18. laſt. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> 
               <hi>he mightily convinced the Jewes,</hi> to wit, by the clear evidence of Scripture which could not be gain-ſaid or ſhifted off by any ſophiſticall evaſions whatſoever. But where the word <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> is uſed to ſignifie the paſſing of ſharp cenſures, I ſhall not be aſhamed to confeſſe my ignorance, but am willing to be informed by my betters, Biſhop <hi>Hall</hi> or any of his brethren. See<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Apoſtle here ſpeakes of a doctrinall ſilencing and confutati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, I hope this is not a priviledge faſtned to an Epiſcopall chaire, but ſuch as is communicable to a Presbyter.</p>
            <p>Thus much ſhall ſuffice to be ſpoken concerning theſe charges gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven to <hi>Timothy</hi> and <hi>Titus,</hi> by which the Doctor hath undertaken to prove them to be inveſted with Epiſcopall power and Juriſdicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, but how well, let others judge. There is one thing more in theſe pages which will deſerve a like animadverſion; it is a paſſage, which had it fallen from the pen of any other then Doctor <hi>Hall,</hi> I ſhould have thought the man had certainly a Pope in his belly; it is this.<note n="c" place="margin">
                  <hi>Pag.</hi> 108.</note> 
               <hi>That Houſe of God which is the Church</hi> (<hi>wherein</hi> Timothies <hi>behaviour is ſo required</hi>) <hi>is not ſome one private congregation, ſuch an one were not fit for that ſtile the pillar and ground of truth, but the famous Dioceſan Church of Epheſus.</hi> Me thinks the phraſe here uſed, and ſtile of ſome other of late amongſt us, comes ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what neere to that of the Jeſuites mentioned by Doctor <hi>Bilſin;</hi>
               <note n="f" place="margin">Differ. betw. Chriſt. ſubject. and unchriſt. rebel. <hi>p.</hi> 224. <hi>part.</hi> 2.</note> 
               <hi>This is,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>the right trade of your apologie to pretend the Church and meane the Pope.—And ſo you make the Church but a cloak-bag to carry the Popes titles after him.</hi> Our Cathedraliſts pretend the Church but meane the Biſhops and themſelves, and ſo the Church is made but a cloak-bag to carry the Dioceſans titles of honour after him. But why, I pray you, may not a particular pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:111196:19"/>congregation be ſtiled the pillar and ground of truth; There is no Orthodoxe Divine can be ignorant that the Church is ſaid to be the pillar of truth,<note place="margin">Non ratione ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chitect onica, ſed ſorenſi.</note> not as the notion of a pillar is taken by Architects in building, for that which doth uphold and beare up the roofe, or loft that lyeth on it, as if the Church did give ſupportance and ſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bilitie to the truth, but as a pillar in the market-place, to which the Kings Proclamation is faſtned, that all his ſubjects may take notice of it. Hath Chriſt faſtned his truth to a Cathedrall only, that there it is to be found, and no where elſe? The ſad experience of that ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norance, ſuperſtition, and profaneneſs which reigne in places neereſt unto them hath verified the Proverbe, The neerer the Church the further from God. <hi>Lyra</hi> though a popiſh Fryar, and one that lived in times of much blindneſſe, yet ſaw ſo much light that he could ſay;<note n="h" place="margin">
                  <hi>Lyra</hi> in Matt. c. 16.</note> 
               <hi>The Church conſists not in men of dignity and power, either Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiasticall or Secular; for many Princes and Popes with other in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feriour perſons have revolted from the faith: wherefore the Church conſiſts in thoſe perſons in whom is the true knowledge and confeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the faith.</hi> I would we had not too much cauſe to confeſſe the ſame of many of our Church-men, Prelates and their adherents, the Cathedrall Dioceſan crew, with others: but albeit there hath been an apoſtaſie in them, yet bleſſed be the Lord for it, we may truly ſay of the Church of <hi>England</hi> at this day, what once a<note n="i" place="margin">D<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                  <hi>Potter</hi> in his anſwer to <hi>Charitie miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taken.</hi>
               </note> Cathedraliſt ſpake in favour of the Church of Rome: <hi>The errours have been the errours of the domineering faction in the Court of England, not the errours of the Church of England.</hi> I hope they will give us leave to ſpeake as favourably of our mother the Church of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> as they of theirs the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> which is with them a true Church. I will ſhut up all that I ſhall ſay concerning <hi>Timothy</hi> and <hi>Titus,</hi> and the pretended Epiſcopall power committed unto them, the ſame as our Hierarchiſts ſay, with what they exerciſe, with the obſervation of a Friar, yet an<note n="k" place="margin">Hiſtorie of the Counc. of Trent. <hi>lib.</hi> 4. <hi>pag.</hi> 332.</note> Hiſtorian of good eſteeme, <hi>It is denyed in words that Eccleſiaſticall Juriſdiction is dominion, as is the ſecular, yet one knoweth not how to put a difference be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween them. But</hi> S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Paul <hi>did, when he wrote to</hi> Timothy, <hi>and repea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted it to</hi> Titus, <hi>that a Biſhop ſhould not be greedy of gaine, nor a ſtriker. Now on the contrary, they make men pay for proceſſes, and impriſon the parties, as is done in the ſecular Courts.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the next place, according to promiſe, I come to view the wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:111196:20"/>of the Apoſtles, and to enquire whether in them there be any ſuch Superiority and Diſtinction in Order and in Office between a Biſhop and a Presbyter, as is pretended by our Prelatiſts. If in this Scripture may be judge it is as cleare as the Sunne, in my apprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, that a Biſhop and a Presbyter are one and the ſame in Order and in Office. For when the Apoſtle doth ſet downe the ſacred or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, we find no other but theſe, Biſhops and Deacons, that which is by the Hierarchiſts made a middle order between both, to wit, of Presbyters is not at all expreſſed in diſtinction from the former, which doth evidently prove, that the diſtinction between a Biſhop and a Presbyter is but an inſtitution of man, not of God, nor hath it foundation in the Word of God. Conſider the Inſcription of S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
               <hi>Pauls</hi> Epiſtle to the Philippians, it is directed to<note n="l" place="margin">Phil. 1.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> 
               <hi>All the Saints in Chriſt Jeſus which are at Philippi, with the Biſhops and Dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cons.</hi> When <hi>Paul</hi> directeth <hi>Timothy</hi> how he ſhould carry himſelf in the Church of God, that is ſaith a late<note n="m" place="margin">Biſhop <hi>Hall, pag.</hi> 108.109.</note> Patron of Epiſcopacie, <hi>how he must carry himſelfe as a Dioceſan, in ſuch a Church where there would be need of all varietie of Church-Officers,</hi> we have no other Orders ſet downe then the fore-mentioned,<note n="n" place="margin">1 Tim. 3.</note> Biſhops and Deacons, together with the qualifications of the one and the other. I demand then of our Dioceſans now how comes it to paſſe that the order of Presbyters is left out. If Presbyters were a diſtinct order from Biſhops, and inferiour to them in place and power, would the Apoſtle have omitted them as unneceſſary and ſuperflu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous in ſuch a Church, as the Dioceſſe of Epheſus, yea of Aſia rather (for of that extent is the Church there mentioned by the Apoſtle ſaid to be, by our fore-mentioned Biſhop.) Come we from <hi>Timo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy</hi> to <hi>Titus,</hi> and view the Epiſtle directed unto him;<note n="o" place="margin">Tit. 1.5.</note> 
               <hi>He is left by the ſame Apoſtle at Creete, that he ſhould ſet in order the things that are wanting, and ordain Elders in every city.</hi> Of what ranke and order theſe Presbyters or Elders were, the verſes immediately following will informe us. The qualifications of thoſe which ſhould be admitted to this order, and be made Presbyters follow; <hi>If any be blameleſſe,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Verſ. 6.</note> 
               <hi>the huſband of one wife, having faithfull chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, not accuſed of riot, or unruly.</hi> Why muſt a Presbyter be ſuch an one,<note place="margin">Verſ. 7.</note> the next verſe gives the reaſon; <hi>For a Biſhop muſt be blame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe as the ſteward of God, not ſelfe-willed,</hi> &amp;c. Therefore muſt a Presbyter be blameleſſe, becauſe he is Gods ſteward, a Biſhop, an
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:111196:20"/>Overſeer (as the Greeke word properly imports, and ſo it is rendred by our late Tranſlators, <hi>Act.</hi> 20.) ſet over the Houſe of God. In a word, if the Apoſtles had in their dayes inſtituted any ſuch diſtinct order of Biſhops above Presbyters, then ſurely either in their laſt and valedictory ſpeeches to thoſe Presbyters whom they ordained, and Churches which they planted, or in their Epiſtles ſent unto them, we ſhould have ſome expreſſions tending to this purpoſe, ſome charge or other given either to the Biſhop how he ſhould car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry himſelfe towards the Presbyters under his power and Juriſdicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, or to the Presbyters how they ſhould behave themſelves to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward the Biſhop ſet over them. But we finde not the leaſt intima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of any ſuch thing; nor of one Biſhop ſet over many flocks and congregations, but rather of more Biſhops then one, which had the overſight of a flock. The command given to the Hebrewes is this,<note n="p" place="margin">Heb. 13.17.</note> 
               <hi>Obey them that have the rule over you, and ſubmit your ſelves, for they watch for your ſoules, as they that muſt give an account.</hi> He doth not ſay <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, Be obedient <hi>to the Biſhop</hi> that is over you, but <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, in the plurall number, <hi>them that have the rule over you, for they watch for your ſoules;</hi> it is too great a burthen for one to be intruſted with the over-ſight, and give an ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count for the ſoules in many congregations. The counſell of S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
               <hi>Paul</hi> to the Theſſalonians runs thus;<note n="q" place="margin">1 Theſ. 5.12.</note> 
               <hi>We beſeech you, brethren, to know them which labour among you, and</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>which are over you in the Lord.</hi> However in the writings of the Fathers, as the<note n="r" place="margin">Orig. of Epiſc. pag. <hi>5.</hi>
               </note> Archbiſhop of <hi>Armagh</hi> hath obſerved, which were ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what neere the Apoſtles dayes, the title of <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> (which is the ſame with the word here uſed by the Apoſtle) is limited unto one, whom other of the Fathers doe peculiarly terme a Biſhop (in what reſpect you ſhall heare more anon) yet, it is cleare by this pla<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> of the Apoſtle, that they confined not that Title unto one, nor did they ſet up one under that title or notion, Superiour to the reſt of the Presbyters, who laboured alſo in the word and doctrine. In which regard<note n="ſ" place="margin">Am<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>t in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>oc.</note> 
               <hi>Beza</hi> ſpake a truth, and no more but a truth, when he ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved from this and other places <hi>that the Church was governed, a Paſtoribus in communi, by the Paeſtors in common.</hi> or by the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon conſent and counſell of the Paſtours, <hi>the degree of Epiſcopacie b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ing not as yet invented</hi> or found out by the Apoſtles or Apoſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like men. Let us proceed, S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
               <hi>Peter</hi> commandeth the Presbyters
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:111196:21"/>to<note n="t" place="margin">1 Pet. 5.1, 2.</note> 
               <hi>feed the flock of God which is amongſt them,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>taking the overſight of them</hi> (or being and performing the office of Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops amongſt them) <hi>not by conſtraint, but willingly, not for filthy lucre, but of a ready mind.</hi> From which and other places it is clear, that in Scripture phraſe <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> is ſo farre from ſignifying an Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der diſtinct from, or ſuperiour to a Presbyter, that it imports no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther thing then the Office of a Presbyter; a truth which<note n="u" place="margin">Diſſert. <hi>1.</hi> de presb &amp; epiſc. cap <hi>6.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Salmaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us</hi> hath proved at large againſt <hi>Petavius</hi> the Jeſuite. Yea, the<note n="*" place="margin">Ibid. cap. <hi>3.</hi> pag. <hi>172.</hi>
               </note> ſame learned Critick hath obſerved that there is as much colour of reaſon to ſay that a Senatour and Counſellour were diſtinct Offices and Orders, as to ſay that a Biſhop and a Presbyter are different in Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice and in Order. For as the Senate and the Counſell did not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitute different bodies, but one and the ſame aſſembly was under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood by both denominations, ſo the particular members of that bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy were ſometimes called Senatours, ſometimes Counſellours. <hi>Idem est,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>de Preſbyterio &amp; Epiſcopio.</hi> The Presbyterie and the Epiſcopium were but one and the ſame body, and convention of Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops and Presbyters.</p>
            <p>The light of Scripture is ſo evident and convincing (unto all thoſe which doe not ſhut their eyes againſt it, being prepoſſeſſed with other fancies that from thence (to omit other teſtimonies of the Fathers, with ſundry Divines of note both Proteſtant and Popiſh)<note n="m" place="margin">Diſt. <hi>60.</hi> cap. Null. ex urb. Papa. Sacros or lines dicimus diaconatum &amp; Presbyteratum. Hos quidem ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tos eccleſia pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitiva habuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe dicitur.</note> 
               <hi>Gratian,</hi> and<note n="x" place="margin">Sent. lib. <hi>4.</hi> diſt. <hi>24.</hi> tit. <hi>1.</hi> Excellentèr cano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes duos tantum ſacros ordines appellari cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, diaconatus ſcil. &amp; presbytera<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>us, quia hos ſolos Eccleſia primitiva legetur habuiſſe, &amp; de bisſolis praeceptum Apoſtolihabemus.</note> 
               <hi>Peter Lumbard</hi> have confeſſed, <hi>that the Scripture mentioneth no other ſacred Orders then of Preſbyters and Deacons, the primitive Church is ſaid to have theſe onely, and we have the precept of the Apoſtle concerning theſe alone.</hi> As <hi>Gratian</hi> in his text of the Canon Law, ſo<note n="y" place="margin">Dicunt quidem quod in eccleſia prima primi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiva co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mune crat officium epiſcoporum &amp; ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerdotum, &amp; no mina crant communia. diſt. <hi>95.</hi> cap. Olim, &amp; officium crat commune: ſed in ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cunda primitiva caeperunt diſtingui &amp; nomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ua Presbyter et Epiſcopus erant prorſus ſynony<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma, &amp; etiam adminiſtratio co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>munis erat, quia communi conſitio ſacerdotum regebantur eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiae. In ſchiſmatis ergoremedium (ut bicdicitur) fact a eſt praelatio ut unus praeeſſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t &amp; quoad quaedam ſacramenta, quae modò appropriantur epiſcopis. Gloſſ. ikn diſt. <hi>95.</hi> cap. Legimus. verb. Poſtea.</note> 
               <hi>Johannes Semeca</hi> in his Gloſſe thereon tels us, <hi>In the firſt Primitive Church Biſhops and Preſbyters or Prieſts were all one, both in name and office; the names and offices began to be distingui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed in the ſecond primitive Church; when for a remedy of ſchiſme one was advanced in the Church (which was before gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned by the common conſent of Preſbyters)
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:111196:21"/>in reſpect of name, and adminiſtration, and ſome ſacraments, which are now appropriated to the Biſhops.</hi> Thus <hi>Semeca.</hi> If any ſhall deſire to know of what extent this firſt primitive Church is, none can better informe him then learned D<hi rend="sup">r</hi> USSHER, once Divinity Profeſſor at <hi>Dublin,</hi> now Archbiſhop of <hi>Armagh,</hi>
               <note n="z" place="margin">De ſucc. &amp; ſtatu Eccleſ. cap. <hi>1.</hi> pag. <hi>19.</hi>
               </note> who having obſerved out of <hi>Hegeſippus,</hi> that during the age of the Apoſtles the Church continued <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>a pure and unde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>filed Virgin,</hi> addes <hi>in matters of Religion we are not aſhamed to appeale to this first Primitive Church (for ſo it hath pleaſed ſome to distinguiſh)</hi> ſaith he, referring us in the margin to this fore-men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned Gloſſe of <hi>Semeca.</hi> And truly as in articles of faith and points of Doctrine, againſt all Romaniſts with other pretenders of antiquity, ſo in matters of Diſcipline, and this particular point of controverſie concerning the Parity, or rather Identity of Biſhops and Presbyters againſt all Hierarchiſts whatſoever, we are neither afraid nor aſhamed to appeale to this firſt Primitive Church, the Church in the Apoſtles dayes. Before I part with <hi>Gratian</hi> and the Canon Law, I ſhall adde this out of it, we finde there another Origi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall of this Imparity and diſtinction in Order between a Biſhop and a Presbyter,<note n="a" place="margin">Horum diſcretio à Gentilibus maximè intro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducta eſt, qui ſuos Flamines, alios ſimpliciter Flamines, alios Archiflamines, alios Proto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtamines appellabant. Grant decr. par. <hi>1.</hi> diſt. <hi>21.</hi> Vide plura diſtinct. <hi>80.</hi> Can. in Illis.</note> 
               <hi>The difference that now is between an Archbiſhop, a Biſhop, and a Preſbyter was introduced,</hi> ſaith <hi>Gratian, into the Church from the imitation of the Heatheniſh Hierarchie, who ſo marſhal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led their Prieſts that ſome were Archi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flamines, ſome Protoflamines, ſome Fla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mines.</hi> The ſame is acknowledged for the ſubſtance of it by the<note n="b" place="margin">
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>t Rom. veteres olim majores &amp; minores Pontifices, &amp; inter hos unum ſummum, qui omnes ſacris praecrant, habebant: it a &amp; nos in Chriſtianiſmo eaſdem denominationes ſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus: Archiepiſcopi dicti ſunt tanquam pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mores Epiſcopi, &amp;c. Deſacr. Ord. p. <hi>169.</hi> edit. Pariſ. an. <hi>1558.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Canons of Coleine</hi> in their <hi>Enchiridion of Chriſtian Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</hi> And were it needfull I could ſhew out of ſundry<note n="c" place="margin">Mat. Park. Antiq. Brit. p. <hi>5.</hi> Paggit in his Chriſtianogr. and Fitzberbert the Ieſ.</note> Divines that this forme of Church Government was here erected at firſt in <hi>England</hi> in imitation of the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theniſh Hierarchie by <hi>Lucius</hi> the firſt Chriſtian King that embraced the faith. Among thoſe many and pregnant teſtimonies which might be produced in confirmation of this truth, againſt the Divine Inſtitution of the Majority of Biſhops above Presbyters, I ſhall trouble your patience but with one remarkable paſſage in the
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:111196:22"/>Councell of Trent.<note n="d" place="margin">HIſtor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e of the Councell of Trent. <hi>lib</hi> 7. <hi>p.</hi> 619.</note> 
               <hi>When in the Congregation, Oct.</hi> 8. <hi>All the Spaniards with ſome others made a new inſtance that the Inſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and Superiority of Biſhops</hi> de Jure divino <hi>might be defined; unto the Legates chamber the next morning came three Patri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>arches, ſixe Archbiſhops, and eleven Biſhops, with a request that it might not be put into the Canon, that the Superiority is De Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re divino.</hi> And marke I beſeech you the reaſons, for in themſelves, but eſpecially proceeding from the mouthes of ſuch and ſo many perſons, they carry a great deale of weight with them; in regard that 1. <hi>It ſavoured of ambition.</hi> 2. <hi>It was unſeemly themſelves ſhould give ſentence in their own cauſe.</hi> 3. <hi>Becauſe the greater part would not have it put in.</hi> And whoſoever ſhall peruſe that hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtory, and diligently obſerve the managing of this buſineſſe in the Councell, ſhall finde that the opinion of the Spaniards, againſt which the fore-mentioned Patriarks, Archbiſhops, and Biſhops did produce their reaſons (which I doe not finde were ever anſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red or refuted) was inſerted into the Canon, meerly on theſe two grounds 1. In oppoſition to the Lutherans, this was the reaſon gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven by the Archbiſhops of<note n="e" place="margin">Ib. p. <hi>604.</hi>
               </note> Granata, in the Congregation held, <hi>Oct.</hi> 13.1562. and of<note n="d" place="margin">
                  <hi>P.</hi> 606.</note> Zara, as alſo by the<note n="f" place="margin">
                  <hi>Pa.</hi> 607.</note> Biſhop of Segovia in the following Congregations. 2. In favour of the Pope, for they were afraid that if the Divine inſtitution and ſuperiority of Biſhops were denyed, or the Prelates honour did decay, the Popes triple Crown would ſoon fall off his head. This made the Biſhop of Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>govia in plain termes confeſſe,<note n="g" place="margin">
                  <hi>Pa.</hi> 607.</note> 
               <hi>If the power of the Biſhops be weakned, that of the Pope is weakned alſo:</hi> and when the Secretary of the Marqueſſe of Peſcara dealt with the Archbiſhop of Granata for his ſtiffeneſſe in urging the divine Inſtitution of Biſhops, advi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing him not to touch any thing in prejudice to the holy See; Gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nata anſwered,<note n="h" place="margin">Ib pa <hi>629.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>He never meant to ſay any thing against the Pope, but thought that whatſoever was ſpoken for the authority of Biſhops, was for the benefit of his Holineſſe; being aſſured that if their authority were diminiſhed, the Obedience to the holy See would decreaſe alſo, though by reaſon of his old age he knew it would not happen in his time.</hi> Thus much of the firſt argument ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken from the teſtimonies of Scripture.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The writings of thoſe which immediately ſucceeded the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles, and lived in the next age after them, ſhew that in their dayes
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:111196:22"/>Biſhops and Presbyters were all one in name and office, not one preferred above the other in Order and Superiority of power. <hi>Polycarpe</hi> was as is confeſſed the Diſciple of S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
               <hi>John,</hi> the<note n="i" place="margin">Epiſ. part. <hi>2.</hi> p. <hi>156.</hi>
               </note> Angel of the Church of Smyrna, ſaith Biſhop <hi>Hall,</hi> following therein (as in moſt others) D<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>Downham.</hi> Now whether there were any ſuch Order of Biſhops ſuperior to Presbyters in the Church of Chriſt in his dayes, let the world judge from his own words in his Epiſtle to the Philippians. I will not ſpend lines, much leſſe leaves in the praiſe of the author, or his Epiſtle; I leave that to others who make good the Poets ſaying,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Laudat venales cupiens extrudere merces.</hi> Mercator. Nor will I inſiſt on the Inſcription of the Epiſtle, wherein he doth conjoyne with himſelfe the Presbyters of the Church of Smyrna, though from thence<note n="k" place="margin">Diſſert. de presb. &amp; epiſc. cap <hi>4.</hi> p. <hi>232.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Salmaſius</hi> doth prove that he was not a Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop in that reſtrained ſenſe wherein the word was uſed in after ages, for ſaith he, there is no example of an Epiſtle written by a Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop; wherein, when once a Biſhop came to be advanced above the Presbyters, he doth conjoyne them in his Inſcription as his Compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions and Equals: But take his plaine and poſitive command or counſell to the Philippians, how they muſt behave themſelves. Hee requires them to be<note n="l" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> 
               <hi>ſubject to the Preſbyters and Deacons as un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to God and to Christ.</hi> By which it is cleare there were then no other orders then theſe two, none above a Presbyter to which they muſt be in ſubjection. Here is not the leaſt mention of a Biſhop, as <note n="m" place="margin">Omiſſa neſcie quamebrem E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſcopis menti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>one. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſp. digreſſ. in <hi>4. Tim.</hi> lib. <hi>1.</hi> ca. <hi>1.</hi> p. <hi>133.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Eſpencaeus</hi> doth acknowledge, though being prepoſſeſſed with ſome fancies of his owne, <hi>de ordine Principante,</hi> as he cals the or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of Biſhops, for which he doth contend, he wondreth why they are omitted. Let us proceed, and ſee what power and authority theſe Presbyters had in the Church of Philippi, This we ſhall learne from his Injunction unto them; for he commands them to <hi>provide things honest in the ſight of God and men, abſtaining from all an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, reſpect of perſons and unjuſt judgement.</hi> He wils them farther to <hi>flee all covetouſneſſe, not ſuddenly giving credit to accuſations againſt any one, nor be harſh in judgement.</hi> Theſe paſſages I owe to<note n="n" place="margin">Loc. cit p. <hi>235.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Salmaſius,</hi> by which it is evident that theſe Presbyters of Philippi, to whom he gives this in charge, had then Eccleſiaſticall Juriſdi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctive power in their hands, and none was ſuperior unto them there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in in the Church of Philippi in thoſe dayes.</p>
            <pb n="38" facs="tcp:111196:23"/>
            <p>Before I proceed I muſt remove one rubbe that is caſt in the way by the<note n="o" place="margin">Archbiſhop of Armagh, <hi>Orig. of Epiſ.</hi>
               </note> Patrons of Epiſcopacie; it is this, <hi>Polycarpe</hi> was himſelfe a Biſhop of the Church of Smyrrna, as is proved amongſt other evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dences by the teſtimonie of <hi>Ignatius,</hi> who in his Epiſtle to the Church of Smyrna<note n="p" place="margin">Epiſt. ad Symrn.</note> ſalutes him under that name, as a perſon di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinct from the Presbytery, and exhorteth all the people to follow their Biſhop as Chriſt Jeſus did his Father, and the Presbytery as the Apoſtles, telling them that no man ought either to adminiſter the Sacraments, or doe any thing appertaining to the Church with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the conſent of the Biſhop: and of<note n="q" place="margin">Li. <hi>3.</hi> adv. baer. cap. <hi>3.</hi> &amp; in epiſt. ad Florin.</note> 
               <hi>Irenaeus,</hi> who ſo ſtiles him, and witneſſeth that he himſelfe was preſent when <hi>Polycarpe</hi> him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe did diſcourſe of his converſation with S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
               <hi>John.</hi> From all which it is inferred that he was the Angel or Preſident of the Church of Smyrna, when S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
               <hi>John</hi> wrote this his <hi>Revelation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Yet all this makes nothing againſt what I have delivered, as I conceive under favour, and with ſubmiſſion to men of greater rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding and better judgement: For 1. Sundry paſſages in that Epiſtle of <hi>Ignatius</hi> to <hi>Polycarpe</hi> are, as<note n="r" place="margin">Margin. annot. in epiſt. Ignat. ad Polyc.</note> 
               <hi>Vedelius</hi> hath obſerved, ſuppoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titious, thruſt into them by ſome one or other out of the pretended Conſtitutions of <hi>Clemens, lib.</hi> 2. <hi>cap.</hi> 26. 2. Albeit <hi>Ignatius</hi> doth in that Epiſtle ſalute <hi>Polycarpe</hi> the Biſhop, and the Presbyterie, yet it doth neceſſarily follow that he was a Biſhop in order diſtinguiſhed from the Presbytery, if he were a Presbyter Preſident of the Pres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bytery it is a ſufficient reaſon why in this falutation of <hi>Ignatius</hi> he ſhould be named in the firſt place, and the Presbyterie after him. It appeares by <hi>Ignatius</hi> elſwhere that the Presbyters were Counſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lors unto and Coaſſeſſors with the Biſhop in the Presbyterie, for ſo he doth expreſly call them:<note n="ſ" place="margin">In epiſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ad Troll. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> 
               <hi>What is the Preſbyterie,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>but a ſacred Aſſembly, the Counſellours and Coaſſeſſours of the Biſhop.</hi> In the Romane common-wealth though all the <hi>Patricii</hi> or Noble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men were Counſellours of State and Senatours, yet there were two choſen out from among the reſt, who had for honours ſake the denomination of Conſuls appropriated unto them, yet this title of honour did not advance them to a Place or Dignitie of a different Order from or Superiour to the reſt of the <hi>Patricii,</hi> they were all Counſellours, but theſe two the Preſidents of the Counſell; and from this their Orrice they had their name of honour <hi>Conſules à conſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lendo.</hi> How weak a ground, the reſtriction of the name Biſhop un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:111196:23"/>him that is a Preſident of the Presbyterie, to prove his diſtincti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in order from thence, hath been ſhewed before out of<note n="*" place="margin">Diſſert. de presb. &amp; epiſc. pag. <hi>232.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Salma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fius,</hi> who hath made it evident that by the ſame reaſon, a Counſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour and Senatour; The Councell and the Senate ſhould conſtitute different Orders, and Offices: yea, all that the Primate of Armagh (whom for his Pietie and Learning I ſhall ever honour) doth in plain termes plead for (at leaſtwiſe ſeemes unto me to plead for) and doth undertake to prove is only this, that he to whom the title of Biſhop (which was as is confeſſed by D<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>Reynolds,</hi> whom he alleadgeth at firſt common to all the Presbyters, by whoſe common counſell and advice all Church affaires were ordered) is reſtrained by the Fathers, was a Preſident of the Presbyterie, which may eaſily be granted without any great advantage to the Hierarchiſts, or prejudice to the Presbyterians. But if by reaſon of Preſidentſhip it ſhall be inferred that the Biſhop was in Order and in Office diſtinct from and ſuperior to the Presbyters; I ſhall for my part be ready to aſſent unto thoſe which ſay ſo, on the ſame conditions that that Old Archbiſhop of<note n="r" place="margin">Fa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>etur Armachanus diverſam ſententiam<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> eſſe magis amicum Doctoribus eccleſiae, cui pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ratum ſe profitetur morem gerere; node e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinis differentia oſtendatur oraculis. mich. de Pal. in <hi>4.</hi> diſt. <hi>24.</hi> diſp. <hi>2.</hi> Num epiſc. fit. ordo.</note> Armagh profered to ſubſcribe to the opinion of the Prelates and Doctors, (who were well-pleaſed with their aſſertions that did ſay there was by divine inſtitution a difference between a Biſhop and a Presbyter) <hi>So that the difference may be manifested out of the divine Oracles,</hi> and what is affirmed be proved by them.</p>
            <p n="3">3. True it is that <hi>Irenaeus</hi> doth indeed ſet forth <hi>Polycarpe</hi> un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der that name Biſhop of the Church of Smyrna, yea and withall doth ſay that he was conſtituted Biſhop of that Church by the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles; yet doth it not follow that he was a Biſhop in Order ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periour to a Presbyter, which I ſhall prove two wayes: 1. By the writings of the Apoſtles (which beſt of all informe us what orders of Church Officers they did inſtitute) a Biſhop and Presbyter are one in Order and Office. Of this I have ſpoken before, and therefore will but mention it: onely I will adde the judgement of that fore-mentioned old and learned Archbiſhop of Armagh in this point; who conſidering the paſſages of the Apoſtle in his Epiſtle to <hi>Timothie,</hi> wherein there is mention of no other Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:111196:24"/>but Biſhops and Deacons, delivereth it as a<note n="u" place="margin">Conſtant quod inter orcinem Epiſcopalem, &amp; inter ordinem Diaconatue non eſt orao medius, quo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>iam ſi quis eſſet, non dubium, quia iſte Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctor maximus qui ſuum evangelium recepit à Chriſto, ut ipſe ſcrihit ad <hi>Gal. 1.</hi> ſuum diſcctum diſcipulum Timotheum de illo ord<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ne inſtrux<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſſet, &amp; ei regulas dediſſet, ficut de ſuperiori &amp; inferiori re<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>utas dedit. Rich. Armach. lib. <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>1.</hi> quaeſt. Armen cap <hi>5.</hi> fol. <hi>84.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>manifest and unquestionable truth that there is no middle order be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween them, for if there were, out of all doubt that great Doctor, who received his Goſpel from Jeſus Chriſt, would have in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>structed Timothy therein, and preſcribed rules concerning that, as he did concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the order above and below it.</hi> 2. Out of <hi>Irenaeus</hi> himſelfe, who<note n="*" place="margin">Haec dogmata tibi, qui ante nos fuerunt priſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byteri qui &amp; Apoſtolorum diſcipuli <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>xtiterunt, non tradiderunt —Poſsum coram deo teſtificar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> beatum ilum &amp; Apoſt olicum Presbyterum, ſi tale quid audiſſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t reclamatum. Iraen. in epiſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ad Plorin. Cent. Magd. ent. <hi>2.</hi> cap. <hi>10.</hi> col. <hi>134, 135.</hi>
               </note> elſewhere cals both <hi>Polycarpe</hi> himſelf, and other biſhops of Aſia Diſciples of the Apoſtles <hi>Apoſtoli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call Preſbyters.</hi> Under the ſame notion doth he mention <hi>Anicetus, Pius Hyginus, Teleſphorus</hi> (who are by others called Biſhops of Rome) giving them no other title then this,<note n="a" place="margin">In Epiſt. ad victor.</note> 
               <hi>The Preſbyters that were before you:</hi> Whoſoever ſhall peruſe ſundry paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſages in<note n="x" place="margin">Iren. lib. <hi>3.</hi> adv. haer. cap. <hi>3. compared with</hi> ca. <hi>2.</hi> ejud lib. <hi>and</hi> li. <hi>4.</hi> cap. <hi>43. compared with</hi> cap <hi>44.</hi> &amp; <hi>45.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Irenaeus</hi> will clearly ſee that in him the <hi>Succeſſion of Biſhops is all one with the ſucceſſion of Preſbyters.</hi> I will mention but one and referre the Reader to the reſt in the margent (if he thinke fit to con<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ult the authour himſelfe)<note n="y" place="margin">Iren. lib. <hi>4.</hi> cap. <hi>43.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>We muſt obey,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>thoſe Preſbyters which are in the Church, thoſe which have a ſucceſſion from the Apoſtles, as we have ſhewed. Who toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with the ſucceſſion of the Biſhoprick or Epiſcopacie, have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived the gift of truth according to the good pleaſure of the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</hi> The places are ſo cleare, the words ſo plaine and evident that from thence <hi>Spalatenſis</hi> did rightly inferre,<note n="z" place="margin">De rep. Eccl. l. <hi>2.</hi> c. <hi>3.</hi> n. <hi>44.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>In all Preſbyters Ire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naeus doth both acknowledge and confound one and the ſame order of Epiſcopacie,</hi> though afterwards ſeeking to avoide the pregnant te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimonies, which overthrow his poſition, and the poſition of other Hierarchiſts, he gives this childiſh and ſlender anſwer, or rather ſil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly evaſion, that<note n="a" place="margin">Ibid. n. <hi>42.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>He cals thoſe which wore true Biſhops by the name of Preſbyters,</hi> which how weake it is, let any man of under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding judge. Wherefore untill I be convinced by clearer evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence (to which I ſhall be ready to yeeld, if any be produced) I ſhall ſay with <hi>Chamier,</hi>
               <note n="b" place="margin">Pauſtr. tom <hi>2.</hi> l. <hi>10.</hi> de Oc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. Pont. c. <hi>6.</hi> in fine.</note> 
               <hi>Auſim aſſerere, I dare be bold to main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:111196:24"/>it, that Preſbyters and Biſhops are no where diſtinguiſhed in Irenaeus.</hi> Thus much for anſwer to that objection. I proceed to another inſtance. How little ſtrength to Epiſcopall Soveraignty over Presbyters the Epiſtle of <hi>Clemens</hi> to the Corinthians doth afford (in the commendation of which Author and Epiſtle,<note n="c" place="margin">Biſhop <hi>Hall, pag.</hi> 129, 130, 133.</note> one that hath lately ſtept forth, as another <hi>Atlas,</hi> to beare up Epiſcopa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie by head and ſhoulders, is pleaſed to ſpend two whole pages at leaſt) you may eaſily perceive, if either you peruſe the Epiſtle it ſelf, or parallell that paſſage cited by the forementioned ſtickler for Prelacie with divers others in<note n="d" place="margin">Diſſert. de Presb. &amp; epiſ. p. <hi>202.</hi> ad p. <hi>219.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Salmaſius</hi> out of the ſame Epiſtle. For there you ſhall finde 1. that Biſhops and Presbyters are <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, both denominations ſetting forth one and the ſame order, one and the ſame office. 2. That the Church of Corinth at that time, and other Churches alſo, were governed not by one but by many Biſhops, that is to ſay, Presbyters. The paſſages are quo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by that learned Critick at large, I will in briefe but point unto them. Firſt, what the Apoſtles practiſe was <hi>Clemens</hi> there ſets downe thus: <hi>Preaching in cities among the Nations, they did con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitute the first fruits of them, to be Biſhops and Deacons, over them that ſhould afterward beleeve.</hi> Theſe Biſhops are afterward in many places called Presbyters, <hi>Bleſſed are thoſe Preſbyters that went before. It is a ſhamefull thing to heare that the ancient and firme Church of Corinth ſhould out of reſpect unto one or two per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>move ſedition against the Preſbyters.</hi> Afterwards he perſwades thoſe which had been the authors of the contention to repent and yeeld ſubjection to the Presbyters. From theſe and ſundry other paſſages <hi>planiſſimè conſtat,</hi> ſaith<note n="d" place="margin">Pag. <hi>219.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Salmaſius, it is moſt evident and cleare, that that Church was then governed by Preſbyters alone, who were alſo called Biſhops, all conſtituted in equall authoritie, honour and power in the government thereof.</hi> Amongſt many other that are remarkable, I will only touch upon one, which ſeeing the Author is ſo highly magnified, and the Epiſtle commended with a great deale of ſilken language beſtowed on it, might me thinks make ſome impreſſion on the Commender, and others of his Order, as it is very pathetically delivered by <hi>Clemens, Wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſoever he be amongſt you that is of a generous ſpirit, that is of a compaſſionate diſpoſition, whoſo is full of love let him ſay: If for my ſake there be ſedition, ſtrife, and ſchiſmes, I depart, I am con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:111196:25"/>to be gone whitherſoever you will, and will doe thoſe things which are commanded me by the people: Only let the flock of Chriſt live in peace with the Preſbyters that are ſet over it. Whoſoever ſhall doe this ſhall purchaſe to himſelfe exceeding great glory in the Lord, and every place will readily receive him.</hi> Thus that holy, that Apoſtolicall man <hi>Clemens,</hi> whoſe counſell if it might have found entertainment in the hearts of our Prelates and their adhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents, neither <hi>Scotland</hi> of late yeeres, nor <hi>England</hi> at this day had met with ſuch commotions and diſtractions. Or if examples, and the Preſidents of thoſe Fathers (in whom becauſe they were Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops, our late<note n="e" place="margin">Biſhop <hi>Hall, p.</hi> 62. It is our glory &amp; com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort we have had ſuch Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deceſſours.</note> Hierarchiſts do glory as being their Predeceſſours) are likely to be more effectuall with thoſe which would be accoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted their poſteritie, I could put them in minde of <hi>Gregorie Nazi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anzen,</hi> who was content to lay down his Epiſcopall honour, and to deſcend from that throne which he knew not well whether he might more properly call an hierarchicall or tyrannicall throne; nor did he feare to commit any ſacriledge againſt that holy order, or contract on himſelf the guilt of that crime, but<note n="d" place="margin">Orat. <hi>28</hi> &amp; Carm. de div. vitae gen. ad pſeudoepiſ.</note> finding the Church waſted by contentions, States and Kingdomes exceedingly ſhaken, and like to be overturned by warres about that ſame <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>that great and new name,</hi> as he cals the Epiſcopall dignitie, he willingly did it, induced thereunto by a moſt prevailing argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.<note n="e" place="margin">Quum certus fit à Deo non excludi quibus thronus eripia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur. Cent. Mag. Cent <hi>4.</hi> c. <hi>10</hi> col. <hi>525.</hi> edit. Baſ. <hi>2624.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>He was aſſured of this, God would not diſ-throne him in Heaven, though he loſt his throne on earth.</hi> If the example of one induced thereunto by the hope of heaven be not ſufficient, I could propoſe to our Prelates for a Preſident the practiſe of<note n="f" place="margin">Lib. de geſt. cum Emer. Don. epiſ. tom. <hi>7.</hi> col. <hi>6, 7, 638.</hi> edit. Baſan. <hi>1542.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Auſtin, and almoſt three hundred African Biſhops, whoſe hearts were ſo enfla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med with a deſire of union and peace in the Church, that they were ready for the procuring of it to lay downe their Biſhopricks, which in ſo doing they did not account to be loſt, but more ſafely recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended unto God.</hi> And whereas amongſt them all there were but two found to whom this motion was diſpleaſing, the brotherly exhortation and reproofe generally of all the reſt, did make them change their mindes and confent to doe, what the reſt of their bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren did. The exhortation is very ponderous, and full of moving arguments. Give leave, O ye Fathers of the Church, unto a poore Presbyter to repreſent before you, what once your Predeceſſours ſpake unto them, who were loath to part with their dignities for
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:111196:25"/>the Churches benefit. They propoſe in the firſt place that of our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour, <hi>Who ſo humbleth himſelfe ſhall be exalted;</hi> and from thence inferre, <hi>Why ſhould we doubt to offer to our Redeemer the ſacrifice of this humilitie? Hath he deſcended from Heaven into humane members that we might become his members, and are we afraid to deſcend from our ſeats that his very members be not torne in pieces by cruell diviſion? There is nothing more ſufficient for us then that we be faithfull and obedient Christians. This we are ſtill. But we are made Biſhops for the Chriſtian people, therefore let us doe that with our Epiſcopall honour, which may conduce to the Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an peace of Chriſtian people. If we be profitable ſervants why doe we envie the eternall gain of our maſter for our temporall prefer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment? Our Epiſcopall dignity will be more fruitfull unto us, if, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing laid down, it may rather collect, then being retained ſcatter the flock of Chriſt. Austin the Biſhop ſaid, My brethren, if we have the Lord in our thoughts, this higher place is the watch-tower of the vine-dreſſer, not the top of honour for him that is proud. If whileſt I retain my Biſhoprick I ſcatter the flock of Christ, how is the dammage of the flock the honour of the Shepheard? With what face ſhall we in the world to come hope for the honour promiſed by Chriſt, if our honour in this world doth hinder Christian unity?</hi> Thus farre the African Biſhops.—<hi>Sed Cynthius aurem.</hi> I returne unto, and proceede in the proving of our Propoſition laid downe before.</p>
            <p n="3">3. In Chriſtian Churches which were of Apoſtolicall founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and others after them, we finde two Biſhops in a Church or Citie, both in, and after the Apoſtles dayes; not one advanced before the other. Which being duly conſidered we may invert that argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment which is uſed by our Hierarchiſts for the maintainance of their Epiſcopall Monarchie. You know who hath laid down this amongſt his <hi>Poſtulata:</hi>
               <note n="g" place="margin">
                  <hi>Epiſc.</hi> by div. right. <hi>part.</hi> 1. §. 12. <hi>p.</hi> 50.</note> 
               <hi>We may not entertain ſo irreverent an opinion of the Saints and Fathers of the Primitive Church, that they who were the immediate ſucceſſours of the Apoſtles would, or durſt ſet up a forme of government different from that which was fore-deſigned unto them.</hi> Let this be granted, the poſition may ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſily be retorted on their own heads thus, If the Apoſtles had inſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted one Biſhop onely in a Church, and placed him in ſuperiority of power and order above the Presbyters, can we think that the Saints
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:111196:26"/>and Fathers of the primitive Churches, or the Churches themſelves, would have ſo ſoon ſwerved from the rule and practiſe of their firſt founders, and have ſet up or admitted two Biſhops where the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles had ordained but one. The truth of this aſſertion touching the plurality of Biſhops in a Church may be eaſily proved by varietie of examples.<note n="h" place="margin">Diſſert. de gub. Eccleſ. p. <hi>302, 303.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Gerſom Bucerus</hi> hath proved it by no leſſe then ten examples out of Scriptures, and others out of Eccleſiaſticall hiſtory. I will onely mention ſome few. <hi>Narciſſus</hi> and <hi>Alexander</hi> both Biſhops of Hieruſalem, not by ſucceſſion one after the other, but both at the ſame time, as is proved out of<note n="i" place="margin">Eccl. hiſt. li. <hi>6.</hi> ca. <hi>9.</hi> &amp; <hi>10.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Euſebius. Ignatius</hi> and <hi>Evodias</hi> both Biſhops of Antioch at the ſame time, the one ordai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned by <hi>Peter,</hi> the other by <hi>Paul,</hi> as the fore-mentioned<note n="*" place="margin">Gerſ. Buc. p. <hi>439.</hi>
               </note> forraine Divine hath proved by the confeſſion of <hi>Clemens, Conſtit. l.</hi> 7. <hi>c.</hi> 46. and <hi>Baronius, tom.</hi> 1. <hi>ad an.</hi> 45. At Rome <hi>Linus</hi> and <hi>Cletus,</hi> or <hi>Anacletus</hi> were <hi>Coepiſcopi</hi> Fellow-Biſhops in <hi>Peters</hi> dayes, and afterwards as <hi>Platina</hi>
               <note n="l" place="margin">In vita Sancti Petri.</note> hath acknowledged, and before him <hi>Ruffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus, in praefar. ad lib. Recognit.</hi> as<note n="m" place="margin">Pan. tom. <hi>2.</hi> l. <hi>13.</hi> c. <hi>4.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Chamier</hi> hath obſerved out of him, and the<note n="n" place="margin">Cent <hi>1</hi> part. <hi>2.</hi> c. <hi>10.</hi> in Lino.</note> Centuriſts of Magdenburge after them both. <hi>Libe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rius</hi> after his returne from exile was conjoyned with <hi>Felix</hi> in the Epiſcopall See at Rome, by the decree of the Synod of Syrmium, as I have learned from<note n="o" place="margin">Cat. teſt. ver. l. <hi>4.</hi> col. <hi>255.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Illyricus</hi> and <hi>Gonlartius</hi> out of<note n="p" place="margin">Lib. <hi>4.</hi> c. <hi>14.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Sozomen:</hi> which Synod was held no leſſe then fiftie ſix yeeres after the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell of Nice, which firſt made a Canonicall conſtitution to the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary, <hi>prohibiting that there ſhould be two Biſhops in one citie:</hi> as<note n="q" place="margin">Lib. <hi>1.</hi> c. <hi>6.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Ruffinus</hi> hath ſet down that Canon: yea, later then this <hi>Auſtin</hi> was made Biſhop of Hippo in the dayes of <hi>Valerius</hi> and joyned with him as his Colleague in the Epiſcopall honour and Function, albeit <hi>Auſtin</hi> was very unwilling, yet the<note n="x" place="margin">Dum id fieri ſolere ab omnibus ſuaderetur, at<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> id ignare tranſmatinis &amp; Africanis Eccleſiae exemplis probaretur, compulſus at<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>ctas ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cubuit, &amp; Epi ſcapatus curam &amp; majoris loci ordinationem ſuſcepit. Poſſlid. in vita Aug. c. <hi>8.</hi> Quod quidem quia tanta ejus obaritate, tan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> populi ſtudio dominum id velle credidt, nonnullis jam exemplis praecedentibus quibus mibi omnis excuſatioi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>laudehatur, veheme<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ter timuiexcuſare. Aug. ep. <hi>34.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d Pauſin.</note> 
               <hi>Primate of Numidia Megatius Cala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menſis, and Valerius together with all the reſt Biſhops that were preſent perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded him thereunto, and by varietie of ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples in the African and tranſmarine Churches proved it to be a thing ſo uſuall,</hi> that <hi>Austin</hi> was left without all excuſe, and yeelded to undertake <hi>coepiſcopatus ſarcinam,</hi> as he cals it, the <hi>burthen of Coepiſcopacie</hi> with <hi>Valerius:</hi> for the prohibition by the Nicene canon was not yet come to
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:111196:26"/>the knowledge of <hi>Valerius,</hi> nor to the cares of <hi>Austin,</hi> as he doth<note n="ſ" place="margin">Ep. <hi>110.</hi> Quod cone liio Nieeno prohibitum, ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſſe neſciebam nec ipſe ſciebat.</note> elſe where profeſſe. This is a truth ſo clear, and which hath ſuch varietie of inſtances for the confirmation of it, that the<note n="*" place="margin">Neq, fuit tanta valigie priſcu illis Epiſcopis l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>cum ſibi interdum aſcicere aliquem, ex ſua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum Eccleſiarum Presbyteris, qui &amp; ipſe tum furiſdictione &amp; ordine, u u<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> pleno Epiſcopalis propriae poreſtatis tum etiam nomine in eadem Eccleſia ſimul eſſet, &amp; diceretur Epiſcopus. de rep. Eccl l <hi>2.</hi> c <hi>9.</hi> n. <hi>14.</hi>
               </note> Arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biſhop of <hi>Spalato</hi> doth confeſſe, <hi>The anci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent holy Biſhops made no ſcruple of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king one of their Preſbyters their compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ni<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n, who both in Juriſdiction and Order, and full uſe of power properly Epiſcopall ſhould be their Colleague and Fellow-bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop in the ſame Church.</hi> Yea,<note n="t" place="margin">Idem eſt juris in parte quod in toto, &amp; in par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vis quod in magnis, ſed in eodem epiſcopatu poſſunt ſimut eſſe duo epiſcopi, Cauſ <hi>7.</hi> q. <hi>1.</hi> c. Non eſt autem. &amp; C Periſti &amp; C. Quia vero. Ergo conſimiliter propter neceſſitatem vel uti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litatem poſſent eſſe ſnnut plures ſummi Ponti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fices dial part. <hi>3.</hi> tract. <hi>1.</hi> lib. <hi>2.</hi> c. <hi>25.</hi> ſol. <hi>202.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Occham</hi> proving out of the Canon Law it ſelfe that there may be two Biſhops in a Biſhoprick or Dioceſſe, doth thence inferre that by the ſame reaſon there may be alſo two Popes,<note n="u" place="margin">Fideles propter neceſſitatem vel utilitatem ſufficienter moventem conſtituendo plures Pon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifices non facerent conditionem Eccleſiae dete<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rivem, ſed meliorarent cam. cap. <hi>26.</hi> ſol. <hi>203.</hi> ad ſeptimum</note> as the government of one and the ſame Church by more Biſhops then one conduceth to the benefit thereof, ſo the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giment of the Church Catholike by many Popes.<note n="a" place="margin">Loc. cit. cap. <hi>15.</hi> paulo ante finem.</note> This he maintaines might be done in both, without any rent or diviſion in the Church, without the breach of that unity which the Apoſtle doth require, for among all thoſe things which he reckons up as grounds of union, and motives to the conſervation of it,<note n="b" place="margin">Epheſ. 4.</note> One faith, one Baptiſme, &amp;c. <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>num Apoſtolicum minimè ponit,</hi> ſaith he, the Apoſtle makes no mention of one Apoſtolicall either Pope or Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late. In a word; the practiſe of governing a Church by more Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops then one was for a while ſo common and uſuall (though by degrees it did begin in ſome places ſooner to grow out of uſe then others) that if <hi>Epiphanius</hi> his obſervation be right, it was anciently proper to Alexandria alone to have one Biſhop, whereas other Churches and Cities had two. His words are cleare and expreſſe for it;<note n="x" place="margin">Haer. <hi>68.</hi> de Milet. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> 
               <hi>For Alexandria had not anciently two Biſhops as other ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties had.</hi> This teſtimonie of <hi>Epiphanius</hi> concerning Alexandria I firſt lighted upon in<note n="y" place="margin">in Aug. de haer. haer. Acrian.</note> 
               <hi>Danaeus,</hi> and ſince I met with it in him, I have oft times wondred, that in all the quotations out of the Fathers for Epiſcopacie, our Hierarchiſts take no notice of it. From the ſame <hi>Danaeus</hi> I have learned one thing more touching the forementioned
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:111196:27"/>Citie, where the Epiſcopall Monarchie firſt had footing, to wit, that out of the ſame<note n="z" place="margin">Ibid.</note> Church <hi>proceeded the Monaſtick life, and divers other things which were the bane of the Church.</hi> Perhaps in this regard our Prelates are aſhamed of this their originall, and would therefore fain bewitch the mindes of men with an opinion of ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther deſcent from Chriſts inſtitution and his Apoſtles. Dealing herein as wiſely for themſelves, as the old Romans did, who being aſhamed of the ſpurious and inceſtuous birth of their firſt Founder <hi>Romulus,</hi> pretended a Divine pedegree from <hi>Mars</hi> in a wood. But for my part I love them both ſo well, that I ſhall deſire, that as Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops and Monks did riſe ſo they may fall, as they did come ſo they may go together, and the Chriſtian world be rid at once of them both, which have proved <hi>Eccleſiae pestes</hi> the bane of the Church.</p>
            <p>Before I paſſe from this, one thing I muſt crave leave to adde, it concerneth the Succeſſion of Biſhops, which the Hiſtorians that did ſet it down, ſo mention, as if there were but one in a Church at once: yet this doth nothing contradict what hath beene ſpoken touching their plurality <hi>Simul</hi> at one and the ſame time in the ſame Church. For 1. Divers of thoſe Hiſtorians in their expreſſions and narrations had reference to the cuſtome of thoſe times in which themſelves li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved. For as much as in their dayes the cuſtome of governing by many was changed into a government by one, and the name com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon at firſt to all, limited and reſtrained unto one, hence they ſpeake but of one, though indeed (as hath been ſhewed) there were at the ſame time more Biſhops then one in a Citie. 2. When there were two or more equall in name and Office, he that was the Sur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viver is reckoned as the Succeſſor, whereas indeed he was not Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſor properly, but onely a Colleague living longer then his fellow-biſhop. Thus doth<note n="a" place="margin">Exercit. <hi>8.</hi> in Ignat. epiſt. ad Mariam, cap. <hi>3.</hi> num. <hi>6.</hi> conſtant Linum &amp; Cletum ante Cle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentem <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>bitſſe, quibus defunctis ſolus. Clemens ſuperſtes, ſolus etiam Epiſcopt nomen retinuit, tum quia inter adjutores Apoſtolorum ſolus reſtabat, &amp;c.</note> 
               <hi>Vedelius</hi> reconcile the difference which is between hiſtorians concerning thoſe three Biſhops of Rome, <hi>Linus, Cletus,</hi> and <hi>Clemens,</hi> ſhewing that the name of Biſhop was given to the laſt of theſe who was the ſurviver in that Church, where through the whole Chapter he diſcovereth the vani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of thoſe anſwers which are given by <hi>Bellarmine, Baronius;</hi> and others. Leſt our Hierarchicall Monarchie ſhould thinke to elude this and blow it away as the fancie of a Diſciplinarian of the Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neva
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:111196:27"/>cut, I will back it with the ſuffrage of <hi>Antonius de Dominis</hi> the Archbiſhop of <hi>Spalato,</hi> whom for his pains in patronizing the Epiſcopall cauſe they cannot but reſpect.<note n="b" place="margin">De rep. Eccl. l. <hi>2.</hi> c. <hi>3.</hi> n. <hi>63.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Quoniam ex his tribus Collegis,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>Becauſe of theſe three that were Colleagues</hi> Linus <hi>died first,</hi> Cletus <hi>next, and laſt of all</hi> Clemens, <hi>and each of them governed that Church with full authority, hence it came to paſſe that ſome of the ancients reckoned</hi> Linus <hi>the firſt Biſhop of Rome,</hi> Cletus <hi>or</hi> Anacletus <hi>the ſecond, and</hi> Clemens <hi>the third, as if they had been differenced in time one from the other, and one ſucceeded the other, when as indeed there was no proper ſucceſſion at all.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4. As moſt Churches had more then one Biſhop, ſo ſome for di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers yeeres together long after the Apoſtles dayes had none at all, but were inſtructed in the faith by Presbyters alone without a Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop over them. The<note n="c" place="margin">Forbeſ. lren. lib. <hi>2.</hi> cap. <hi>11.</hi> p. <hi>159.</hi>
               </note> Scortiſh pacificator in his <hi>Irenicum</hi> hath ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved out of<note n="d" place="margin">Ibo. Mail. li. z. de geſt. Scto c. <hi>2.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Johannes Maoior</hi> that <hi>the Primitive Church of Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land flouriſhed in the faith two hundred and thirty yeares at least without any goverment by Biſhops,</hi> being inſtructed in the faith and governed only by Prieſts and Monks. The ſame is recorded be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore them both concerning that Church by<note n="e" place="margin">Scoticbron. l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. <hi>3.</hi> ca. <hi>8.</hi> ap. lacob. Armach. de pri. Eccl. Brit. p. <hi>800,</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Johannes Fordonus,</hi> who addes that <hi>the Preſbyters did governe the Church, ritum ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quentes Eccleſiae primitivae, following the cuſtome of the primitive Church.</hi> Adde unto this one thing more which is remarkable; The Fathers in the ſecond Councel of Carthage, which was held, <hi>an.</hi> 428. did obſerve that<note n="f" place="margin">Concil. Cart<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. <hi>2.</hi> can. <hi>5.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>untill that time ſome places never had any Biſhops at all, and thereupon they did ordain,</hi> ut tales in poſterum non habe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent, <hi>that ſuch places as had none before, ſhould not have any for future time.</hi> From which Canonicall Conſtitution I may with<note n="g" place="margin">Diſſ. de gub. Eccleſ. p. <hi>307.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Gerſom Bucerus</hi> argue thus, If thoſe Fathers had conceived that the government by Biſhops was appointed by the Lord Chriſt, or his Apoſtles, they could not, they would not by an Eccleſiaſticall Canon have eſtabliſhed, or permitted to the Churches the violation of Chriſts. Inſtitution, or the Ordinance of his Apoſtles.</p>
            <p n="5">5. When after the Apoſtles dayes the diſtinction between a Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop and a Presbyter began, yet that difference which was then put was no advancement to a diſtinct order, but onely to an higher de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree in the ſame order, nor did it bring along with it any ſuperiority in power or Juriſdiction over and above the Presbyters. The truth of this poſition may be eaſily made manifeſt, and confirmed by theſe particulars.</p>
            <pb n="48" facs="tcp:111196:28"/>
            <p n="1">1. The name of Biſhop (which together with the office was common to all the Presbyters) was now limitted and appropriated unto him that was the eldeſt Presbyter. The name being thus reſtrai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, there was a prioritie granted him, to whom in reſpect of age and yeeres, in reſpect of his longer ſtanding in the Presbyteriall cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, and conſequently in regard of wiſedome, gravitie, experience, or Endowments, reverence was due from his Colleagues, being his Juniors, and in that regard after a ſort Inferiors. That of <hi>Ambroſe,</hi>
               <note n="h" place="margin">
                  <hi>in</hi> 1 Tim. <hi>c.</hi> 3.</note> 
               <hi>Is Epiſcopus eſt qui inter Preſbyteros primus, He is the Biſhop who is the first among the Preſbyters</hi> is a cleare teſtimonie, confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming what hath been delivered. For it doth declare manifeſtly, as<note n="i" place="margin">Pauſt. tom. <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</hi> l. <hi>9.</hi> de Oec. Pont. c. <hi>5.</hi> n. <hi>8.</hi> nihil a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bud quam inter Presbyteros is qui plures ann<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s in eo muncie Presbyteratus miniſtriaſſet.</note> 
               <hi>Chamier</hi> hath well obſerved, <hi>what was the degree of a Biſhop in the first and purest times of the Church; that it was no more then this, He was accounted the Biſhop, who among the Preſbyters had miniſtred longeſt in the office of a Preſbyter.</hi> Hence the forenamed French Divine doth conclude,<note n="k" place="margin">Ibid.</note> 
               <hi>that at firſt there was no other dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference between a Biſhop and the Preſbyters, then what is between the Deane and Canons in a Cathedrall.</hi> In reference to this,<note n="l" place="margin">Sum. contr. tract. <hi>2.</hi> q. <hi>22.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vetus</hi> doth conceive that <hi>Tertullian</hi> ſpeakes, when he ſaith <hi>Praeſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent probati qui<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan>, Seniores; Approved Elders doe ſit as Preſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dents, who have obtained that honour not by price but by teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie:</hi> In teſtimonie of that reverence and reſpect which age and Senioritie in the Miniſtery did beſpeake at the hands of his fellow. Presbyters, was the <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> the chiefe ſeat in the Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call Senate aſſigned unto him, to whom the name of Biſhop began now to be reſtrained on the fore-mentioned grounds. Like as in the more publike conventions of Biſhops and Presbyters aſſembled in a Councell, the chiefeſt ſeat was deputed for him that was the anci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>enteſt and moſt venerable. On this ground as <hi>Euſebius</hi> reports, ſaith <hi>Rivetus,</hi>
               <note n="m" place="margin">Hiſt. l. <hi>5.</hi> c <hi>22.</hi>
               </note> when the Biſhops of Pontus met together, <hi>Palmos</hi> was made Preſident, becauſe he was <hi>antiquiſſimus &amp; maximè ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerabilis;</hi> the Eldeſt and moſt reverend amongſt them. Hence<note n="n" place="margin">Hom. <hi>3.</hi> in Act. Apoſt,</note> 
               <hi>Chryſoſtome</hi> doth compare the Preeminence of the Biſhops over the Presbyters to the Preeminence of the Eldeſt brother or firſt-born over his younger brethren, who hath indeed a certain preemi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nence over them, but it is <hi>a brotherly preeminence, not a Lordly or Juriſdictionall prelation,</hi> as<note n="o" place="margin">Fraternam quidem non de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpoticam ne<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> juriſd<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ctiona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem Spal de rep. eccl. l. <hi>1.</hi> ca. <hi>5.</hi> n. <hi>13.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Spalatenſis</hi> doth expreſſe it, the reſt of his brethren being by ordinary right his equals in all things, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepting
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:111196:28"/>age, and that honour which is due to him in reſpect of it, the precedencie of primogeniture, which doth not inveſt him with any commanding power over them, or put them in ſubjection unto him. The name of Biſhop being thus limitted to him that was the Elder Presbyter occaſioned the mention of one alone in the wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings of thoſe who ſet downe the ſucceſſion of Biſhops. Learned <hi>Salmaſius</hi> hath illuſtrated this by two examples.<note n="p" place="margin">Diſſert. <hi>1.</hi> de presb. &amp; epiſc. ca. <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</hi> p. <hi>274.</hi>
               </note> When Athens was governed by nine <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> or Riders, the firſt of them onely gave the name to the yeere, whence he was ſtiled <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. The Romane Emperours did oft-times make many Conſuls in a yeer, which were called <hi>Conſules per ſuffectionem,</hi> yet theſe though they had full Conſular authority were not regiſtred among the Conſuls, but onely thoſe which were created int he beginning of the yeere, becauſe they were the Eldeſt, the firſt Conſuls.</p>
            <p n="2">2. That Primacy which was granted unto him which was the firſt and eldeſt Presbyter, and was now peculiarly called the Biſhop, was only at firſt a Primacy of order, no Superiority of power, or Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſdictive dominion, that Church affaires ſhould be ordered by him alone without the conſent and counſell of the Presbyters. Obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vable to this purpoſe is that expreſſion of <hi>Pius</hi> biſhop of Rome in his ſecond Epiſtle to <hi>Juſtus</hi> biſhop of Vienna,<note n="q" place="margin">Presbyteri &amp; Diaconi non ut majorem, ſed ut Chriſti mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrum te obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent. ap. Sal. p. <hi>275.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Let the Preſbyters and Deacons obſerve you not as one greater then they, but at the Miniſter of Chriſt:</hi> in which, you ſee, he doth in plain termes deny that <hi>Justus</hi> the biſhop was greater in point of power and authority then the Presbyters and Deacons. You know, Reverend and Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loved, what was the reſolution of<note n="r" place="margin">Ad id quod ſcripſerunt mibi compresbyteri noſtri Donatus &amp; Fortunatus, Novatus &amp; Gurdius, ſolus reſcribere nibil po<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ui, quande à primordio Epiſcopatus mei ſta<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>uerim nihil ſine conſilio veſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o, &amp; fine conſenſu plebis meae, privata ſententiagerere. Ep. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. exedit. Gon<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lart. aliis. lib. <hi>3.</hi> ep. <hi>10.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Cypri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an</hi> Biſhop of Carthage, <hi>from the firſt en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trance to his Epiſcopacy he determined to doe nothing in the managing of Church affaines of his own head without the coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell of the Preſbyters, without the conſent of the people,</hi> which he laies down as a rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, why he alone could not return an anſwer to that wherein <hi>Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natus</hi> and the reſt of the Compresbyters did conſult him. Nor did <hi>Cyprian</hi> entertaine this reſolution, and obſerve it in his practice meerly out of a voluntary humility and condeſcenſion, as<note n="ſ" place="margin">De Pent. Ro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. li. <hi>1.</hi> c. <hi>6.</hi> in reſp. ad tertium arg.</note> 
               <hi>Bellar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine</hi> would beare the world in hand, and by this ſhift elude this pregnant teſtimonie; but he acknowledged himſelf by his place and
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:111196:29"/>Office to be bound thereunto, even by that relation wherein he ſtood to the Presbyters, and the Presbyters to him,<note n="ſ" place="margin">Sed cum ad vot per Dei gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiam venero, tunc de iis quae velgeſta ſant, vet gerenda ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cut mutune bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor poſcit, in commune tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctabimus, id. ib.</note> 
               <hi>by vertue of that honour which they mutually owed one to the other.</hi> As the Preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byters and people did owe this honour to the Biſhop that without his advice and conſent they ought not to doe any thing; ſo the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop owed the ſame honour unto them not to doe any thing of his own head without their counſell and conſent. What <hi>Cyprian</hi> pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſeth concerning himſelf, the late learned<note n="t" place="margin">Daven. det. queſt. q. <hi>41.</hi>
               </note> Biſhop of Salisbury confeſſeth was in all likelihood obſerved by the reſt of the godly Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops in thoſe dayes. How exorbitant from this rule the practices of our Prelates have been, the Chriſtian world doth know full well; and he that ſhould goe about to reduce them unto it, might deſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vedly be accounted <hi>Augiae ſtabuli repurgator,</hi> as<note n="u" place="margin">Annot. in cypr. loc. cit.</note> 
               <hi>Gonlartius</hi> ſpeakes, the purger of <hi>Augias</hi> ſtable ſo full of dung and filth, that it would be an <hi>Herculean</hi> labour for to cleanſe it. True it is that when the title of Biſhop was reſtrained unto one of the Presbyters, there did within a little after begin to be a kinde of reſervation and reſtriction of ſome of thoſe acts and Offices which were before common to all the Presbyters. This was done for orders ſake, <hi>pro bono pacis,</hi> for the preſervation of the Churches peace, and for the honour of the Biſhop, who being choſen by the conſent of the Presbyters and people, had now a Preſidentſhip over them, and ſo after a ſort a Majoritie of adminiſtration<note n="a" place="margin">Majoritas adminiſtrationis, quae quidem admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtratio à juriſdictione pender, ex conſenſu ſul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jectionalt partim conſtu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>tur. ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ut dicunus <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lectum in cligences (ex eo quod habet admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrationem ordinariam) habere juriſdictionem Conc. Carth. l. <hi>2.</hi> c. <hi>13.</hi> p. <hi>7.7.</hi> ed. Baſ cum priv. Caſ Majeſt. ex off. Henrici-Petrina.</note> 
               <hi>ex conſenſu ſubjectionali</hi> as Cardinall <hi>Cuſanus</hi> hath it, from the free and volun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tary act of thoſe who conſented to the prelation of the Biſhop, and ſubjecting themſelves unto him.</p>
            <p>Ordination is one of thoſe acts, the pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er whereof the Biſhops doe challenge as one of thoſe Prerogatives which belong to their Order, yet if you look into the<note n="b" place="margin">Quamvis. Chorcpiſcopis &amp; presbyteris mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterterum communis ſit diſpenſatio quaedam ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men eccleſiaſticit regulis ſibt prohibita noverint: ſicut eſt presbyterorum &amp; diacomnorum. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ut virginum conſecratio, ſicut conſſ i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>utio altaris, ac benedictio velur<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ctio Syn. Hiſpal. <hi>2.</hi> ſub Stſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kulo can. <hi>7.</hi> ap. Cent Maga cent. <hi>7.</hi> c. <hi>9.</hi> col. <hi>142.</hi>
               </note> Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nons of the ſecond Councell of <hi>Hiſpalis,</hi> which was held at leaſt 600. yeares after Chriſt, you ſhall finde this reckoned up a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong other particulars, which <hi>the Preſby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters are there commanded to know are prohibited them by Imperi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all and Ecoleſiaſticall conſtitutions.</hi> And mark I pray you the reaſon
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:111196:29"/>why they might not meddle with this and other acts,<note n="x" place="margin">Quoniam quamquam conſecrationem habeant, Pontificatue tamen apicem non habent; quem ſatis deberi epiſcopis <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>thoritate, canonum prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipitur, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> per hoc. &amp; diſc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>io graduum, &amp; dignitatis ſaſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>gium ſummi pontificit dem<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>etur. Ibid.</note> 
               <hi>the name and title of Biſhop is by the Canons of the Church limited unto one, and by the ſame power are theſe Offices limited alſo, that ſo the difference of degrees</hi> (which the Church had put be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene a Biſhop and a Presbyter) <hi>and the honour of the Biſhop might be manifeſted.</hi> So the Fathers in that Councell. The ſame is acknowledged in the<note n="y" place="margin">Solum propter authoritatem ſumme ſacerdeti Clericorum ordinatio &amp; conſecratio reſervata eſt, ne a multis diſcipline eccleſiae vindicata co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordiam ſoiveret, ſcandala generaret. Concit. Aquiſgran. ap. Eocbel. decret. Eccl. Gald. <hi>5.</hi> tit. <hi>8.</hi> ca. <hi>88.</hi> pag <hi>784.</hi>
               </note> Councell of A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſgran, <hi>an.</hi> 816. in the dayes of <hi>Ludovi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus</hi> the firſt. <hi>Ordination is reſerved to the Biſhops only for authority, or as an enſigne of his honour, and for the prevention of ſcandals and diviſions in the Church,</hi> but as for a difference out of the word of God between a Biſhop and a Presbyter, they prove at large from the Apoſtles words to <hi>Titus, Timothy,</hi> and <hi>Act.</hi> 20. that there is none, but Biſhops and Presby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters are one and the ſame; yet did not this reſervation by an Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiaſticall canon put the power of Ordination into the hands of the Biſhop alone, ſo as that he might doe it without the concurrence of his Presbyters. But as the Presbyters were by the Canon of the Church prohibited to ordaine, ſo was the Biſhop by the ſame Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nonicall conſtitutions prohibited to doe it without their conſent.<note n="z" place="margin">Epiſcopus ſine concilio clerico<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum ſuorum cle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ricos non ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>net. Conc. Carth. <hi>4.</hi> can. <hi>22.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Let not a Biſhop ordaine Clergie-men without the counſell of his Clergie,</hi> ſaith the <hi>Canon of the Councell of Carthage,</hi> regiſtred by<note n="a" place="margin">Diſt. <hi>24.</hi> ca. <hi>6.</hi> Epiſcopus.</note> 
               <hi>Gratian in the Canon Law:</hi> which who ſo will be pleaſed to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſult ſhall find that his Gloſſator<note n="b" place="margin">Gloſſa in lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cum. Vide etian<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> diſt. <hi>67.</hi> cap. <hi>1.</hi> &amp; Gloſ in ver. Sacerdotes.</note> 
               <hi>Semeca</hi> doth anſwer an objection made to the contrary, and proves that the word <hi>ſolus,</hi> where it is ſaid the Biſhop alone may give honour, and alone may take it away, doth exclude other Biſhops, but not his own Clergie. So that a Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop with his own Clergie might ordaine, without the conſent of other Biſhops, but not doe it alone by his owne peereleſſe power, without the reſt of his Clergie conſenting to, and concurring with him in the action. In this regard it was decreed in the eleventh Councell of Toledo in Spain,<note n="c" place="margin">Diſt. <hi>23.</hi> cap. Presbyter.</note> 
               <hi>When a Biſhop doth lay his hands on the head of him who was to be ordained, let all the Preſbyters who are preſent lay on their hands alſo by the hand of the Biſhop.</hi> Presbyters have you ſee a ſhare with the Biſhop in the impoſition of
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:111196:30"/>hands at Ordination, which they doe,<note place="margin">Iren. Forb. lib. <hi>2.</hi> cap. <hi>11.</hi> pag. <hi>163.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>not only as conſenting to the ordination,</hi> ſaith <hi>Forbeſius,</hi> (for the conſent of the people was alſo required, yet never were they ſharers in this Act of Impoſition of hands, and Ordination whereby an Eccleſiaſticall power is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferred, as both he and<note n="e" place="margin">De rep. Eccl. lib. <hi>2.</hi> c. <hi>2.</hi> n. <hi>51.</hi> p. <hi>187.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Spalatenſis</hi> have obſerved, but by ſuffrage did they manifeſt their approbation of the perſon elected, or their election of him that was to be ordained)<note n="f" place="margin">Tanquam or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinantes, ſeu ordinem conferentes, &amp; ex poreſtate ordinan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>di diviritus accepta, gratiam ordinate, boc ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hibito ritu, apprecantes. Forb. ubi ſupra.</note> 
               <hi>but as thoſe which were Co-ordainers with the Biſhop, and by the power, of Ordination received from the Lord, praying for grace to be conferred on the perſon ordained by them and the Biſhop.</hi> This Canonicall reſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of Ordination to the Biſhop did no more invalidate the power of Presbyters to ordaine by vertue of their Presbyteriall order, then if a Canon ſhould have been made to inhibite a Presbyter to baptize, to preach, to adminiſter the Sacrament of the Lords Supper in the preſence, or without the conſent of the Biſhop, it would be of force thence to conclude that a Presbyter as a Presbyter, by vertue of his order might not performe theſe Presbyteriall acts and offices. It is not unknowne that long agone even in the dayes of<note n="g" place="margin">Dandi quidem [Baptiſm] habet jus ſummus Sacerdos qiueſt Epiſcopus, debinc Presbyteri &amp; Diaconi, non tamen ſine Epiſcopi authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate, propter Eccleſiae honorem Quo ſalvo, ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>va pax eſt. Tertull de <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ap. c. <hi>17.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Tertullian</hi> there began to be a reſervation of Baptiſme to the Biſhop, that Presbyters and Deacons might not doe it without the leave of the Biſhop, all which was done (on the ſame ground that Ordination was, as hath been ſhewed before) <hi>for the honour of the Biſhop, to whom the Church had conferred honour, and for the Churches peace:</hi> yet none did ever inferre from thence that this did properly belong to the Biſhop, and that a Presbyter might not doe it, except he had a Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops licence. But if the<note n="h" place="margin">Veteres à Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſmo a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>i ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nationem argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentatos ſuiſſe patet ex Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtro. l. <hi>4.</hi> diſt. <hi>25.</hi> Sadcel. reſp. ad <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>urr Sopb. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>40.</hi>
               </note> Maſter of the Sentences may be beleeved, albeit Ordination was limited to the Biſhop, yet did the ancients ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gue from the power of adminiſtring Baptiſme to the power of Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dination; Presbyters might baptize, therefore they might ordaine. Thus did they reaſon for the power, even then when the execution of the power was by canonicall-conſtitution reſtrained and ſhut up, <hi>ſub certis terminis poſitivis propter meliùs,</hi> as<note n="i" place="margin">Conc. Cath. l. 2. c. 13.</note> 
               <hi>Cuſanus</hi> ſpeaks in the like caſe, <hi>within certain poſitive limits and bounds, and that for the good and benefit of the Church,</hi> as it ſeemed unto them which firſt made, and afterwards continued thoſe limitations &amp; re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrictions. Thus much for Ordination.</p>
            <pb n="53" facs="tcp:111196:30"/>
            <p>Juriſdiction is the next thing wherein the Biſhops doe claime a peereleſſe power; this reſpecteth either Presbyters ſubjected to cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure and power of Juriſdiction in caſe of delinquency, or the people, in the ſentence of Excommunication. The field is very large, I will not expatiate, but only tender ſome few gleanings which I had ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered in the courſe of my ſtudies in this argument; I will not inſiſt on that<note n="k" place="margin">Epiſcopus nul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lius cauſam au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diat abſ<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentia clerico<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum, alioquin irrita erit ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentia epiſcopi, nifi clericorum praeſentia con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmetur. Conc. Carth. <hi>4.</hi> can. <hi>23.</hi>
               </note> Canon of the Councell of Carthage which <hi>prohibiteth the Biſhop to meddle with the hearing of any cauſe but in the preſence of his Clergie, and pronounceth the ſentence of the Biſhop voide if it were not by them confirmed.</hi> Concerning which Canon D<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>Down<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham</hi> himſelf thus ſpeakes.<note n="l" place="margin">Defence of his Sermon, <hi>ti.</hi> 1. <hi>p.</hi> 179.</note> 
               <hi>Seeing good lawes ariſe from bad man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners: It is to be imagined that the Preſence of the Clergie, and Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtance of the Preſbyters</hi> (who were the Biſhops Coaſſeſſors, and from the beginning were appointed Judges of cauſes as himſelf doth<note n="m" place="margin">Ibid. p. <hi>177.</hi>
               </note> acknowledge) <hi>was neglected; and this neglect gave occaſion to the making of this Canon.</hi> What is by the Fathers in this Synod decreed concerning the Cognizance of cauſes in generall, is afterward (for that Councell was held about the year 401.) by<note n="n" place="margin">Si quid de quo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cun<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> clerico ad aures tuas per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venerit, quod is juſtè poſsit effendere, non faci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lè credas; nec ad vindictam te ret accendat in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cognita, ſed praeſentitus ſenioribus eccleſiae tuae diligenter eſt veritas perſcrutanda, &amp; tunc ſi qualttas rei popoſcerit, canonica diſtrictio cul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pam ſcriat delinquentis. Greg. regiſt. epiſt li. <hi>11.</hi> indict. <hi>6.</hi> epiſt. <hi>49.</hi> prout citatur apud Grat. ſed in edit. eper Greg. an. <hi>1615.</hi> eſt epiſt. <hi>51.</hi> ad I<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>han. Epiſc. Panermit.</note> 
               <hi>Gregory</hi> the Great mentioned and commanded in particular to be obſerved in the cauſe of a Presbyter, againſt whom accuſations are brought, or fame is raiſed; for he commands the Biſhop to whom he writes <hi>that in ſuch caſes he ſhould in the preſence of the Seniors of the Church make diligent inquirie into the matter, and then proceed to a Canonicall cenſure as the qualitie of the crime ſhould require:</hi> Yea<note n="o" place="margin">In epiſt. ad Cler. Eccleſ. Tornac. apud Cat. teſt. verit. l. <hi>9.</hi> col. <hi>1000.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Hincma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rus</hi> the Archbiſhop of Rhemes preſcribeth the ſame courſe to be followed, citing the very words of <hi>Gregorie</hi> for it. I will onely touch on ſome Canonicall Conſtitutions which have regulated the power of the Biſhops in point of Juriſdiction over the Presbyters. Who ſo will take the pains to conſult<note n="p" place="margin">Cauſ. <hi>15.</hi> q. <hi>7.</hi> Cap. <hi>1.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Gratian,</hi> the Compiler of the Canon Law ſhall finde ſundry Canons of more then one Councell of Carthage (to wit, <hi>Carthag.</hi> 1. <hi>can.</hi> 11. &amp; <hi>Concil. Carthag.</hi> 2. <hi>c.</hi> 10. &amp; <hi>Concil. Carthag.</hi> 3. <hi>can.</hi> 8.) ordaining that in caſe any crime were objected againſt a Presbyter, the cauſe ſhould be heard by ſixe Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops, the cauſe of a Deaon accuſed, ſhould be heard by three, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides his own Biſhop. This order in one of thoſe Councels is thus ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tified,<note n="q" place="margin">Carth. <hi>2.</hi> can. <hi>10.</hi>
               </note>
               <pb n="52" facs="tcp:111196:31"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="53" facs="tcp:111196:31"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="54" facs="tcp:111196:32"/>
               <hi>Ab univerſis epiſcopis dictum est; veterum ſtatut<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> â nobis debere ſervari. It was ſaid by all the Biſhops, that we ought to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve the ſtatutes of the ancient Fathers.</hi> Whereunto may be added this, that when in the Councell of <hi>Hiſpalis</hi> complaints were made that this rule was broken, it was by the Fathers in that Synod orde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red that<note n="r" place="margin">Statutum eſt juxta priſcorum Pa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rum decre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum. ſynodati ſententia, quod nollus fine concilii exam ne dejiciendum quemtibet presbyterum, vel Diaconum au leat. Na<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> multi ſuni qui indiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſſos poteſtate tyrannica, non au<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>boritate ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nonica damaant. Syn. Hisp. <hi>a.</hi> act. <hi>6.</hi> Cent. Magd. cent. <hi>7.</hi> cap. <hi>2.</hi> col. <hi>142.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>no Biſhop ſhould preſume to put down a Preſbyter or Deacon without ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amination before a Councell.</hi> The contrary practice of ſome was adjudged to be <hi>the exerciſe of a tyrannicall power, not of Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nonicall authority.</hi> I will not tire your pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience with repetition of the ſame decree revived and confirmed in another<note n="ſ" place="margin">Concil. Tribu. an. <hi>895.</hi> ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. ap. Cent. Magd. cen. <hi>9.</hi> c. <hi>9.</hi> co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. <hi>262.</hi>
               </note> Councell almoſt 900. yeares after Chriſt. Only this I will adde; that, This ancient order of the Councell and conſent of ſix Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops in the caſe of a Presbyters depoſition from his place, was not neglected by any regular allowance, untill the Apoſtaſie of Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſt ſo far prevailed, that the Goſpel in the ſincere and Orthodoxe Profeſſion thereof was perſecuted under the name of hereſie. In this caſe <hi>Gregory</hi> the ninth (whoſe Decretals were publiſhed, <hi>an.</hi> 1230.) gave a<note n="*" place="margin">Quaniam E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſcoporum un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merus ad degra dationem Clericorum a Canonibus conſtitutus, non p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>eſt de ſocili convenire: Concedtmus ut ſacerdotem, vel alium clericum in ſacris ordini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus conſtitutum (cum pro hereſi ſuerit curiae ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aulari relinquendus aut perpetuò immurand<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>) <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>onvocatis Abbatibus, altiſ<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> praelatis ac Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gioſis perſonis, ac literatis ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> Dioceſis, de qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus expedire videbatur, ſuus ſolus poſſit Epiſ <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>opiu degradase. Sext. decret lib <hi>5.</hi> tit. <hi>2.</hi> ca. <hi>1.</hi>
               </note> diſpenſation, that <hi>the Dioceſan Biſhop alone in the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of his Abbots with ſome Prieſts and other religious or learned perſons of the Dioceſſe might proceede to the ſentence.</hi> In all caſes hereſie excepted, the foremen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned Ordinances of a Synodall audience for the Depoſition of a Presbyter ſtood in force in ſucceeding ages, as that learned Canoniſt<note n="t" place="margin">Inſtit. Iur. Can. lib. <hi>1.</hi> tit. <hi>20.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Paulus Lancelotus</hi> hath obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved. By this which hath been ſpoken let the indifferent and impartiall Reader judge of the practices of our Prelates, how ſtrangely exorbitant, that I ſay not tyrannicall in a ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry high degree they have been, in their proceedings, and execution of that Juriſdiction which they have uſurped.</p>
            <p>Excommunication is another branch of Juriſdiction, which is claimed alſo by the Biſhops as properly belonging unto them.<note n="u" place="margin">
                  <hi>Davenant,</hi> abi. ſupra. Mucro e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſcopalis, &amp; fulmen epiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>opale.</note> They tell us this Eccleſiaſticall cenſure was alwaies accounted <hi>the Biſhops ſword, and the Biſhops thunderbolt:</hi> and indeed ſince they have ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken the power thereof into their hands, and as they have managed
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:111196:32"/>it, it hath been an Epiſcopall thunderbolt, that is to ſay, <hi>brutum ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men,</hi> a thunderbolt which doth neither fright nor hurt any; the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuntiation of this ſentence, being much corrupted (that I ſay not quite altered) from the practice of the Apoſtles, and the Church in former dayes, when <hi>no puniſhment was impoſed without great la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentation of the multitude, and greater of the better ſort,</hi> ſaith the<note n="a" place="margin">Lib. <hi>4.</hi> p. <hi>330.</hi>
               </note> Author of the Hiſtory of the Councell of Trent; which he doth prove from thoſe expreſſions of the Apoſtle,<note n="b" place="margin">1 Cor. 5.</note> 
               <hi>Ye have not lamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, to ſeparate ſuch an one from among you.</hi> And<note n="x" place="margin">2 Cor. 12.</note> 
               <hi>I feare that at my coming I ſhall lament many of thoſe who have ſinned before.</hi> But as for thoſe amongſt us which have challenged this power, and ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken it into their hands, they have rather carried themſelves like <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lomons</hi> foole or mad-man, which caſteth arrowes, firebrands and death, and yet ſaith, Am I not in ſport. Concerning this, you are not ignorant what <hi>Hierome</hi> ſaid of old,<note n="y" place="margin">Presbytero li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cet, ſi peccave<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ro, tradere me Satanae. in Ep. ad Heliod.</note> 
               <hi>A Preſbyter may deliver me to Satan if I offend.</hi> However this power hath been by the Prelates wreſted out of the hands of Presbyters, yet there have not been wanting thoſe, who, when Prelates were in the height of all their pride, and darted out their thunderbolts as it pleaſed them, have maintained that the power of denouncing and executing that ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence did belong to the Presbyters. I will only produce a witneſſe or two in this, and proceed.<note n="z" place="margin">Defenſor pacis part. <hi>2.</hi> cap. <hi>15.</hi> pag. <hi>256.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Marſilius Patavinus</hi> diſputing concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the order of Prieſthood, or of a Presbyter (for they are all one) and the power of the Keyes to binde and looſe, obſerveth out of the forementioned Father, <hi>the Church hath theſe Keyes in the Preſby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters and Biſhops,</hi> and gives this reaſon why <hi>Hierome</hi> ſpeaking of this power of the Keyes, doth mention Presbyters before the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops,<note n="a" place="margin">Preponens in boc pretbyteros, quoniam au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritas baec d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>betur presbytero in quantum presbyter, primò &amp; ſecundum quod ipſum.</note> 
               <hi>becauſe this authoritie belongs to a Preſbyter as a Preſbyter primarily and properly.</hi> From the ſame Authour I firſt tooke notice of this,<note n="b" place="margin">Cap <hi>6</hi> pag. <hi>165</hi> in init.</note> albeit <hi>Timothy</hi> (a Biſhop as our Hierarchiſts ſay) was then at Corinth when the Apoſtle gives charge to excom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municate the inceſtuous perſon, yet we heare not a word of com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand to the Biſhop to doe it, but a mandate unto others. <hi>When ye are gathered together, and my ſpirit, with the power of the Lord Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt, to deliver ſuch an one unto Satan.</hi> The charge is given to the Presbyters of Corinth, it was not the act of one, but <hi>of</hi>
               <note n="c" place="margin">2 Cor 2.6.</note> 
               <hi>many</hi> who did denounce and execute the ſentence on him. Had it been
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:111196:33"/>proper to a Biſhop S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
               <hi>Paul</hi> would not have ſo much forgotten him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, as to lay the blame and burthen upon others, and omit the men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of him. I finde alſo that<note n="d" place="margin">Gloſ. in cauſ. <hi>2</hi> q. <hi>1.</hi> ca. <hi>11.</hi> verbo Excommuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cet. Eccleſiarum praelati de jure communi poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſunt excommunicare, licet epiſcopi jam prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcripſerint contra multos praelatos.</note> 
               <hi>Bartholo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maeus Brixnienſis</hi> and <hi>Johannes Semeca</hi> both Gloſſators of the Canon Law, doe maintaine and prove even out of it, that <hi>by right Preſbyters may excommunicate, though the Biſhops by cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome and Preſcription have taken the power out of their hands.</hi> The ſame Interpreters of the Canon Law agree in this alſo.<note n="e" place="margin">Non debet Epiſcopus revocare ſententias ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>communicationis juſtè lat as ab eorum praelatis, ſine corum conſenſit. Gloſſ. in diſt. <hi>50.</hi> cap <hi>64.</hi> verb. injungere.</note> 
               <hi>A Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop ought not to revoke the ſentence of excommunication which a Prieſt hath on juſt ground pronounced, without the Prieſts conſent which did pronounce it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By this which hath been ſpoken, it is evident I hope, that though there were a Primacy granted, yet at firſt the Biſhop had no Supe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rioritie of power, much leſſe was the power of Ordination or Juriſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction put into his hands alone: you are not ignorant that <hi>Calvin, Bucer, Bullinger,</hi> and <hi>Zanchie</hi> have maintained that the Biſhop was at firſt no other then a Preſident of the Presbytery, his Act and Office in their meeting, as of the Conſul in the Senate, to propound matters, to gather votes, and declare the reſolutions of the Presby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terie: With what ſcorn this is rejected by our Epiſcopall Monarches you all know, as if they were the meere fancies of <hi>Calvins</hi> braine, and the teſtimonie of the reſt (which confirme their aſſertions by pregnant paſſages out of antiquitie) ſlighted, becauſe they are Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plinarians of the Geneva cut. If Proteſtant Divines be not regar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, let us ſee whether the judgement of a Fryer, and conſent of a Jeſuite, will be of more weight with our Prelates, there is good rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon to expect it, conſidering that Papiſts and Prelates were ſo linked together in their votes, (whileſt they had any) Jeſuites and Biſhops are at this day (as all the world ſeeth) ſo neerly conjoyned in their deſignes. The Fryer is <hi>Petrus Suavis</hi> that Hiſtorian of note, who diſcourſing at large touching the Originall of Epiſcopall power, and Church cenſures, as they were anciently adminiſtred, tels us,<note n="f" place="margin">Hiſt. of the Councell of Trent. <hi>lib.</hi> 4. <hi>p.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>3<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> 
               <hi>The judgement of the Church, as is neceſſary in every multitude was to be conducted by one, who ſhould preſide and guide the action, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe the matters, and collect the points to be conſulted on. This care due to the more principall and worthy perſon, was alwayes commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:111196:33"/>to the Biſhop.</hi> Judge now, I pray you, Fathers and Brethren, whether this be any more then to be a Preſident of the Presbyterie, or Senate Eccleſiaſticall. How the Biſhops power came afterwards to be ampliated, you ſhall there finde ſet forth to the full; the paſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges are all of them too large for me to repeat, or tranſcribe; they are worth his reading that ſhall take paines to peruſe them. I ſhall only mention one,<note n="g" place="margin">Ibid. pa. <hi>331.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>The goodneſſe and charity of the Biſhops</hi> (mark this, I pray you, he doth not ſay the Superioritie and power, but the goodneſſe and charity of the Biſhops) <hi>made their opinion for the moſt part to be followed, and by little and little was the cauſe that the Church, charity waxing cold, and not regarding the charge laid upon them by Christ, did leave the care to the Biſhop; and ambition a witty paſſion, which doth inſinuate it ſelfe in the ſhew of vertue, did cauſe it to be readily embraced.</hi> This and much more that Fryer in the ſame place. The Jeſuite is <hi>Salmeron,</hi> who expoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding the words of the Apoſtle to <hi>Titus,</hi> I left thee in Creete to or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dain Elders in every City, poſitively affir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth<note n="h" place="margin">Nec hoc loco permiſit Paulus Tito ut praefi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>at omnibus eccleſiis miniſtros: baec enim regia eſſet poteſtas, &amp; ju<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> eligendi tolleretur eccleſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>is,&amp; Paſtorum collegto judicium adimeretur. Sed hoc tantum jubet Apoſtotus ut omnibus ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctionibus praeſit tanquam moderator, &amp; electos orat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>one, jejunio, &amp; impoſitione manuum con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecrare<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> habes, <hi>Act. 6. 13, 14.</hi> Ob id enim Titum priùs à ſe ordinatum Epiſcopum reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quit, ut alios ipſe conſtitueret: ſicut d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>itur Conſul aut Dictator Conſutes alios creaſse, quia Comitia de eis eligendis babuerunt, Salm. in <hi>Tit. 1</hi> diſp. <hi>1.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Paul did not in that place permit Titus alone to ſet Ministers over the Churches, for this were to invest him with a Kingly power, and by this meanes the right of Election ſhould be taken a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way from the Churches, and the judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment ſhould be taken away from the Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of Pastors. But the Apoſtle doth on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly command him this that he ſhould be Preſident at all elections as a Moderator, that he ſhould by prayer, faſting, and Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition of hands conſecrate thoſe that were choſen, as the Apoſtles themſelves did,</hi> Act. 6.13, 14. <hi>For this cauſe did he leave Titus, or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained a Biſhop formerly, that he ſhould ordain others, as the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſul or Dictator is ſaid to create Conſuls, becauſe they held the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitia, the Aſſemblies for the election and creation of them.</hi> This being a truth ſo cleare, confirmed, as you ſee, by teſtimonies on all hands, I wonder with what face it is ſpoken againſt,<note n="i" place="margin">Epiſc. by div. right. <hi>pa.</hi> 120.</note> and another paſſage out of <hi>Hicrome, Tanquam imperator in exercitu,</hi> as the Generall in the Army, brought in <hi>obtorto collo</hi> quite againſt the haire. For <hi>Hierome</hi>
               <note n="k" place="margin">In Epiſt. ad Evagr.</note> in that place ſpeaks not concerning the power
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:111196:34"/>which the Biſhop had over the Presbyters, but concerning the man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of his prelation, to wit, by the free election of the Presbyters of Alexandria, who did chooſe one out of their own company, whom they placed in an higher degree, and called Biſhop. This forme of prelation, by election, he doth there illuſtrate by two examples, 1.<note n="l" place="margin">Quomodo ſi exercitus impe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ratorem ſactat, aut Diacone eligant de ſe quem induſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um noverint, &amp; Arcbidiaconum vocent. ibid.</note> Of ſouldiers in an army making choiſe of a Generall and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mander in chiefe over them; but the Father doth not ſay the Biſhop carried himſelfe as a Generall in an army, or had power given him anſwerable to the power of a Generall. Nay on the contrary he tels the Biſhops in plain termes they<note n="m" place="margin">Sicut ergo Presbyteri ſciunt ſe ex eccleſiae conſuetudine, ei qui ſibi praepoſitus ſuerit ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jectos eſſe: ita Epiſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>opi nover<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> ſo magis con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuetudine, quam diſpoſitionis Domini<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ae verita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te Presby<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>u eſſe majores: &amp; in communi de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bere Eccleſiam regere: in Epiſt ad Titum. ca. <hi>1.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>ought to governe the Church by the common counſell of the Preſbyters, above whom they are by the custome of the Church ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vanced.</hi> 2. He inſtanceth in the fact of Deacons, making choiſe of one whom they know to be induſtrious, and ſet him to be Arch-deacon over them. This latter paſſage is cunningly omitted, the former miſalleadged and fraudulently perverted, becauſe the one cuts the comb of Epiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>copall Dominion, the other, as it is wreſted, ſeemeth at firſt ſight to uphold or favour it. Indeed the execution of Martiall Law hath well pleaſed them which are now turned Martialiſts. It is too well known how they have hang'd up Miniſters <hi>ad placitum</hi> at their pleaſure, by their ſuſpenſions, excommunications, deprivations,<note n="n" place="margin">Conc. Hiſp. <hi>2.</hi> act. <hi>6.</hi> ap. cent. Magd<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>cent. <hi>7.</hi> cap <hi>9.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>by a tyrannicall power, not canonicall authority,</hi> as was complained of old againſt ſome Prelates, in the ſecond Councell of <hi>Hiſpalis.</hi> But <hi>ab initio non fuit ſic,</hi> from the beginning it was not ſo. The Colledge of Presbyters granted unto the Biſhop the chiefeſt ſeat in their publike meetings, and gave honour to him as to their Senior, and he was commanded to carry himſelf towards them as toward his Colleagues, by the<note n="o" place="margin">Epiſcopus in quolibet loco ſedens ſtare Preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terum non patiatur, Conc Carth. <hi>4.</hi> can. <hi>34.</hi> E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſcopus in eccleſia &amp; conſeſſu presbuterorum ſublimior ſedeat, Intra domum verò collegam ſe Presbyterorum cognoſcat. can. <hi>35.</hi> ap Grat diſt. <hi>95.</hi>
               </note> Canons of the fourth Councell of Carthage, unto which Canons regiſtred by <hi>Gratian</hi> this Summarie or ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle is prefixed,<note n="p" place="margin">Epiſcopus non dominum, ſed Collegam ſe presby<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>erorum cognoſeat</note> 
               <hi>Let the Biſhop know that he is not a Lord over, but Colleague of the Preſbyters.</hi> In this regard in the ſame Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noniſt, the<note n="q" place="margin">Epiſcopi ſe ſacerdotes eſſe noverint non do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minos, bonorent clericos quaſi clericos, ut &amp; it ſis à clericis quaſi epiſcopis honos. eſeratur, Grat. diſt <hi>95.</hi> ca. Eſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o ſubjectus ex Hier. ad Nepot. epiſt. <hi>2.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Biſhops are commanded to ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour their Clergy as Clergy-men, that ſo
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:111196:34"/>the Clergy may reciprocally honour them as their Biſhops.</hi> And the forementioned<note n="r" place="margin">Hoc eſt contra ſupercilium Epiſcoporum, qui ſubdiros appellant ſi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ios, cum debeant cos appel. lare fratres. Cauſ. <hi>8.</hi> q. <hi>1.</hi> cap. Quid autem. vol ſoci<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s cauſ. <hi>10</hi> q. <hi>3.</hi> cap. Cavendum. Gloſſ. in verb. quaſi clerices.</note> Gloſſator <hi>Semeca</hi> hath obſerved that <hi>this doth ſharply reprove the pride of thoſe Biſhops who account them their ſubjects and underlings, whom they ought to reckon of and call their bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, and companions.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Laſt of all, when the Biſhop began to be diſtinguiſhed in name from the Presbyters, and the forementioned Preſidentſhip and Priority was granted him, yet was he not thereby advanced to an order diſtinct from, and ſuperior to the order of Presbyters, but only to an higher degree in that Order. This is cleare by this, that at the firſt diſtinction of a Biſhop from the Presbyters, there was no new conſecration or ordination of the Biſhop. <hi>Antonius de Dominis,</hi> a man Prelaticall enough, doth confeſſe, induced thereunto by the cleare teſtimonie of <hi>Ambroſe,</hi>
               <note n="ſ" place="margin">De rep. eccl. lib. <hi>3.</hi> cap. <hi>3.</hi> n. <hi>2.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>at the beginning, whenſoever a Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop dyed, and the Epiſcopall throne was vacant, there was not ſo much as an election of him that was to ſucceed</hi> (much leſſe any new ordination) <hi>but the eldeſt Preſbyter came proſently in the roome of the deceaſed Biſhop.</hi> The words of <hi>Ambroſe</hi> are expreſſe for it.<note n="t" place="margin">Primi pretby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teri Epiſcopi appellabautur, ut recedente co, ſequent ei ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cederet. in <hi>4</hi> ca. ad Eph.</note> 
               <hi>The first Preſbyters were called Biſhops, ſo as that when he</hi> (to wit the firſt or eldeſt Presbyter) <hi>departed, the next did ſucceed him.</hi> Thus it was at firſt, the reaſon why this order was changed, that Epiſcopacie ſhould be conferred by Election, not by Succeſſion, is there given by the ſame Father.<note n="*" place="margin">Quia caperunt ſequentes Presbyteri indigul inveniri ad primatus tenendes, immatata eſt ratio, proſpiciente Concilie, ut non ordo ſed me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritum crearet Epiſcopum, multerum Sacerdo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum judlcio conſtitutum, ne indigum temer<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> uſurparer, &amp; eſſet multis ſcanlalum. id. ibid.</note> 
               <hi>Becauſe the Preſbyters which followed were found unworthy to hold that Primacy, the man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of prelation was purpoſely changed, that worth not order ſhould make a Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop, being appointed by the judgement of many Preſbyters, leſt an unworthy perſon ſhould raſhly uſurpe the place and honour, and ſo prove ſcandalous to many.</hi> Yet did he that was named the Biſhop remain ſtill a Preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byter, as the ſame<note n="u" place="margin">Poſt Epiſcopum diaconi ordinationem ſubji<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cit. Quare? niſi quia Epiſcopi &amp; diaconi una ordinatio eſt, uter<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> enim eſt ſacerdes, ſed Epiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>copus primus; ut omnis Epiſcopus Presbyter ſit, non omnis Presbyter Epiſcopus Hic enim Epiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>copus eſt, qui inter Presbyteres primus. Ambr. in <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Tim.</hi> cap. <hi>3.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Ambroſe</hi> teſtifieth, though he was accounted the Biſhop who was the firſt of the Presbyters, and in that reſpect the chiefeſt. As for the Biſhops of Alexandria, they had no other Ordination
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:111196:35"/>then the free election of their Presbyters, as is evident from the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly alleadged paſſages of<note n="*" place="margin">In Epiſt. ad Evagr.</note> 
               <hi>Hierome.</hi> Whence our learned and la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>borious <hi>Willet</hi> doth acknowledge,<note n="x" place="margin">Syn. Papiſ. cont. <hi>5.</hi> q. <hi>3.</hi> p. <hi>177.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>the ſpeciall conſecration of Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops was ordained only for the dignitie of that calling.</hi> So that what was in the firſt inſtitution of it deviſed and ordained meerly for the dignitie and honour of that Epiſcopall function, that is<note n="y" place="margin">
                  <hi>Epiſc.</hi> by div. light. <hi>pag.</hi> 105.</note> now made uſe of as an argument to prove from thence a diſtinction of order. In a word<note n="z" place="margin">De Invent. ver. l. <hi>4.</hi> cap. <hi>6.</hi> p. <hi>276.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Polydore Virgil</hi> doth confeſſe, that <hi>anciently in the conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crating of a Biſhop, there were no other ceremonies then theſe that the people met together to give their testimonie and ſuffrage in the Election, both Miniſters and people did pray, and the Preſbyters gave impoſition of hands.</hi> Which doth manifeſtly prove that both Biſhop and Presbyter were one order not diſtinct, even then when there was in ſome reſpects a difference made between them. And long after this diſtinction began,<note n="a" place="margin">Iohannes Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſienſis in lib. depoteſtate re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> &amp; Papali, quem So<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>bona approbavit, aſſicaat Presbyte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ros non eſſe Pontiſiribus inferiores, quod ad eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentralem miniſterii dignitatem attinet. Id<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> conſirmat ratione hac, quod eorum ordinatio conſlet iiſdem verbis quibus &amp; Epiſcooporum, &amp; Apoſtolorum, viz. Accipite Sp ſanctam. &amp; Quodcun<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> tigaveritis in terra, erit ligatum in c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</hi> Teſte D. Pleſſeo libd<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> eccl. ca <hi>12.</hi> p <hi>252.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Johannes Pariſienſis</hi> in a treatiſe of his concerning the power of the King and of the Pope (which was approved by the <hi>Sorbon</hi> of <hi>Paris</hi>) maintains that Preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byters are not inferior to Biſhops, which he doth prove by this, they have one and the ſame ordination, as that noble French<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man <hi>Philip Morney</hi> hath obſerved. Now admit we yeeld unto our Hierarchiſts, that the Angel here ſpoken of is in the forementioned ſenſe and kinde a Biſhop, the Senior of the Presbyters, and Preſident of the Presbyterie, as<note n="b" place="margin">In locum.</note> 
               <hi>Beza</hi> taketh it, and<note n="c" place="margin">Conference with <hi>Hart, ch.</hi> 8. <hi>div.</hi> 3. <hi>p.</hi> 535.</note> Doctor <hi>Reinolds,</hi> whoſe judgement of this place the Archbiſhop of Armagh hath publiſhed with ſome additions of his own out of antiquity; yet what is all this to a Biſhop in order diſtinguiſhed from, and ſuperior in power to the Presbyters. Our learned country<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man D<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>Reinolds</hi> doth not ſay, that this Angel or Preſident of the Presbyterie was ſuch a Biſhop, nor doth the Reverend Primate of Armagh ſay that he was of a different order; but only that the name of Biſhop was limited to him that had the Preſidentſhip. Who that was hath been expreſſed before by the clear teſtimonie of <hi>Ambroſe,</hi> to which <hi>Auſtin</hi> doth agree,<note place="margin">Tom. <hi>4.</hi> queſt. exutroq. mix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>m cap. <hi>101.</hi>
               </note> ſaying, <hi>Quid eſt epiſcopus, niſi primus Preſbyter, hoc eſt ſummus ſacerdos?</hi> Much leſſe doth D<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>Reinolds</hi> affirme that he which had the Preſident<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hip had it by divine right, or undertake to prove or inferre from hence a diſtinction in Order
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:111196:35"/>between a Biſhop and a Presbyter by the word of God; for if ſo he ſhould contradict himſelf, having expreſſed his judgement to the contrary, and proved it both by Scriptures, and by variety of other authors<note n="*" place="margin">In his letter to Sir <hi>Francis Knollys,</hi> which was reprinted about the ſame time that the Archbiſhop of Armagh publi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed this piece of D<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                  <hi>Reinolds</hi> with his own Additions.</note> Whether this be not a weak inference, or rather a ſtrange <hi>Non ſequitur;</hi> The Angel of Epheſus was a Preſident of the Presby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terie of Epheſus, therefore he was a Biſhop differenced in order from and ſuperior in power to the Presbyters of Epheſus, let any reaſona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble man judge. It is well known that the Speakers of both Houſes of Parliament are Preſidents, as it were, yet not by their Preſidentſhip advanced to an higher order, the one is a Peere, the other a Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moner, though as Speakers they are in ſome ſort differenced from the Peeres and Commons. The Prolocutor in a Convocation as it ſtood formerly was by order a Clarke, and no more, though as Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>locutor he had a Preſidentſhip over the Clarks of the Convocation. Such was the preeminence of him that was Preſident of the Presby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tery. In which regard <hi>Beza,</hi> though he grant the Angel here to be the Preſident, yet might juſtly and on good ground maintain,<note n="d" place="margin">Hinc ſtatui epiſcopalis ille gradus poſteae humanltùs in eccleſiam Dei invectus, certè nec poteſt nec debet. Beza in loc.</note> 
               <hi>that from hence that Epiſcopall degree, which was afterwards by men brought into the Church of God, neither may nor ought to be eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhed.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus have you, Fathers and Brethren, ſome of my thoughts con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning this argument of Epiſcopacie, contracted into as narrow a compaſſe as I could. Wherein I have endeavoured to prove, that the Angel in my text is not a Biſhop diſtinct from a Presbyter in Order, Office, and fixed Superiority, and ſo to diſprove their Inſtitution <hi>de Jure divino.</hi> Concerning which their pretended originall, I cannot but aſſent unto the judgement of a learned Divine amongſt us, one that is well known to be a man of great reading, and inſight in anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity, as alſo to be no Puritan,<note n="e" place="margin">M. S. deſchiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mate.</note> 
               <hi>They but abuſe themſelves and others, that would perſwade us that Biſhops by Chriſts Institution have any Superioritie over other men, farther then of reverence, or that any Biſhop is ſuperior to another further then poſitive order agreed upon amongst Chriſtians hath preſcribed. For we have be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeved him that taught us, that in Christ Jeſus there is neither high nor low, and in giving honour every man ſhould preſerre ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther before himſelf: which ſayings moſt excellently cut off all claim to ſuperiority, by title of Chriſtianity, except we can think theſe things were ſpoken to poore and private men. Nature and Religion
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:111196:36"/>agree in this, that neither of them hath an hand in this heraldry of</hi> Secundum, ſub &amp; ſupra. <hi>All this comes from compoſition and agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of men amongst themſelves. Wherfore this abuſe of Chriſtia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, to make it a Lackey to ambition, is a vice for which I have no extraordinary name of Ignominie, and an ordinary I will not give it, lest you ſhould take ſo tranſcendent a vice to be but triviall.</hi> Thus the forementioned Divine clearly overthrowing their ſuperio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity by Divine right; from which if our Prelaticall men be beaten, let them not wonder that they ſhould be caſhiered as Uſurpers and Intruders. For, not to inſiſt on their doome out of the book of God, we will be content to take them at their owne word, if they dare ſtand to it, and let them have their option. You know what a Bravado the Humble Remonſtrant hath made, as being willing to put it to this iſſue, <hi>if they be not able to prove their Divine Inſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tution, they are content to be hiſſed out of all Christian Congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gations.</hi> The like brag and challenge is made by a late<note n="f" place="margin">Biſhop <hi>Hall, part.</hi> 2. §. 10. <hi>p.</hi> 129.</note> Patron of Epiſcopacie, who ſeemeth to be very neere of kinne to the Remon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrant in confidence and ſilken language. As for continuance in their places and dignities <hi>Jure humano</hi> by the Law of man. Firſt, of all they ſcorne (you ſee, and all the world knowes it) that tenure, and therefore it is not fit that they ſhould have the benefit of it. Second<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, Though they ſhould be willing to ſtick to it, yet it is neither con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venient nor neceſſary, that they ſhould here plead cuſtome and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcription, at leaſtwiſe that the plea ſhould be in force inviolably a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt an alteration. <hi>Ludovicus Arelatenſis</hi> in his ſpeech againſt <hi>Panormitan</hi> in the Councell of Baſil having proved out of the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers that by the Word of God there is no difference between a Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop and a Presbyter, hath foretold the<note n="g" place="margin">Si pront Hie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ronymo placet, Epiſcopt ſunt ſola confuetudi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne praelati preſ. byteris, uti<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> fie ri poteſt ut con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuetudinem tol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tat contraria conſuetudo. Aen. Syl lib. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> de geſt. con<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſil. ap Orth. Gra. in faſcia rer. ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pet. fol. <hi>12.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Poſſibility of changing this frame of government brought into the Church meerly by cuſtome.</hi> Eſpecially when the inconveniencies of that cuſtome, which came in by degrees, and was embraced at firſt under a plauſible pretence of good and benefit, ſhall be diſcovered, and the burthen of it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come inſufferable. This is that which <hi>Beza</hi> doth intimate upon my text, that the <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> or Preſident ſhould not have been perpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall; however<note n="h" place="margin">
                  <hi>Biſhop</hi> Hall, loc. cit p. <hi>125.</hi>
               </note> one of late looking on his words with an Epiſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pall paire of ſpectacles, bleſſeth himſelfe at the reading of them, as if ſome foul feind or other did fright him, threatning to pull the Mytre off his head, the Rochet off his backe, and wreſt the Crozier
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:111196:36"/>Staffe out of his hands. Let the impartiall and unprejudicated Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der peruſe his<note n="i" place="margin">Imòne perpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuum quidem i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtud <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> munm eſſe neceſſariò oportuiſſe, ſicut exortae inde <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>yrannis ol<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>garchica (oujus apex eſt Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cbriſtians beſtia) certiſſima cuns totius non ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiae <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>do, ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rbis pernicie, nunc tandem declarat. Bez. in Ap<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>c. <hi>2.1.</hi>
               </note> words, and if I miſtake not, you will finde no more but this, he ſhewes by the evil conſequents which followed, <hi>viz.</hi> the tyrannie of Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lates, and promotion of Antichriſt, to the ruine of the Church and confuſion of the whole world almoſt, which followed upon that perpetuall Preſidentſhip, that it ſhould not have been perpetu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all; he doth not queſtion whether it were perpetuall or not, nor ſay it was not, as the Prelate doth wreſt his words; but ſaith it appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth now at length it ought not to have been, for as much as it pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved in the end of ſuch dangerous conſequence, and ſo pernitious un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to both Church and States. If on the fore-mentioned, and other grounds which might be named, we all agree to renounce it, and caſt it off, we herein doe no more, then what we have a diſpenſation for from a great Maſter of the ceremonies (yet one whom for his lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, and elaborate paines againſt the Papiſts I ſhall ever honour) who, having maintained the Poſition of Proteſtants concerning the indiſtinction of a Biſhop and Presbyter by the Word of God, by the teſtimonies of Papiſts themſelves (as his uſuall courſe is) and vindi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cated it from the imputation of Aerianiſme and Hereſic<note n="k" place="margin">Abſit ut prax<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cam, quae ad tol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lendum ſchiſma inſtituta ſuit, per ſchiſma per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>runpere veli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus, &amp; non po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiùs cam ſancte &amp; humiliter colamus: dum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modo (quod in escleſia veſtr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Patres conci<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>orum gravitèr dolebant) ſchiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matis remedium non pariat ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nenum tyranni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dis Morto<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Apo. Cath. lib. <hi>1.</hi> cap. <hi>33.</hi> in ſine.</note>, doth in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed diſlike a ſchiſmaticall oppoſition againſt Epiſcopacy, and the practiſe of the Church therein, deſiring it ſhould be obſerved holily and with humility, yet with this Proviſo, <hi>So that the remedie of ſchiſme doe not produce the poyſon of tyrannie.</hi> So that by his own conceſſion, when once the remedie is turned into poyſon, and ſo be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come not only as bad, but alſo worſe then the diſeaſe, it is then by all means lawfull and poſſible to be expelled. If this ſatisfie not, but our Hierarchiſts will ſtill quarrell and complaine of ſchiſme, faction and diſorderly proceedings; I ſhall return them the ſame anſwer which D<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>Bilſon,</hi> a man ſufficiently Hierarchicall, gives the Jeſuites, who complained that matters of Religion were in Queene <hi>Elizabeths</hi> dayes eſtabliſhed by a Lay-Parliament (who were not to meddle with Church affaires) without conſent of the Prelates and their popiſh Clergie.<note n="l" place="margin">D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ffer. betvv. Chriſt. ſubject. &amp; unchriſt. re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bell. <hi>part.</hi> 3. <hi>p.</hi> 299. <hi>caii. Lond. an.</hi> 1586.</note> 
               <hi>The Chriſtian Princes, take which you will, that first received, and after wards reſtored the faith in their Empires and Kingdomes, tyed not themſelves to the voyces and ſuffrages of their Clergie which were in preſent poſſeſſion of their Churches,
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:111196:37"/>but eft-times removed them without counſell or common conſulta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</hi> And a little after, <hi>Why restraine you truth to the aſſemblies and ſentences of Popes and Prelates, as though they must be gently entreated and fairely offered by Chriſt, before he might attempt or ſhould recover his own.</hi> When the Jeſuites reply, <hi>We would have things done in order.</hi> The Doctor returneth them this anſwer, <hi>Call you that order where Chriſt ſhall ſtand without doores till your Clergie conſent to bring him in?</hi> Afterwards, when the Jeſuites urge a Commiſſion and lawfull authoritie;<note n="m" place="margin">Pag <hi>300.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>He that is ſent to preach</hi> (ſaith the Doctor) <hi>may not hold his tongue till my Lord the Pope</hi> (you may thinke if you pleaſe on him, who would faine be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>inveſted in that title, which once his Predeceſſor had, being accoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, <hi>alterius orbis Papa,</hi> the Pope of the other world) <hi>and his mytred fathers can intend to meet, and liſt to conſent to the ruine, as they coceive, of their dignities &amp; liberties. Deſpiſe you Councels?</hi> ſay the Jeſuites:<note n="n" place="margin">Pag. <hi>301.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>By no meanes,</hi> ſaith the D<hi rend="sup">r</hi>, <hi>ſo long as they be Councels, that is ſober &amp; free conferences of learned &amp; godly teachers: but if they waxe wanton againſt Christ, and will not have truth recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved till they have conſented,</hi> which is the diſpoſition of our Prelates and their adherents at this day, <hi>we reject them as conſpiracies of the wicked, which no Chriſtian ought to reverence.</hi> Thus farre Doctor <hi>Bilſon.</hi> The concluſion of <hi>Clemangiis</hi> in his complaint of the exorbitancies of Prelates ſhall cloſe up my diſcourſe,<note n="o" place="margin">Tract. de Prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ulib. Sim. in ſine. p. <hi>166.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Expergiſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re Domine tandem aliquando; Awake, O Lord, at length, looke downe upon us, pitty us and viſit thy Church with thy ſalvation. Heale her, for there is none but thou canst cure her, Powre into her wounds the wine of reproofe, and oyle of conſolation. Take thy fanne into thy hand, and throughly purge thy floore which is contaminated with ſo great, and ſuch impure defilements. Purge thy vineyard which is exceedingly over-growne with thornes. Make as of old a whip of ſmall cords, drive the money-changers out of the Temple, cast out the buyers and ſellers, and exterminate out of the limits of thy Church all the wicked merchants, unleſſe they repent, amend and reforme; Smite the Gehazites with lepro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie. Caſt downe and daſh in pieces the Simonites, with their master Simon, which are flowne ſo high, and by the miniſterie of Satan mounted up, ſo that none can pull them down unleſſe thou be pleaſed to doe it.</hi> Or if we muſt have an Engliſh Letanie to be uſed in all
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:111196:37"/>Collegiate and Cathedrall Churches and Chappels ſeeing our Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lates are grown ſo brazen-faced as to tell us, their Juriſdiction is no other but charitable,<note n="p" place="margin">
                  <hi>Epiſc.</hi> by div. right, <hi>p.</hi> 137.</note> 
               <hi>as charitie managed the cenſures before ſo charitie doth it ſtill;</hi> (yet I think you all know, and ſo doe others alſo, that their proceedings have been ſo charitable, that we may truly ſay of them, what once<note n="q" place="margin">Non ambigimus de rugitu Leonu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>, quando vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derimus Principes eccleſie ita in ſubditos po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulos detonare, &amp; vo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e tyrannica plebem conte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rere ut non paſtore mingrege, ſed Leonem inter oviculas putes frendere. Hier. in <hi>Zeph. 3.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Hierome</hi> did of the Biſhops in his dayes, <hi>they were more like to Lions roaring among the ſheep, then like ſhep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herds ſet over the flock;</hi> or what <hi>Didacus Stella</hi> of the Prelates in his time, when in charitie they have come to viſit,<note n="r" place="margin">Non eo ten lust animo (Praelati ad viſitan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum dioeceſos ſuos) ut infirmis medeantur, nec ut ſame pereuntes alique auxilio reſt aurentur, ſed ut eos exeuterent &amp; diviſcerent. Admodum ſimiles bi praelati ſunt reorum cuſtodibus, qui damnatos &amp; in carcere detentos viſitant, non ut aliquod ſolatii gonzs eis praeſtent, ſed ut do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lorem augeant, catenas at<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> compedes fortiùs comprimendo. It a nimirùm, &amp;c. Enar. in Luc. tom. <hi>2.</hi> in cap. <hi>10.</hi> p. <hi>5.</hi> edit. Antwerp. an. <hi>1622.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>they come as the Jaylor doth to viſit his Priſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, that he may extort his ſees, ſee whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther they be faſt bound or not, and to lay more bolts on their heeles</hi>) were I fit to give advice to ſo grave and learned an Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemblie, I ſhould deſire this might be one branch of the Letanie, if we have any: <hi>From Papall tyrannie, and Prelates Charitie, Good Lord deliver us.</hi> With this directo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie; Let all the people ſay, <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="errata">
            <head>Errata.</head>
            <p>PAge 3. in marg. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. <hi>ibid lin. ult.</hi> Clement. <hi>lege</hi> Clemangiis. <hi>p.</hi> 4. <hi>line</hi> 7. <hi>licae. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> loco. p.</hi> 14. <hi>l.</hi> 23 <hi>Hierodantia. l. Hierodoulia. p.</hi> 18. in morg. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. <hi>ibid. lia.</hi> 14 <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. <hi>p.</hi> 24. <hi>l.</hi> 26. Kingdome in. <hi>l.</hi> Kingdome of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven in. <hi>ib.</hi> in m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rg. <hi>San. l. Sum. lb. lin.</hi> 30. becauſe they are, they hold, <hi>l.</hi> becauſe they hold <hi>p.</hi> 38. <hi>l.</hi> 12. doth neceſſarily, <hi>l.</hi> doth not neceſſarily.</p>
            <p>As for the reſt, if there be any literall miſtakes or ſuch like errours, the cour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous Reader will e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ly obſerve and correct them.</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
